<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikivoyage</sitename>
    <dbname>enwikivoyage</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.46.0-wmf.24</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="1728" case="first-letter">Event</namespace>
      <namespace key="1729" case="first-letter">Event talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ljubljana</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19931</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5218112</id>
      <parentid>5215177</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-25T09:31:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>2253620</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 0 sources and tagging 1 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.9.5</comment>
      <origin>5218112</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="111041" sha1="qz15d1xy27uka8z2e6c4lupzzhiaez5" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner |Ljubljana banner.jpg|unesco=yes|dotm=yes|unesco_cc=yes}}

'''Ljubljana''' ("lee-oo-blee-AH-nuh") is the small but delightful capital of [[Slovenia]]. While the city's population had grown to 295,500 in 2020, the sights and amenities are concentrated in the charming old centre. It's full of artists, museums, and galleries, it's friendly and easy to reach, and it's a good base for exploring the rest of the country.

==Understand==
[[File:Sl-Ljubljana.ogg]]
[[File:Ljubljana - Stari trg 4 (Valvasorjeva hiša).jpg | thumb | 300px | House on Stari Trg ]]
Ljubljana stands at the entrance to a plain in an otherwise mountainous region, the confluence of several river valleys, so it's been a focus for settlement, trade and transport since prehistory. The first known city was the Roman ''Colonia Iulia Aemona''; in medieval times it became '''Laibach''' and this name is still used by some German-speakers (as well as modern Slovenia's most notable cultural export, the band of that name). It fell under the gravity of Austria-Hungary and was a duchy or province of the Habsburg Empire until 1918. For much of the 20th century it was part of Yugoslavia until independence in 1991. This means that Ljubljana has simply been a regional capital, and has only been the national capital of a relatively small country for a few decades. The city landscape reflects this: it's compact and walkable, cosy and friendly, rather than grandiose. There are no vast ceremonial boulevards, bling palaces or imperial fists of fortification. It's not a place where you hop around ticking off must-see sights, like a bug with a selfie-stick for antennae. Relax, stroll and enjoy the atmosphere.

No-one really knows how its current name came about: it resembles ''ljubljena'' - "beloved" - in Slovenian, but that seems to be just a happy coincidence. It sits in the valley of the Ljubljanica river, with green hills hemming it in on either side. The river makes a right angle, with the castle and oldest parts of the city on the hill in the southeast quadrant. A 19th century street grid extends north of the river, then the modern town sprawls to the west and north. Three natural disasters shaped the city architecture. An earthquake of 1511 caused extensive re-building in Renaissance style, and in stone to curb the fires of the wooden city. Another earthquake in 1895 prompted rebuilding in Vienna Secession style. It was flooded by the river multiple times until the Gruber Canal was cut across the southeast quadrant in the 18th century, turning the castle hill into an island. Therefore the main flow bypasses the old centre, which was protected from the devastating 2010 floods of the Danube catchment region. The "Triple" and "Dragon" bridges stand intact as proud symbols of Ljubljana.

Ljubljana is a year-round destination but you need to dress for the Balkan climate. Summers are warm, with daytime highs of 30°C. There are often public events and festivals, with streets converted from traffic thoroughfares to event spaces, but afternoons can be humid with thunderstorms and downpours. Early summer and autumn enjoy more even temperatures, and there's a student buzz as the university is in session. In winter it's near-zero, often with snow, and biting winds off the hills, but as Christmas approaches the streets are decorated by thousands of lights, and food and drink kiosks pop up along the river bank. February is grey, before in spring the city blooms with flowers planted on its streets and crossroads. 

* {{listing
| name=Ljubljana Tourist Information Centre | alt= | url=http://www.visitljubljana.com | email=tic@visitljubljana.si
| address=Stritarjeva | lat=46.050871 | long=14.506462 | directions=next to the Triple Bridge
| phone=+386 1 306-4583 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 08:00-20:00, Sa Su 10:00-18:00 | price=
| content=Also offers three sightseeing tours in the summer at 10:00, 14:00, and 17:00 for €10. There are nice souvenirs and a free map.
}}

==Talk==
The main language of the city is unsurprisingly [[Slovenian]]. Bosnian, Croatian, and Serbian are becoming less understood by young people, while older people typically speak them fluently. Most inhabitants of Ljubljana speak English, especially people under the age of 40, with some of them also being able to speak German, Italian, French, Spanish and/or Russian. It's worth trying any major European language you speak.

==Get in==

===By plane===
* {{go
| name=Jože Pučnik Airport | alt=Brnik Airport {{IATA|LJU}} | url=https://www.lju-airport.si/en/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.224444 | long=14.456111 | directions=27 km north of Ljubljana
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Ljubljana Jože Pučnik Airport | image=Ljubljana Airport with mountains and Adria Airways planes 2015.jpg | wikidata=Q1109558
| lastedit=2021-07-13
| content=This airport has flights from [[Amsterdam Schiphol]], [[Brussels Airport]] and Charleroi, [[Paris Charles de Gaulle]], Belgrade, Niš, London ([[Heathrow]], [[Gatwick]] and Luton), [[Frankfurt Airport]], [[Munich Airport]], [[Helsinki Airport]], [[Madrid Barajas]], Warsaw, Podgorica, [[Zurich Airport]], [[Tel Aviv Ben Gurion Airport]] and Istanbul, plus seasonal flights to the Med. A new Terminal A opened in June 2021 and serves all regularly scheduled flights. It's connected by a short corridor to the old Terminal B, now used for charter flights. Both have the usual airport facilities, see map on website, but B is small and frankly tatty. There are over a dozen car rental agents, with all the big names represented.
}}

[[File:Ljubljana bus station - platform 28.jpg | thumb | 300px | Stand 28 for the bus to the airport ]]
[[File:Avtobusne povezave z letališča Jožeta Pučnika 2023.jpg|thumb|Buses timetable from Jože Pučnik Airport to Ljubljana in 2023]]
[[File:Avtobusne povezave do letališča Jožeta Pučnika 2023.jpg|thumb|Buses from Ljubljana bus station to Jože Pučnik Airport in 2023]]
'''Getting there and away''':
* '''By bus''':
:* [https://arriva.si/en/ Arriva Bus] takes 50 min to the main bus and railway station ("Ljubljana AP", Stand 28), with several stops. It runs every 30 min M-F 05:20-20:10, and Sa Su holidays 06:10–19:10. The fare is €4.10, pay the driver on boarding; cannot pay with the city Urbana card. (May 2023)
:* From the airport, cross to the parking lot. To the right is the bus stop for Arriva Bus. €4.00, cash only.
:* Bus route 64 (LPP) goes from Ljubljana bus station ("Ljubljana AP", Stand 28). The fare is €4.10, can pay with Urbana card or Visa/Mastercard (Jan 2026).
:* Outbound from the city, alternate buses continue from the airport to [[Bled]], so this has an hourly service taking 30 min. Morning buses that continue to Bled may fill up.
:* A bus to [[Kranj]] runs every hour or two, taking 20-40 min. 

* '''By shuttle''' – Several operators offer shuttle transfers, which are {{EUR|12|when=2023-05-26}} per person, more for a door-to-door private transfer. They include [https://www.goopti.com/en/ Goopti], [https://shuttle.nomago.si/ Nomago], [https://www.airportljubljana.co/ Airtrail Slovenia] and [https://tuamv.com/ TuamV].
* '''By taxi''' – You might pay around €50 for a metered taxi to the city.
* '''By car''' – See airport website for the many car hire agencies. Driving off, follow the one-way system and go west then left onto the link road, which gets you on A2 towards Ljubljana.

'''Other airports''' nearby that but might prove convenient are [[Trieste#By plane|Trieste]], [[Venice#By plane|Venice]] Marco Polo, and [[Treviso#By plane|Treviso]] (in Italy); [[Vienna Airport]], [[Klagenfurt#By plane|Klagenfurt]], and [[Graz#By plane|Graz]] (in Austria); and [[Zagreb#By plane|Zagreb]] (in Croatia).

=== By train ===
[[File:Ljubljana train station interior.jpg | thumb | 300px | Inside the railway station]]
* {{go
| name=Ljubljana railway station | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=1 km north of the river, with the bus station on its south flank.
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1817806
| lastedit=2023-04-25
| content=There are a number of ticket machines around the station. Access to most of the platforms is a relatively long way from the booking hall.
}}

Slovenian Railways website is [https://potniski.sz.si/en/ here] .  For at least some routes, tickets can be purchased in advance at the OEBB 'Scotty' web site.  (https://fahrplan.oebb.at/webapp/#!P|TP!H|373191) 

International train tickets will need to be purchased at the ticket desk in the station. Domestic tickets can be purchased from ticket machines in the station or website. Note that on certain classes of trains, e.g. IC (intercity), there is a surcharge included in the ticket price if you travel on the train you booked. Domestic tickets may be issued on a IJPP card that can be reused. There are weekend tickets with a 75% discount can only be purchased with a IJPP card. These cards can be obtained from ticket desks.

The railway station was under construction in late October, 2025.  Travelers may want to allow an extra ten minutes to find their platform.

International Connections:
* Trains from [[Munich]] take 6 hr 15 min, with one direct and one changing daytime service and one sleeper, via [[Salzburg]], [[Villach]] and Lesce (for [[Bled]]), and dividing at Ljubljana for [[Rijeka]] or [[Zagreb]]. In early 2021 this route was disrupted by engineering works in the tunnel near Villach, but is now normal. From Paris and points north travel via Munich.

* Trains from [[Vienna]] take 6 or 7 hours; most involve a change but there is one direct service via [[Semmering]], [[Graz]], [[Maribor]] and Zidani Most.

* Trains from [[Budapest]] run daily, taking 7 hr 30 min via Zidani Most. Connections taking 9 hours are available hourly. 

* Trains from [[Zagreb]] run 4 or 5 times a day, taking 2 hr 30 min via Dobova (the border) and Zidani Most.

* Trains from [[Rijeka]] run twice a day, taking 3 hours via [[Opatija]], and being joined at Ljubljana onto the Munich train.

* Trains from [[Trieste]] run twice a day, taking 2 hr 30 min via Villa Opicina on the border. From elsewhere in Italy change at Trieste, the direct train from Venice has been axed.

===By bus===
* {{go
| name=Ljubljana bus station | alt=''avtobusna postaja'' | url=https://www.ap-ljubljana.si/en/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=next to the train station
| phone=090 934230 (domestic) | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q15972632
| lastedit=2023-04-25
| content=Has services throughout Slovenia, as well as to foreign countries. The station has several useful schedule search engines (also in English) for working out connections. Generally speaking, a bus can take you almost anywhere in Slovenia within a few hours. Tickets can also be bought on-line  using cards but they must be printed out before use. The bus station can do this for you and is a workaround for the fact that the bus station itself only accepts cash.
}}

Direct international connections: [[Trieste]] (2 hours), [[Zagreb]] (2 hours), [[Venice]] (4 hours), [[Banja Luka]] (5 hours), [[Bihać]] (6 hours), [[Bologna]] (6 hours), [[Budapest]] (6 hours), [[Munich]] (7 hours), [[Florence]] (8 hours), [[Tuzla]] (8 hours), [[Zenica]] (8 hours), [[Belgrade]] (8 hours), [[Ulm]] (9 hours), [[Stuttgart]] (10 hours), [[Sarajevo]] (10 hours), [[Niš]] (12 hours), [[Karlsruhe]] (12 hours), [[Mannheim]] (13 hours), [[Frankfurt]] (14 hours), [[Skopje]] (15 hours), [[Tetovo]] (16 hours), [[Sofia]] (16 hours), [[Pristina]] (18 hours), [[Copenhagen]] (19 hours), [[Malmö]] (20 hours), [[Gothenburg]] (24 hours), [[Linköping]] (28 hours), [[Örebro]] (34 hours), [[Stockholm]] (36 hours).

'''Left luggage''', available by asking at the ticket windows in the Bus Station for €3.50.

===By car===
[[File:Metelkova mesto 2017 048 (36587794042).jpg | thumb | 300px | Travel planning before the internet: Metelkova Art Centre is by the railway station]]
{{seealso|Brotherhood and Unity Highway}}
Ljubljana is at the centre of the Slovenian road network, which means that if you're not driving towards the border, you're approaching Ljubljana. Traffic can be frustrating at rush hours, but is generally lighter than in larger European capitals. Huge jams can occur if there's an accident or road works, though, so consult the [http://www.promet.si/portal/en/1traffic-conditions.aspx Traffic-information centre]{{Dead link|date=February 2026 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} or use a navigation app with traffic information.

There are several car parks throughout the city centre, and cheaper ones at the outskirts. Those offer day-long parking with return city bus ticket included in the price. Most car parks are operated by the [https://www.ljubljana.info/parking/ Municipal company]. Short-term street parking in blue zones is payable at parking meters scattered around (€1.30/hr in the city centre, 2 hours max; €0.50/hr further out, 3 hours max; Saturday afternoon and Sunday parking is free). Parking meters don't return change, but they also accept the Urbana card (see below). Payment is also possible with the Urbana ([https://apps.apple.com/us/app/urbana/id1608543324 iOS], [https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.margento.urbanaplus&amp;hl=en Android]) and [https://www.easypark.com/en-si EasyPark] apps.

Renting a car is also an option, especially to explore rural areas outside the city and during public holidays. The car sharing service [https://avant2go.si/en Avant2Go] has many pickup locations: Ljubljana, the airport, larger Slovenian cities, and Croatia and Austria. Prices start at €0.085/min plus €0.39/km or €39 for 24 hours.

===By ride sharing===
The main website is [https://prevoz.org Prevoz.org, (click on "mednarodni prevozi" for international rides)]{{cbignore}}. The website is only in Slovene, but simple enough to navigate. The columns are "from", "to", "time" (of departure) and "cost", you can sort them by clicking on top row, or use the search engine on top. You have to register to see the phone number, you can use an existing account. Most drivers would speak enough English to arrange the ride. Note however that there is no rating system in place, nor any payment system – you pay cash to the driver. Generally the price is around €5/100-120 km within Slovenia, usually a bit more abroad. If you're arriving in your own car and want to pick some passengers, you can of course also post it on the site.

=== Hitchhiking ===
Much of the country's traffic is either heading into Ljubljana or back out. Outbound you need to know the main hitching spots:
* '''Northeast''' to [[Maribor]] and Austria: on Dunajska cesta just west of the railway station, take Bus 6, 8 or 11 north to Smelt and the World Trade Centre, 15 min. Turn right and you'll see the entry ramp for Highway H3.
* '''Southwest''' to [[Koper]], [[Rijeka]] and Italy: on Dunajska cesta or Kongresni trg take Bus 6 south to the end of the line at Dolgi most. The highway is before you, with the entry ramp to A1 and A2 just left - it's A1 you want. You'll also see an entrance to the parking area of a house, stand there as vehicles are better able to pull in. 
* '''East''' to [[Novo Mesto]] and [[Zagreb]]: on Dunajska cesta take Bus 3 south to the end of the line at Rudnik. Walk on a further 200 m along Dolenjska cesta to the crossroads and entry ramp opposite the railway crossing. You want A2 eastbound.

==Get around==
{{Mapframe|46.049955|14.506408|zoom=14|width=520|height=560|layer=M|lang=en}}
{{Mapmask |46.1415,14.4696 |46.1416,14.4698 |46.1418,14.4702 |46.1422,14.4718 |46.1421,14.4719 |46.1417,14.4719 |46.1417,14.4718 |46.1411,14.4716 |46.1407,14.4718 |46.1407,14.4716 |46.1404,14.4721 |46.1402,14.4721 |46.1402,14.4723 |46.1404,14.4725 |46.1403,14.4727 |46.1401,14.4728 |46.1400,14.4728 |46.1400,14.4730 |46.1398,14.4731 |46.1398,14.4734 |46.1399,14.4736 |46.1389,14.4750 |46.1385,14.4752 |46.1382,14.4751 |46.1382,14.4752 |46.1377,14.4753 |46.1371,14.4745 |46.1370,14.4745 |46.1364,14.4750 |46.1363,14.4757 |46.1357,14.4759 |46.1368,14.4773 |46.1378,14.4787 |46.1377,14.4794 |46.1375,14.4795 |46.1374,14.4799 |46.1375,14.4800 |46.1371,14.4809 |46.1371,14.4812 |46.1372,14.4825 |46.1373,14.4833 |46.1376,14.4835 |46.1379,14.4841 |46.1384,14.4847 |46.1386,14.4852 |46.1389,14.4849 |46.1391,14.4849 |46.1401,14.4863 |46.1413,14.4868 |46.1415,14.4881 |46.1416,14.4890 |46.1414,14.4908 |46.1411,14.4910 |46.1414,14.4917 |46.1415,14.4925 |46.1417,14.4931 |46.1421,14.4938 |46.1420,14.4970 |46.1428,14.4973 |46.1427,14.4981 |46.1423,14.4986 |46.1423,14.4993 |46.1424,14.4996 |46.1423,14.5003 |46.1424,14.5009 |46.1427,14.5013 |46.1432,14.5024 |46.1441,14.5049 |46.1440,14.5052 |46.1448,14.5056 |46.1455,14.5055 |46.1460,14.5058 |46.1458,14.5071 |46.1451,14.5095 |46.1446,14.5105 |46.1439,14.5112 |46.1439,14.5117 |46.1439,14.5124 |46.1441,14.5138 |46.1430,14.5141 |46.1418,14.5147 |46.1413,14.5151 |46.1397,14.5139 |46.1390,14.5131 |46.1385,14.5139 |46.1379,14.5141 |46.1375,14.5146 |46.1372,14.5155 |46.1364,14.5164 |46.1362,14.5174 |46.1358,14.5184 |46.1341,14.5204 |46.1331,14.5203 |46.1328,14.5201 |46.1314,14.5197 |46.1312,14.5201 |46.1300,14.5207 |46.1287,14.5208 |46.1276,14.5213 |46.1273,14.5215 |46.1270,14.5221 |46.1266,14.5230 |46.1260,14.5235 |46.1256,14.5236 |46.1252,14.5243 |46.1253,14.5249 |46.1251,14.5257 |46.1248,14.5265 |46.1241,14.5277 |46.1239,14.5291 |46.1238,14.5294 |46.1237,14.5295 |46.1224,14.5294 |46.1221,14.5296 |46.1218,14.5300 |46.1217,14.5307 |46.1214,14.5311 |46.1211,14.5314 |46.1207,14.5319 |46.1204,14.5326 |46.1204,14.5330 |46.1207,14.5335 |46.1209,14.5338 |46.1210,14.5349 |46.1211,14.5357 |46.1209,14.5358 |46.1207,14.5355 |46.1206,14.5355 |46.1202,14.5365 |46.1194,14.5370 |46.1191,14.5372 |46.1189,14.5381 |46.1183,14.5390 |46.1180,14.5394 |46.1174,14.5393 |46.1173,14.5391 |46.1172,14.5391 |46.1170,14.5389 |46.1164,14.5392 |46.1163,14.5392 |46.1159,14.5396 |46.1157,14.5402 |46.1156,14.5410 |46.1157,14.5415 |46.1157,14.5421 |46.1158,14.5427 |46.1161,14.5434 |46.1160,14.5438 |46.1162,14.5440 |46.1161,14.5442 |46.1157,14.5446 |46.1155,14.5452 |46.1145,14.5464 |46.1142,14.5478 |46.1136,14.5484 |46.1138,14.5491 |46.1139,14.5492 |46.1139,14.5496 |46.1141,14.5501 |46.1143,14.5505 |46.1150,14.5515 |46.1156,14.5516 |46.1157,14.5519 |46.1168,14.5525 |46.1164,14.5533 |46.1167,14.5540 |46.1167,14.5542 |46.1159,14.5551 |46.1157,14.5577 |46.1156,14.5586 |46.1153,14.5601 |46.1152,14.5601 |46.1152,14.5603 |46.1151,14.5603 |46.1151,14.5608 |46.1149,14.5610 |46.1150,14.5611 |46.1147,14.5615 |46.1146,14.5616 |46.1145,14.5619 |46.1138,14.5625 |46.1135,14.5625 |46.1133,14.5627 |46.1133,14.5629 |46.1134,14.5635 |46.1134,14.5641 |46.1137,14.5645 |46.1134,14.5652 |46.1133,14.5652 |46.1131,14.5653 |46.1130,14.5653 |46.1127,14.5655 |46.1126,14.5659 |46.1124,14.5661 |46.1124,14.5663 |46.1122,14.5665 |46.1121,14.5664 |46.1121,14.5668 |46.1120,14.5668 |46.1120,14.5670 |46.1119,14.5672 |46.1117,14.5671 |46.1117,14.5669 |46.1116,14.5669 |46.1115,14.5670 |46.1116,14.5673 |46.1115,14.5674 |46.1113,14.5675 |46.1111,14.5679 |46.1109,14.5676 |46.1107,14.5679 |46.1107,14.5681 |46.1105,14.5681 |46.1105,14.5677 |46.1104,14.5674 |46.1101,14.5674 |46.1100,14.5675 |46.1102,14.5682 |46.1100,14.5683 |46.1098,14.5681 |46.1098,14.5683 |46.1099,14.5686 |46.1099,14.5688 |46.1097,14.5690 |46.1098,14.5693 |46.1096,14.5695 |46.1092,14.5693 |46.1090,14.5687 |46.1087,14.5682 |46.1081,14.5681 |46.1078,14.5683 |46.1053,14.5709 |46.1044,14.5713 |46.1038,14.5719 |46.1029,14.5725 |46.1030,14.5725 |46.1033,14.5731 |46.1040,14.5739 |46.1046,14.5750 |46.1052,14.5753 |46.1055,14.5759 |46.1055,14.5765 |46.1036,14.5786 |46.1034,14.5790 |46.1031,14.5796 |46.1036,14.5799 |46.1049,14.5799 |46.1059,14.5794 |46.1062,14.5794 |46.1064,14.5796 |46.1070,14.5808 |46.1077,14.5807 |46.1076,14.5811 |46.1069,14.5816 |46.1064,14.5817 |46.1061,14.5820 |46.1063,14.5824 |46.1065,14.5827 |46.1068,14.5828 |46.1071,14.5825 |46.1074,14.5828 |46.1076,14.5826 |46.1077,14.5826 |46.1082,14.5830 |46.1081,14.5832 |46.1079,14.5831 |46.1078,14.5829 |46.1076,14.5829 |46.1075,14.5838 |46.1073,14.5841 |46.1066,14.5844 |46.1064,14.5846 |46.1061,14.5846 |46.1059,14.5843 |46.1057,14.5844 |46.1052,14.5853 |46.1052,14.5859 |46.1050,14.5863 |46.1048,14.5872 |46.1048,14.5876 |46.1043,14.5884 |46.1044,14.5888 |46.1049,14.5898 |46.1041,14.5918 |46.1039,14.5916 |46.1038,14.5918 |46.1036,14.5920 |46.1030,14.5929 |46.1026,14.5930 |46.1020,14.5932 |46.1010,14.5930 |46.1006,14.5927 |46.1004,14.5929 |46.1002,14.5927 |46.0987,14.5942 |46.0982,14.5929 |46.0974,14.5933 |46.0973,14.5925 |46.0961,14.5935 |46.0958,14.5933 |46.0954,14.5925 |46.0916,14.5923 |46.0894,14.5922 |46.0891,14.5905 |46.0876,14.5912 |46.0861,14.5918 |46.0861,14.5919 |46.0856,14.5922 |46.0858,14.5942 |46.0857,14.5960 |46.0856,14.5967 |46.0850,14.5990 |46.0839,14.6024 |46.0819,14.6070 |46.0773,14.6175 |46.0762,14.6206 |46.0757,14.6221 |46.0753,14.6242 |46.0749,14.6264 |46.0746,14.6283 |46.0750,14.6282 |46.0749,14.6307 |46.0749,14.6336 |46.0752,14.6359 |46.0754,14.6377 |46.0757,14.6391 |46.0762,14.6406 |46.0769,14.6427 |46.0784,14.6461 |46.0788,14.6478 |46.0791,14.6501 |46.0792,14.6541 |46.0792,14.6565 |46.0787,14.6608 |46.0787,14.6628 |46.0789,14.6642 |46.0794,14.6657 |46.0800,14.6666 |46.0845,14.6725 |46.0862,14.6752 |46.0865,14.6758 |46.0854,14.6771 |46.0853,14.6775 |46.0840,14.6768 |46.0840,14.6771 |46.0841,14.6772 |46.0841,14.6773 |46.0811,14.6776 |46.0801,14.6773 |46.0798,14.6772 |46.0794,14.6773 |46.0791,14.6777 |46.0790,14.6784 |46.0782,14.6798 |46.0778,14.6802 |46.0774,14.6805 |46.0773,14.6812 |46.0769,14.6819 |46.0771,14.6835 |46.0775,14.6843 |46.0776,14.6862 |46.0775,14.6867 |46.0774,14.6870 |46.0770,14.6874 |46.0759,14.6879 |46.0754,14.6887 |46.0747,14.6895 |46.0741,14.6902 |46.0740,14.6906 |46.0737,14.6911 |46.0731,14.6915 |46.0736,14.6919 |46.0747,14.6933 |46.0770,14.6967 |46.0767,14.6982 |46.0761,14.6983 |46.0760,14.6991 |46.0761,14.6995 |46.0764,14.7000 |46.0774,14.7011 |46.0782,14.7025 |46.0784,14.7036 |46.0784,14.7040 |46.0783,14.7044 |46.0782,14.7051 |46.0783,14.7062 |46.0782,14.7069 |46.0779,14.7075 |46.0779,14.7080 |46.0778,14.7084 |46.0777,14.7092 |46.0777,14.7096 |46.0776,14.7106 |46.0777,14.7112 |46.0780,14.7117 |46.0779,14.7118 |46.0776,14.7117 |46.0769,14.7117 |46.0767,14.7116 |46.0758,14.7136 |46.0759,14.7154 |46.0757,14.7164 |46.0754,14.7167 |46.0758,14.7173 |46.0754,14.7181 |46.0750,14.7185 |46.0746,14.7186 |46.0743,14.7192 |46.0739,14.7196 |46.0736,14.7207 |46.0734,14.7213 |46.0723,14.7231 |46.0721,14.7230 |46.0715,14.7232 |46.0710,14.7230 |46.0703,14.7231 |46.0697,14.7230 |46.0687,14.7219 |46.0686,14.7216 |46.0689,14.7209 |46.0687,14.7202 |46.0683,14.7195 |46.0683,14.7190 |46.0682,14.7189 |46.0681,14.7191 |46.0680,14.7194 |46.0679,14.7203 |46.0674,14.7213 |46.0674,14.7215 |46.0667,14.7220 |46.0662,14.7228 |46.0660,14.7236 |46.0657,14.7238 |46.0657,14.7240 |46.0660,14.7247 |46.0659,14.7254 |46.0662,14.7271 |46.0662,14.7274 |46.0660,14.7275 |46.0660,14.7277 |46.0658,14.7277 |46.0657,14.7286 |46.0656,14.7287 |46.0656,14.7293 |46.0661,14.7301 |46.0660,14.7311 |46.0661,14.7313 |46.0663,14.7315 |46.0662,14.7317 |46.0661,14.7319 |46.0663,14.7324 |46.0663,14.7331 |46.0665,14.7335 |46.0668,14.7335 |46.0670,14.7340 |46.0670,14.7345 |46.0668,14.7348 |46.0666,14.7350 |46.0666,14.7354 |46.0673,14.7361 |46.0673,14.7366 |46.0675,14.7375 |46.0675,14.7381 |46.0678,14.7383 |46.0678,14.7390 |46.0680,14.7402 |46.0678,14.7405 |46.0677,14.7410 |46.0677,14.7417 |46.0677,14.7420 |46.0680,14.7423 |46.0677,14.7432 |46.0676,14.7440 |46.0679,14.7450 |46.0682,14.7453 |46.0682,14.7457 |46.0680,14.7461 |46.0677,14.7461 |46.0673,14.7458 |46.0670,14.7461 |46.0665,14.7463 |46.0663,14.7461 |46.0658,14.7463 |46.0655,14.7463 |46.0645,14.7465 |46.0638,14.7471 |46.0633,14.7472 |46.0624,14.7470 |46.0621,14.7471 |46.0618,14.7468 |46.0611,14.7467 |46.0605,14.7460 |46.0603,14.7457 |46.0596,14.7463 |46.0594,14.7468 |46.0592,14.7461 |46.0589,14.7453 |46.0582,14.7445 |46.0581,14.7442 |46.0577,14.7430 |46.0576,14.7421 |46.0572,14.7410 |46.0573,14.7404 |46.0566,14.7408 |46.0562,14.7389 |46.0555,14.7382 |46.0552,14.7376 |46.0554,14.7367 |46.0553,14.7364 |46.0548,14.7350 |46.0546,14.7339 |46.0543,14.7333 |46.0533,14.7320 |46.0529,14.7326 |46.0527,14.7326 |46.0525,14.7323 |46.0522,14.7323 |46.0522,14.7314 |46.0517,14.7314 |46.0517,14.7304 |46.0520,14.7295 |46.0524,14.7284 |46.0521,14.7280 |46.0520,14.7277 |46.0517,14.7274 |46.0519,14.7267 |46.0521,14.7263 |46.0522,14.7256 |46.0521,14.7251 |46.0512,14.7256 |46.0510,14.7258 |46.0506,14.7259 |46.0501,14.7267 |46.0498,14.7267 |46.0493,14.7271 |46.0464,14.7299 |46.0460,14.7302 |46.0456,14.7308 |46.0450,14.7333 |46.0448,14.7334 |46.0447,14.7347 |46.0436,14.7360 |46.0431,14.7363 |46.0421,14.7364 |46.0410,14.7364 |46.0407,14.7365 |46.0404,14.7371 |46.0403,14.7375 |46.0402,14.7376 |46.0401,14.7384 |46.0402,14.7393 |46.0401,14.7399 |46.0400,14.7402 |46.0398,14.7403 |46.0396,14.7411 |46.0395,14.7415 |46.0394,14.7426 |46.0393,14.7427 |46.0391,14.7431 |46.0383,14.7442 |46.0379,14.7445 |46.0375,14.7445 |46.0374,14.7446 |46.0373,14.7448 |46.0373,14.7452 |46.0373,14.7455 |46.0366,14.7456 |46.0363,14.7457 |46.0359,14.7457 |46.0358,14.7460 |46.0355,14.7461 |46.0350,14.7466 |46.0343,14.7472 |46.0342,14.7474 |46.0336,14.7477 |46.0336,14.7483 |46.0333,14.7484 |46.0332,14.7486 |46.0331,14.7491 |46.0330,14.7492 |46.0329,14.7492 |46.0327,14.7491 |46.0326,14.7491 |46.0319,14.7496 |46.0317,14.7500 |46.0311,14.7505 |46.0309,14.7511 |46.0309,14.7519 |46.0308,14.7521 |46.0299,14.7537 |46.0297,14.7553 |46.0296,14.7553 |46.0288,14.7543 |46.0289,14.7541 |46.0282,14.7533 |46.0279,14.7531 |46.0274,14.7523 |46.0271,14.7523 |46.0263,14.7520 |46.0256,14.7520 |46.0255,14.7524 |46.0255,14.7525 |46.0259,14.7530 |46.0260,14.7533 |46.0265,14.7540 |46.0262,14.7545 |46.0261,14.7546 |46.0258,14.7543 |46.0249,14.7550 |46.0246,14.7550 |46.0238,14.7546 |46.0237,14.7545 |46.0239,14.7534 |46.0241,14.7526 |46.0241,14.7520 |46.0240,14.7513 |46.0237,14.7509 |46.0237,14.7507 |46.0238,14.7492 |46.0238,14.7480 |46.0236,14.7473 |46.0230,14.7465 |46.0230,14.7463 |46.0234,14.7456 |46.0234,14.7450 |46.0235,14.7445 |46.0233,14.7433 |46.0231,14.7429 |46.0222,14.7418 |46.0222,14.7416 |46.0219,14.7416 |46.0217,14.7419 |46.0217,14.7422 |46.0213,14.7425 |46.0211,14.7426 |46.0208,14.7404 |46.0206,14.7401 |46.0203,14.7403 |46.0202,14.7411 |46.0183,14.7417 |46.0179,14.7413 |46.0180,14.7406 |46.0179,14.7404 |46.0178,14.7403 |46.0177,14.7405 |46.0173,14.7405 |46.0171,14.7406 |46.0168,14.7410 |46.0167,14.7416 |46.0168,14.7432 |46.0166,14.7438 |46.0159,14.7450 |46.0154,14.7457 |46.0152,14.7453 |46.0151,14.7443 |46.0152,14.7440 |46.0152,14.7419 |46.0148,14.7418 |46.0147,14.7420 |46.0147,14.7423 |46.0143,14.7426 |46.0141,14.7434 |46.0135,14.7447 |46.0134,14.7447 |46.0133,14.7450 |46.0134,14.7453 |46.0139,14.7455 |46.0140,14.7457 |46.0141,14.7467 |46.0142,14.7471 |46.0127,14.7482 |46.0126,14.7477 |46.0125,14.7475 |46.0121,14.7476 |46.0108,14.7465 |46.0104,14.7463 |46.0102,14.7459 |46.0088,14.7451 |46.0082,14.7446 |46.0074,14.7450 |46.0071,14.7454 |46.0077,14.7460 |46.0082,14.7465 |46.0085,14.7469 |46.0085,14.7473 |46.0084,14.7477 |46.0079,14.7485 |46.0078,14.7491 |46.0075,14.7501 |46.0076,14.7507 |46.0077,14.7514 |46.0075,14.7518 |46.0074,14.7518 |46.0071,14.7516 |46.0066,14.7510 |46.0064,14.7506 |46.0060,14.7505 |46.0051,14.7498 |46.0049,14.7493 |46.0046,14.7493 |46.0042,14.7474 |46.0040,14.7474 |46.0036,14.7472 |46.0031,14.7473 |46.0030,14.7472 |46.0025,14.7476 |46.0021,14.7482 |46.0017,14.7480 |46.0004,14.7467 |46.0001,14.7461 |46.0000,14.7460 |46.0000,14.7456 |45.9998,14.7450 |45.9995,14.7445 |45.9987,14.7437 |45.9979,14.7431 |45.9978,14.7419 |45.9975,14.7407 |45.9976,14.7389 |45.9976,14.7386 |45.9980,14.7363 |45.9982,14.7355 |45.9982,14.7342 |45.9979,14.7330 |45.9979,14.7317 |45.9997,14.7315 |45.9997,14.7297 |46.0000,14.7286 |45.9999,14.7269 |46.0001,14.7257 |46.0003,14.7254 |46.0016,14.7245 |46.0018,14.7244 |46.0022,14.7244 |46.0027,14.7242 |46.0037,14.7235 |46.0027,14.7230 |46.0024,14.7230 |46.0021,14.7228 |46.0018,14.7228 |46.0016,14.7225 |46.0011,14.7226 |46.0008,14.7222 |46.0008,14.7216 |46.0007,14.7211 |46.0008,14.7201 |46.0015,14.7196 |46.0022,14.7195 |46.0023,14.7194 |46.0028,14.7194 |46.0031,14.7195 |46.0032,14.7194 |46.0035,14.7189 |46.0038,14.7188 |46.0042,14.7190 |46.0045,14.7186 |46.0048,14.7188 |46.0050,14.7184 |46.0052,14.7184 |46.0065,14.7185 |46.0069,14.7165 |46.0069,14.7161 |46.0067,14.7154 |46.0071,14.7152 |46.0076,14.7145 |46.0085,14.7141 |46.0088,14.7142 |46.0087,14.7146 |46.0090,14.7149 |46.0093,14.7148 |46.0095,14.7145 |46.0099,14.7135 |46.0117,14.7142 |46.0119,14.7144 |46.0122,14.7139 |46.0117,14.7116 |46.0127,14.7106 |46.0126,14.7099 |46.0130,14.7098 |46.0134,14.7095 |46.0138,14.7083 |46.0143,14.7073 |46.0143,14.7064 |46.0153,14.7045 |46.0150,14.7041 |46.0147,14.7035 |46.0145,14.7032 |46.0137,14.7024 |46.0129,14.7026 |46.0123,14.7016 |46.0112,14.7002 |46.0104,14.6989 |46.0114,14.6974 |46.0123,14.6969 |46.0124,14.6967 |46.0124,14.6961 |46.0088,14.6942 |46.0083,14.6944 |46.0081,14.6942 |46.0082,14.6941 |46.0081,14.6938 |46.0081,14.6935 |46.0082,14.6931 |46.0083,14.6928 |46.0085,14.6925 |46.0086,14.6923 |46.0085,14.6921 |46.0087,14.6911 |46.0088,14.6902 |46.0090,14.6897 |46.0095,14.6893 |46.0103,14.6871 |46.0109,14.6856 |46.0107,14.6838 |46.0105,14.6833 |46.0103,14.6830 |46.0097,14.6824 |46.0088,14.6820 |46.0082,14.6814 |46.0079,14.6812 |46.0078,14.6808 |46.0070,14.6799 |46.0061,14.6779 |46.0055,14.6769 |46.0052,14.6760 |46.0048,14.6753 |46.0046,14.6746 |46.0047,14.6744 |46.0041,14.6748 |46.0037,14.6756 |46.0031,14.6756 |46.0027,14.6757 |46.0025,14.6763 |46.0017,14.6778 |46.0015,14.6786 |46.0014,14.6791 |46.0011,14.6802 |46.0007,14.6811 |46.0006,14.6818 |45.9999,14.6830 |45.9991,14.6831 |45.9990,14.6832 |45.9983,14.6827 |45.9977,14.6818 |45.9970,14.6818 |45.9968,14.6809 |45.9966,14.6808 |45.9964,14.6804 |45.9964,14.6801 |45.9958,14.6793 |45.9957,14.6784 |45.9959,14.6780 |45.9961,14.6770 |45.9959,14.6759 |45.9955,14.6750 |45.9954,14.6745 |45.9955,14.6738 |45.9956,14.6732 |45.9956,14.6727 |45.9955,14.6724 |45.9952,14.6722 |45.9950,14.6714 |45.9943,14.6708 |45.9938,14.6701 |45.9936,14.6689 |45.9930,14.6687 |45.9927,14.6688 |45.9925,14.6684 |45.9918,14.6679 |45.9911,14.6677 |45.9892,14.6682 |45.9889,14.6687 |45.9887,14.6692 |45.9884,14.6692 |45.9883,14.6683 |45.9880,14.6678 |45.9881,14.6675 |45.9878,14.6670 |45.9875,14.6659 |45.9878,14.6652 |45.9878,14.6644 |45.9879,14.6640 |45.9879,14.6633 |45.9877,14.6629 |45.9873,14.6626 |45.9875,14.6620 |45.9881,14.6601 |45.9882,14.6594 |45.9885,14.6589 |45.9886,14.6588 |45.9888,14.6583 |45.9886,14.6583 |45.9887,14.6575 |45.9889,14.6570 |45.9879,14.6574 |45.9876,14.6553 |45.9878,14.6545 |45.9881,14.6540 |45.9884,14.6533 |45.9889,14.6519 |45.9891,14.6517 |45.9893,14.6508 |45.9898,14.6499 |45.9893,14.6485 |45.9893,14.6465 |45.9892,14.6465 |45.9889,14.6468 |45.9884,14.6469 |45.9885,14.6465 |45.9883,14.6463 |45.9883,14.6450 |45.9889,14.6441 |45.9890,14.6429 |45.9891,14.6425 |45.9893,14.6420 |45.9900,14.6413 |45.9896,14.6408 |45.9893,14.6407 |45.9875,14.6410 |45.9876,14.6405 |45.9878,14.6400 |45.9884,14.6397 |45.9886,14.6398 |45.9890,14.6400 |45.9890,14.6396 |45.9891,14.6392 |45.9895,14.6388 |45.9896,14.6388 |45.9897,14.6390 |45.9899,14.6390 |45.9904,14.6392 |45.9906,14.6395 |45.9906,14.6394 |45.9905,14.6388 |45.9904,14.6385 |45.9905,14.6379 |45.9914,14.6371 |45.9921,14.6367 |45.9935,14.6352 |45.9939,14.6349 |45.9944,14.6347 |45.9951,14.6348 |45.9956,14.6334 |45.9955,14.6327 |45.9955,14.6320 |45.9950,14.6320 |45.9949,14.6308 |45.9948,14.6306 |45.9945,14.6305 |45.9943,14.6301 |45.9939,14.6303 |45.9926,14.6312 |45.9921,14.6314 |45.9916,14.6318 |45.9909,14.6316 |45.9901,14.6322 |45.9892,14.6326 |45.9891,14.6328 |45.9892,14.6330 |45.9896,14.6331 |45.9896,14.6332 |45.9892,14.6336 |45.9889,14.6341 |45.9886,14.6349 |45.9879,14.6360 |45.9875,14.6365 |45.9873,14.6365 |45.9870,14.6347 |45.9870,14.6338 |45.9871,14.6337 |45.9870,14.6332 |45.9870,14.6326 |45.9868,14.6325 |45.9871,14.6313 |45.9871,14.6305 |45.9874,14.6306 |45.9874,14.6303 |45.9873,14.6294 |45.9874,14.6293 |45.9872,14.6290 |45.9874,14.6261 |45.9874,14.6242 |45.9878,14.6240 |45.9885,14.6240 |45.9886,14.6237 |45.9885,14.6232 |45.9884,14.6218 |45.9883,14.6209 |45.9885,14.6206 |45.9889,14.6206 |45.9896,14.6199 |45.9897,14.6190 |45.9926,14.6172 |45.9936,14.6169 |45.9939,14.6163 |45.9939,14.6162 |45.9940,14.6159 |45.9942,14.6158 |45.9949,14.6156 |45.9953,14.6154 |45.9958,14.6149 |45.9962,14.6148 |45.9964,14.6147 |45.9966,14.6155 |45.9966,14.6156 |45.9961,14.6157 |45.9958,14.6161 |45.9958,14.6163 |45.9960,14.6169 |45.9966,14.6173 |45.9972,14.6178 |45.9982,14.6181 |45.9989,14.6171 |45.9991,14.6166 |45.9991,14.6160 |45.9993,14.6157 |45.9996,14.6154 |46.0000,14.6153 |46.0000,14.6145 |46.0002,14.6145 |46.0015,14.6138 |46.0018,14.6138 |46.0021,14.6128 |46.0019,14.6122 |46.0015,14.6115 |46.0016,14.6108 |46.0015,14.6097 |46.0011,14.6090 |46.0017,14.6086 |46.0017,14.6080 |46.0023,14.6069 |46.0029,14.6065 |46.0033,14.6062 |46.0037,14.6047 |46.0045,14.6031 |46.0050,14.6007 |46.0058,14.6000 |46.0065,14.5987 |46.0070,14.5981 |46.0081,14.5980 |46.0085,14.5985 |46.0088,14.5978 |46.0085,14.5964 |46.0083,14.5957 |46.0081,14.5955 |46.0081,14.5952 |46.0079,14.5949 |46.0082,14.5946 |46.0085,14.5937 |46.0082,14.5927 |46.0083,14.5919 |46.0083,14.5912 |46.0088,14.5906 |46.0114,14.5877 |46.0123,14.5891 |46.0126,14.5888 |46.0128,14.5885 |46.0136,14.5885 |46.0143,14.5875 |46.0148,14.5870 |46.0152,14.5868 |46.0159,14.5860 |46.0160,14.5863 |46.0171,14.5866 |46.0171,14.5861 |46.0169,14.5859 |46.0171,14.5857 |46.0172,14.5843 |46.0176,14.5831 |46.0177,14.5832 |46.0180,14.5828 |46.0192,14.5836 |46.0192,14.5826 |46.0190,14.5824 |46.0191,14.5814 |46.0190,14.5810 |46.0191,14.5802 |46.0190,14.5798 |46.0191,14.5793 |46.0191,14.5783 |46.0190,14.5780 |46.0188,14.5776 |46.0187,14.5772 |46.0184,14.5751 |46.0195,14.5746 |46.0194,14.5741 |46.0194,14.5735 |46.0191,14.5734 |46.0189,14.5734 |46.0184,14.5736 |46.0181,14.5733 |46.0179,14.5732 |46.0178,14.5729 |46.0174,14.5727 |46.0169,14.5732 |46.0167,14.5731 |46.0165,14.5726 |46.0165,14.5719 |46.0167,14.5709 |46.0166,14.5706 |46.0168,14.5701 |46.0169,14.5697 |46.0169,14.5690 |46.0171,14.5684 |46.0164,14.5679 |46.0161,14.5674 |46.0156,14.5668 |46.0153,14.5661 |46.0145,14.5648 |46.0137,14.5642 |46.0134,14.5638 |46.0132,14.5632 |46.0129,14.5623 |46.0127,14.5616 |46.0126,14.5598 |46.0123,14.5594 |46.0126,14.5524 |46.0138,14.5451 |46.0142,14.5410 |46.0148,14.5356 |46.0152,14.5328 |46.0158,14.5302 |46.0140,14.5289 |46.0102,14.5354 |46.0079,14.5389 |46.0078,14.5387 |46.0059,14.5414 |46.0041,14.5380 |46.0038,14.5385 |46.0029,14.5379 |46.0030,14.5376 |46.0000,14.5358 |45.9999,14.5360 |45.9937,14.5344 |45.9905,14.5337 |45.9905,14.5302 |45.9900,14.5296 |45.9905,14.5291 |45.9908,14.5280 |45.9921,14.5268 |45.9922,14.5263 |45.9921,14.5250 |45.9925,14.5245 |45.9930,14.5242 |45.9937,14.5231 |45.9948,14.5226 |45.9955,14.5210 |45.9963,14.5205 |45.9974,14.5198 |45.9965,14.5195 |45.9965,14.5180 |45.9966,14.5180 |45.9965,14.5177 |45.9965,14.5169 |45.9969,14.5126 |45.9966,14.5124 |46.0022,14.5098 |46.0031,14.5094 |45.9949,14.4720 |45.9854,14.4764 |45.9784,14.4786 |45.9777,14.4764 |45.9773,14.4764 |45.9772,14.4758 |45.9776,14.4757 |45.9777,14.4755 |45.9780,14.4728 |45.9772,14.4730 |45.9771,14.4719 |45.9762,14.4675 |45.9785,14.4672 |45.9790,14.4626 |45.9788,14.4594 |45.9794,14.4590 |45.9763,14.4576 |45.9766,14.4569 |45.9767,14.4557 |45.9766,14.4550 |45.9760,14.4532 |45.9756,14.4525 |45.9755,14.4521 |45.9755,14.4512 |45.9755,14.4484 |45.9754,14.4482 |45.9749,14.4474 |45.9745,14.4466 |45.9746,14.4466 |45.9745,14.4461 |45.9742,14.4464 |45.9761,14.4446 |45.9741,14.4417 |45.9742,14.4396 |45.9741,14.4391 |45.9751,14.4374 |45.9759,14.4353 |45.9759,14.4348 |45.9767,14.4341 |45.9768,14.4338 |45.9770,14.4337 |45.9774,14.4338 |45.9780,14.4335 |45.9823,14.4289 |45.9830,14.4292 |45.9841,14.4300 |45.9860,14.4306 |45.9870,14.4310 |45.9874,14.4314 |45.9877,14.4318 |45.9889,14.4356 |45.9899,14.4385 |45.9903,14.4392 |45.9910,14.4401 |45.9913,14.4408 |45.9915,14.4414 |45.9918,14.4425 |45.9921,14.4433 |45.9931,14.4454 |45.9935,14.4465 |45.9937,14.4460 |45.9936,14.4456 |45.9938,14.4448 |45.9942,14.4430 |45.9943,14.4427 |45.9947,14.4425 |45.9959,14.4455 |45.9958,14.4485 |45.9972,14.4535 |45.9971,14.4536 |45.9973,14.4541 |45.9975,14.4547 |45.9986,14.4569 |45.9990,14.4566 |45.9991,14.4563 |46.0007,14.4600 |46.0008,14.4607 |46.0007,14.4617 |46.0019,14.4617 |46.0025,14.4623 |46.0026,14.4627 |46.0029,14.4629 |46.0038,14.4637 |46.0040,14.4635 |46.0052,14.4652 |46.0061,14.4650 |46.0067,14.4648 |46.0073,14.4644 |46.0086,14.4628 |46.0092,14.4616 |46.0093,14.4608 |46.0102,14.4593 |46.0105,14.4585 |46.0105,14.4577 |46.0110,14.4563 |46.0110,14.4545 |46.0104,14.4540 |46.0108,14.4512 |46.0114,14.4496 |46.0122,14.4450 |46.0127,14.4450 |46.0128,14.4456 |46.0133,14.4456 |46.0131,14.4429 |46.0131,14.4421 |46.0133,14.4403 |46.0133,14.4388 |46.0133,14.4379 |46.0149,14.4384 |46.0154,14.4383 |46.0157,14.4385 |46.0164,14.4378 |46.0174,14.4380 |46.0206,14.4332 |46.0262,14.4304 |46.0266,14.4314 |46.0278,14.4308 |46.0283,14.4319 |46.0285,14.4322 |46.0287,14.4326 |46.0284,14.4333 |46.0289,14.4336 |46.0287,14.4336 |46.0292,14.4342 |46.0299,14.4358 |46.0304,14.4364 |46.0312,14.4371 |46.0316,14.4379 |46.0326,14.4394 |46.0344,14.4424 |46.0340,14.4426 |46.0340,14.4427 |46.0384,14.4407 |46.0382,14.4367 |46.0386,14.4368 |46.0386,14.4370 |46.0395,14.4369 |46.0404,14.4358 |46.0408,14.4357 |46.0404,14.4345 |46.0408,14.4345 |46.0409,14.4348 |46.0411,14.4349 |46.0411,14.4343 |46.0411,14.4338 |46.0420,14.4345 |46.0424,14.4345 |46.0426,14.4330 |46.0429,14.4334 |46.0436,14.4350 |46.0440,14.4341 |46.0440,14.4346 |46.0446,14.4356 |46.0446,14.4356 |46.0456,14.4346 |46.0461,14.4339 |46.0464,14.4341 |46.0469,14.4342 |46.0468,14.4347 |46.0473,14.4356 |46.0481,14.4366 |46.0483,14.4368 |46.0480,14.4375 |46.0480,14.4376 |46.0481,14.4378 |46.0477,14.4385 |46.0477,14.4390 |46.0473,14.4392 |46.0471,14.4397 |46.0473,14.4402 |46.0471,14.4408 |46.0475,14.4413 |46.0487,14.4423 |46.0487,14.4420 |46.0491,14.4414 |46.0492,14.4415 |46.0496,14.4407 |46.0502,14.4404 |46.0503,14.4401 |46.0503,14.4395 |46.0513,14.4405 |46.0513,14.4405 |46.0518,14.4408 |46.0530,14.4410 |46.0544,14.4393 |46.0546,14.4391 |46.0547,14.4391 |46.0553,14.4390 |46.0558,14.4391 |46.0570,14.4387 |46.0574,14.4370 |46.0584,14.4376 |46.0589,14.4376 |46.0594,14.4367 |46.0598,14.4366 |46.0601,14.4364 |46.0600,14.4358 |46.0605,14.4346 |46.0604,14.4343 |46.0596,14.4339 |46.0603,14.4332 |46.0606,14.4330 |46.0617,14.4336 |46.0634,14.4339 |46.0631,14.4320 |46.0628,14.4312 |46.0622,14.4302 |46.0619,14.4297 |46.0615,14.4294 |46.0613,14.4294 |46.0610,14.4295 |46.0606,14.4293 |46.0610,14.4284 |46.0617,14.4284 |46.0621,14.4282 |46.0632,14.4273 |46.0637,14.4265 |46.0646,14.4277 |46.0643,14.4284 |46.0642,14.4284 |46.0645,14.4312 |46.0651,14.4305 |46.0657,14.4306 |46.0659,14.4303 |46.0657,14.4301 |46.0657,14.4287 |46.0660,14.4284 |46.0665,14.4281 |46.0664,14.4275 |46.0657,14.4279 |46.0659,14.4260 |46.0662,14.4256 |46.0674,14.4278 |46.0677,14.4279 |46.0678,14.4278 |46.0680,14.4278 |46.0680,14.4281 |46.0675,14.4288 |46.0674,14.4293 |46.0677,14.4296 |46.0681,14.4293 |46.0687,14.4291 |46.0689,14.4283 |46.0688,14.4274 |46.0689,14.4269 |46.0690,14.4265 |46.0693,14.4262 |46.0692,14.4259 |46.0694,14.4256 |46.0697,14.4255 |46.0699,14.4252 |46.0708,14.4234 |46.0712,14.4225 |46.0715,14.4223 |46.0717,14.4227 |46.0723,14.4228 |46.0740,14.4220 |46.0746,14.4223 |46.0753,14.4227 |46.0760,14.4229 |46.0769,14.4239 |46.0775,14.4243 |46.0777,14.4243 |46.0784,14.4241 |46.0790,14.4237 |46.0793,14.4234 |46.0802,14.4243 |46.0806,14.4235 |46.0811,14.4229 |46.0812,14.4224 |46.0816,14.4214 |46.0811,14.4210 |46.0805,14.4209 |46.0801,14.4210 |46.0800,14.4201 |46.0799,14.4196 |46.0794,14.4186 |46.0799,14.4177 |46.0809,14.4169 |46.0811,14.4165 |46.0813,14.4157 |46.0817,14.4157 |46.0820,14.4150 |46.0821,14.4140 |46.0821,14.4131 |46.0821,14.4129 |46.0821,14.4127 |46.0818,14.4117 |46.0816,14.4113 |46.0816,14.4103 |46.0814,14.4089 |46.0814,14.4086 |46.0825,14.4090 |46.0828,14.4088 |46.0834,14.4092 |46.0844,14.4095 |46.0847,14.4100 |46.0850,14.4109 |46.0857,14.4119 |46.0867,14.4111 |46.0882,14.4114 |46.0884,14.4113 |46.0887,14.4115 |46.0892,14.4126 |46.0892,14.4128 |46.0893,14.4133 |46.0893,14.4137 |46.0894,14.4138 |46.0896,14.4138 |46.0902,14.4148 |46.0905,14.4150 |46.0908,14.4150 |46.0913,14.4147 |46.0913,14.4157 |46.0918,14.4161 |46.0919,14.4165 |46.0919,14.4166 |46.0920,14.4168 |46.0925,14.4172 |46.0927,14.4175 |46.0923,14.4178 |46.0920,14.4183 |46.0919,14.4187 |46.0920,14.4199 |46.0918,14.4204 |46.0917,14.4213 |46.0921,14.4217 |46.0920,14.4227 |46.0921,14.4244 |46.0923,14.4251 |46.0924,14.4252 |46.0924,14.4254 |46.0926,14.4253 |46.0926,14.4254 |46.0928,14.4273 |46.0930,14.4278 |46.0930,14.4281 |46.0927,14.4289 |46.0930,14.4293 |46.0942,14.4299 |46.0946,14.4304 |46.0948,14.4308 |46.0944,14.4317 |46.0942,14.4327 |46.0939,14.4337 |46.0931,14.4348 |46.0931,14.4365 |46.0935,14.4362 |46.0939,14.4363 |46.0943,14.4368 |46.0947,14.4374 |46.0948,14.4378 |46.0949,14.4387 |46.0951,14.4392 |46.0951,14.4395 |46.0949,14.4401 |46.0949,14.4407 |46.0950,14.4417 |46.0951,14.4418 |46.0954,14.4421 |46.0956,14.4426 |46.0968,14.4423 |46.0977,14.4413 |46.0980,14.4407 |46.0987,14.4399 |46.0991,14.4384 |46.0994,14.4379 |46.0995,14.4379 |46.1001,14.4360 |46.1002,14.4361 |46.1003,14.4356 |46.1006,14.4352 |46.1014,14.4339 |46.1013,14.4328 |46.1011,14.4322 |46.1012,14.4318 |46.1014,14.4309 |46.1022,14.4302 |46.1029,14.4309 |46.1038,14.4314 |46.1039,14.4312 |46.1043,14.4310 |46.1050,14.4309 |46.1051,14.4306 |46.1052,14.4305 |46.1050,14.4298 |46.1056,14.4292 |46.1063,14.4288 |46.1065,14.4290 |46.1072,14.4283 |46.1082,14.4279 |46.1103,14.4275 |46.1110,14.4277 |46.1114,14.4276 |46.1122,14.4273 |46.1128,14.4273 |46.1131,14.4269 |46.1134,14.4267 |46.1136,14.4269 |46.1151,14.4271 |46.1154,14.4266 |46.1149,14.4244 |46.1149,14.4242 |46.1149,14.4239 |46.1145,14.4213 |46.1140,14.4213 |46.1140,14.4211 |46.1140,14.4209 |46.1142,14.4206 |46.1140,14.4200 |46.1143,14.4202 |46.1145,14.4202 |46.1148,14.4204 |46.1149,14.4207 |46.1153,14.4208 |46.1155,14.4206 |46.1168,14.4206 |46.1171,14.4207 |46.1173,14.4207 |46.1172,14.4212 |46.1173,14.4213 |46.1178,14.4212 |46.1184,14.4216 |46.1195,14.4219 |46.1201,14.4220 |46.1205,14.4223 |46.1209,14.4222 |46.1209,14.4223 |46.1211,14.4223 |46.1212,14.4226 |46.1210,14.4227 |46.1211,14.4228 |46.1210,14.4234 |46.1212,14.4246 |46.1214,14.4249 |46.1216,14.4246 |46.1219,14.4246 |46.1221,14.4247 |46.1222,14.4255 |46.1222,14.4256 |46.1226,14.4253 |46.1228,14.4249 |46.1229,14.4249 |46.1233,14.4257 |46.1236,14.4258 |46.1237,14.4253 |46.1240,14.4252 |46.1244,14.4253 |46.1249,14.4249 |46.1257,14.4253 |46.1257,14.4258 |46.1264,14.4260 |46.1269,14.4265 |46.1271,14.4270 |46.1281,14.4268 |46.1284,14.4269 |46.1285,14.4263 |46.1287,14.4259 |46.1289,14.4267 |46.1287,14.4272 |46.1292,14.4274 |46.1292,14.4283 |46.1292,14.4287 |46.1291,14.4290 |46.1287,14.4290 |46.1287,14.4293 |46.1289,14.4298 |46.1290,14.4298 |46.1288,14.4301 |46.1293,14.4304 |46.1292,14.4306 |46.1289,14.4310 |46.1289,14.4314 |46.1295,14.4319 |46.1291,14.4331 |46.1287,14.4362 |46.1284,14.4375 |46.1280,14.4381 |46.1278,14.4383 |46.1253,14.4390 |46.1239,14.4396 |46.1234,14.4400 |46.1226,14.4411 |46.1213,14.4438 |46.1212,14.4435 |46.1210,14.4440 |46.1216,14.4443 |46.1224,14.4460 |46.1226,14.4459 |46.1233,14.4464 |46.1232,14.4466 |46.1241,14.4479 |46.1244,14.4482 |46.1247,14.4490 |46.1262,14.4500 |46.1274,14.4500 |46.1285,14.4496 |46.1287,14.4508 |46.1286,14.4517 |46.1285,14.4541 |46.1305,14.4534 |46.1305,14.4538 |46.1304,14.4542 |46.1300,14.4556 |46.1303,14.4563 |46.1305,14.4570 |46.1303,14.4573 |46.1305,14.4582 |46.1309,14.4587 |46.1312,14.4597 |46.1317,14.4603 |46.1319,14.4600 |46.1325,14.4607 |46.1335,14.4603 |46.1335,14.4607 |46.1333,14.4620 |46.1337,14.4626 |46.1340,14.4632 |46.1349,14.4641 |46.1350,14.4643 |46.1354,14.4656 |46.1341,14.4668 |46.1346,14.4685 |46.1351,14.4683 |46.1354,14.4683 |46.1368,14.4686 |46.1369,14.4683 |46.1365,14.4680 |46.1363,14.4676 |46.1360,14.4674 |46.1370,14.4650 |46.1385,14.4649 |46.1385,14.4647 |46.1393,14.4650 |46.1396,14.4677 |46.1398,14.4679 |46.1399,14.4671 |46.1415,14.4680 |46.1415,14.4687 |46.1415,14.4696}}

===On foot===
The centre of Ljubljana is small enough to cover by foot. You can pick up a free city map at a tourist information centre or in the train station. Navigating or finding a street is easy as streets are clearly marked.

===By bicycle===

There is also a system called '''[https://www.bicikelj.si/en/home BicikeLJ]''' ([https://apps.apple.com/app/id1509893465 iOS], [https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.jcdecaux.vls.ljubljana Android] apps) where you can rent bikes (first hour free, second hour €1, third hour €2, each additional hour €4). It is designed for short-term hire. It has 300 bikes on 30 stations around the inner city part and you can subscribe with a credit card online. You can take another bicycle after one hour has elapsed, without any cost.

===By bus===
The city's transportation authority [https://www.lpp.si/en LPP] operates 22 bus lines, which are clean and run frequently (every 10–15 minutes, 15–40 minutes during the weekend and summer). Most bus routes operate 05:00-22:30 (Sundays from 06:00). Night routes are: N1 (22:30-05:00), 2, 5 and 6 (03:15–00:00), N3 (21:00–05:00) and N11 (03:15–05:00), but they do not run between (01:00-3:00). Saturdays and Sundays no service on routes 22, 24, 28 and 29. Sundays no service on routes 7L, 8, 18, 20, 21, 27.

To ride the buses, you can either purchase an Urbana card (similar to the Oyster Card in [[London]]), download the Urbana phone app ([https://apps.apple.com/app/id1608543324 iOS], [https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.margento.urbanaplus Android]), or use a contactless Visa/Mastercard when boarding. 

The physical card can be bought at self-service stations ("Urbanomat") found at the larger bus stops across the city, LPP sales sites, tourist information centres and newspaper stands for €2 and need to be loaded with an amount ranging from €1 to €50. 

Upon entering the bus by the front door, you need to position the card next to the reader to pay for the route and validate the ticket. The [https://www.lpp.si/en/informations-passensgers/urbana-mobile-app Urbana app] has the advantage that it can be loaded using a Credit or Debit card and includes real time information.

The cost per journey is €1.50 and includes free transfers for Urbana card or app users within 90 minutes from the first card validation.[[File:Ljubljana (19409666524).jpg | thumb | 300px | Old town centre ]]
[[File:Tromostovje in Prešernov trg (Tromostovje and Prešeren Square).jpg|300px|thumb|Triple Bridge and Prešeren Square by night]]
===By taxi===
The (supposedly) cheapest taxi companies are:
* {{listing
| name=Taxi Laguna | alt= | url=
| phone= | tollfree=080 11 17 (in country only)
}}
* {{listing
   | name = Taxi Metro
   | alt = 
   | url = 
   | phone = 
   | tollfree = 080 11 90 (in country only)
   | lastedit = 2025-08-04
}}
Uber is available, but due to local regulations, it can only be used to hail registered taxies. The ride is metered, as with any other taxi, and the final price can deviate from the estimate in the app. Not all taxis charge the same fare.

Taxi Metro has a good app that you can use to order your taxi and see and estimated price. You can download it for [https://apps.apple.com/us/app/taximetro-ljubljana/id977998476 IOS] or [https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.metrotaxi Andriod]. There is no surge pricing and in case of events it might take a while to find a taxi as there might not be enough taxi drivers on shift.

While ordered taxis are cheap, those waiting on the street will usually have a high "street pickup" charge, and you can end up paying €25 or more for a short ride. Unless you're in a hurry, always order a taxi by phone.

===By boat===
You can see centre of Ljubljana also with frequent boat tour, they last around 1-2 hours.

==See==
[[File:Ljubljanica 01.jpg | thumb | 300px | Triple Bridge and Franciscan church]]

In 2021, seven works in Ljubljana by architect Jože Plečnik were inscribed on the [[UNESCO World Heritage List]]. These are the Trnovo Bridge, the green promenade along Vegova Street, the promenade along the embankments and bridges of the Ljubljanica River, the Roman walls in Mirje, the Church of St Michael, the Church of St. Francis of Assisi and the Garden of All Saints (Plečnik’s Žale).
* {{see
| name=Triple Bridge | alt=Tromostovje | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=At the heart of the old city
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q676315
| lastedit=2023-04-25
| content=The central span is from 1842: it became a bottleneck so in the 1930s footbridges were added on each side, fanning out slightly. On the north bank these lead into '''Prešeren Square''', adorned by the statue of the national poet France Prešeren (1800-1849). It's the obvious rendezvous point in town; the area is pedestrianised. '''The TIC''' is south end of the bridge.
}}
* {{see
| name=Old Town | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.049955 | long=14.506408 | directions=squeezed between the castle hill and Ljubljanica river
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=The old town has two squares, Mestni trg (City square) with the Robba fountain and the city hall behind it, and, further on, Gornji trg (Upper square). Well preserved medieval buildings now house local designer shops, and several popular cafes and restaurants. Although they may look creepy, the perfectly safe narrow lanes lead to charming little squares and buildings.
}}
* {{see
| name=Dragon Bridge |alt=Zmajski Most | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.052044 | long=14.510448 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q660029
| content=Completed in 1901, designed by Croatian Jurij Zainovich. It is guarded by four detailed dragon statues from the city's coat-of-arms. Look out for the dragon motif throughout the city. Be careful around the Dragon Bridge area, as it is on a major busy road just outside the pedestrian zone and near misses (and worse) between inattentive tourists and traffic are common. The dragon bridge is located at the end of the Ljubljana Open Market, just a block or two down the river (north-east direction) from the Triple bridge.
}}
* {{see
| name=Ljubljana Castle | alt= | url=https://www.ljubljanskigrad.si/en/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.048987 | long=14.508575 | directions=You can catch the funicular or walk up
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Entrance to the Castle Courtyard, Chapel and Gift shop is free, but there is a charge for access to the tower
| wikidata=Q2075156
| lastedit=2023-09-16
| content=The tower has magnificent views all over the city. You can also see the Sava River and Kamnik Alps in the distance. Included is a 3D Movie of the history of Ljubljana from a pre-historic settlement to [[Roman Empire]] to modern times (€6.50 for adults, €3 for students, seniors).
}}
* {{see
| name=Republic Square | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.05025 | long=14.500108 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q7314417
|lastedit=2025-08-04| content=Where crowds gathered as Slovenia announced its independence from the Yugoslav Federation in 1991. The square has significant importance for Slovene history, as it was a place of important public gatherings (and demonstrations) in the past. Across the road is the Slovene Parliament. Its façade is decorated with artistic nude statues of Slovenes at work and leisure. The square also houses the International Business Centre.
}}
[[File:Dragon from Ljubljana.jpg | thumb | 300px | Dragon Bridge ]] 
* {{see
| name=Roman Ruins | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.045640 | long=14.498791 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=A short walk west of the centre of town are the remains of the Roman City Walls, including a number of pillars from an entrance gate.
}}
* {{see
| name=Krakovo | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.041604 | long=14.507865 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=A village-like part of the city connecting the centre to the Trnovo suburb.
}}
* {{see
| name=Metelkova | alt= | url=http://www.metelkovamesto.org/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.056921 | long=14.516904 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Metelkova | image=Metelkova mesto1.jpg
|lastedit=2025-08-04| content=A self-declared autonomous culture place to gather for alternative artists, many subcultures and youth. What used to be a military barracks is now full of underground artists, bars and nightclubs. Metelkova can get crowded on Fridays and Saturdays. It is within 5 minute of walk from main Train Station, and it is home to a renowned hostel Celica.
}}
* {{marker | name=Tivoli Park | type=see | wikidata=Q2428528 }} to the west is the city's main park, with a large pond at its southwest end and the hill of Rožnik behind.
* {{see
| name=Ljubljana Zoo | alt= | url=https://info.zoo.si/ | email=
| address=Večna pot 70, | lat=46.052651 | long=14.472187 | directions=take bus 18, 18L
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=09:00–16:30 (winter) (open until 19:00 in summer). Closed Christmas Day. | price=Adults €10; students &amp; seniors €8.50; Children €6.50
| lastedit=2023-09-16
| content=One of the most beautiful zoos in Europe.
}}
* {{see
| name=University Botanic gardens Ljubljana | alt= | url=http://www.botanic-gardens-ljubljana.com/en/ | email=
| address=Ižanska cesta 15 | lat=46.040606 | long=14.514624 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 427-1280 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Open daily, Apr–Jun 07–19, Jul–Aug 07–20, Sep–Oct 07–19, Nov–Mar 07–17. Tropical glasshouse has reduced hours: Daily 10:00–16:45 | price=Gardens are free, tropical glasshouse €2.80
| content=Ljubljana Botanic Garden is the oldest Slovene cultural, scientific and educational institution. It was founded in 1810, the time of the Illyrian Provinces, as a garden of native flora and a section of the Central School (École Centrale). In the garden is also tropical glasshouse.
}}
* {{see
| name=Tomb of National Heroes | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.05152 | long=14.500551 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q85169
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=a tomb and a monument for the national heroes of the World War II resistance struggle in Slovenia, created in 1949.
}}
* {{see
| name=Ursuline Church of the Holy Trinity | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.049993 | long=14.502161 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3397488
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=A Baroque style church built between 1718 and 1726.
}}
* {{see
| name=Congress Square | alt=Kongresni trg | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.050074 | long=14.503688 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q5160826
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=One of the central squares, built in 1821. In 1988 the first free mass demonstration was held here, which was the start of the Slovenian spring, leading to the declaration of Slovenia's independence in 1991.
}}
* {{see
| name=Nebotičnik | alt= | url=https://www.neboticnik.si/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.053141 | long=14.503585 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q4178650
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=A 13 storey high-rise.built in 1931, designed by Vladimir Šubic, with a cafe &amp; bar on the top floor.
}}
* {{see
| name=Sts. Cyril and Methodius Church | alt=Cerkev sv. Cirila in Metoda | url=http://spc-ljubljana.si/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.053867 | long=14.499351 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1262088
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=An Orthodox Church has five domes with golden crosses at their top. It was built from 1932 to 1936, with interior frescos painted between 1986 and 1997.
}}
* {{see
| name=Franciscan Church of the Annunciation | alt=Frančiškanska cerkev Marijinega oznanjenja | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.051861 | long=14.506058 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1785618
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=Built between 1646 and 1660, with a later front facade and bell tower.
}}
* {{see
| name=Ljubljana Cathedral | alt=ljubljanska stolnica | url=http://www.stolnica.com/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.050714 | long=14.508242 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1236564
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=St. Nicholas's Church ''(cerkev sv. Nikolaja)'' was built between 1701 and 1706 on a site dating back to 1262. The fine interior includes fresco painted by Giulio Quaglio between 1703 and 1723.
}}
* {{see
| name=Ljubljana Mosque | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=For non-muslims - Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday and Saturday between 10 and 11 a.m., Exterior is free for all | price=
| wikidata=Q6660940
| lastedit=2026-02-20
| content=An intricate set of buildings, the first mosque in the country.
}}
===Museums===
[[File:StNicholas-Ljubljana.JPG | thumb | 300px | Ljubljana cathedral]]
* {{see
| name=Museum of Architecture and Design |alt=MAO| url=https://mao.si/en/ | email=mao@mao.si
| address=Rusjanov trg 7 | lat=46.050659 | long=14.563161 | directions=Bus 20 Nove Stožice-Fužine, 22 Kamna Gorica-Fužine
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Tu-Su 09:00-18:00, M Closed | price=Adult €7, Concessions €3.50
| lastedit=2023-09-11
| content=Hosts a permanent exhibition of Jože Plečnik's works.
}}
* {{see
| name=Plečnik House | alt=Plečnikova hiša | url=https://mgml.si/en/plecnik-house/ | email=plecniki@mgml.si
| address=Karunova 4-6 | lat=46.042315 | long=14.502283 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 280 16 04 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Adults €8, Concessions €6
| lastedit=2023-09-12
| content=Devoted to great Slovenian architect Jože Plečnik, who lived in this building from 1921 to 1957. The house contains rooms with the artist’s valuable original furniture and personal objects, an archive of his sketches and plans and a collection of clay, plaster and wooden models, a library, Plečnik’s correspondence, a photo archive, thesis projects of Plečnik’s students and an archive of the Academy of Architecture Collection. Access only by guided tour of not more than 7 people, booked at least five days in advance.
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Modern Art | alt=MG+ | url=http://www.mg-lj.si/en/ | email=
| address=Cankarjeva 15 | lat=46.053146 | long=14.498681 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Tu–Su 10:00–18:00 | price=€5 adults, €2.50 students &amp; 65+
| wikidata=Q6961178
| lastedit=2023-09-12
| content=For those who prefer contemporary art, MG+ houses the national collection of 20th-century Slovene art (paintings, sculptures, prints, drawings, photography, video and electronic media collections), a collection of works from the former Yugoslavia, and the Eastern European collection "Arteast 2000+.".
}}
* {{See
|name=Museum of Contemporary Art |alt=+MSUM |url=http://www.mg-lj.si/en/visit/779/info_msum/
|address=Maistrova 3 |lat=46.0557850 |long=14.51712705
|phone=
|lastedit=2023-09-12
|content=Opened in 2011 in the former military barracks complex this is complementary museum to the MG+. Opening hours and prices same as +MG. Adult combined tickets available.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Gallery | alt= | url=https://www.ng-slo.si/en/ | email=
| address=Prešernova 24 | lat=46.053727 | long=14.499861 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 2415418, +386 1 2415424 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu&amp;W F-Su 10:00-18:00 Th 10:20:00 | price=Permanent Exhibitions Adults €8 Concessions €6. see website for others.
| wikidata=Q1953536
| lastedit=2023-09-12
| content=Definitely worth visiting if you care about art. It exhibits two important permanent collections that include works of some of the best and most renowned Slovenian (impressionist) painters (Jama, Grohar, Jakopic, Azbe). You can also see there a restored original of the Robba Fountain, a monument of national cultural heritage.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum of Slovenia - Prešernova | alt= | url=http://www.narmuz-lj.si/ | email=info@nms.si
| address=Muzejska ulica 1 | lat=46.052222 | long=14.499444 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 2414400 | tollfree= | fax=+386 12414422
| hours=daily 10:00-18:00, Thursday 10:00-20:00, closed on public holidays. | price=Free admission each first Sunday of the month
| wikidata=Q2033282
| content=The oldest and the largest Slovene museum. It was founded in 1821. Existent museum building on the Museum street, was built in 1888 and was the first, building, assigned solely to culture in Slovenia. Today its stores a rich collections of valuable objects. The oldest spring back to the Stone Age, but there are also the newer ones, which are still used in our everyday life. Important columns of museum activity are also rich museum library and unit for preservation and restoring.}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum of Slovenia - Metelkova | url=http://www.nms.si | email=info@nms.si
| address=Maistrova 1 | lat=46.055647 | long=14.516249| directions=
| phone=+386 1 2307030 | tollfree= | fax=+386 12414422
| hours=Tu-Su 10:00-18:00, closed on public holidays. | price=
| content=In the new building of the National museum of Slovenia on the Metelkova Street, are exhibited collections of the applied art heritage of Slovenia. The permanent exhibition brings together objects of applied arts from the 14th century to the present day.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum of Contemporary History |alt=Muzej novejše in sodobne zgodovine| url=https://www.muzej-nz.si/en/ | email=
| address=Celovška 23 | lat=46.059109 | long=14.495105 | directions=walk through the pleasant Tivoli park to get here.
| phone=+386 1 3009610 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Adults €6, Children, Students 65+ €4
| lastedit=2023-09-10
| content=Slovenia's 20th-century history museum gives you a real sense of the country's roller-coaster ride through regime after regime. Its immersive exhibits include a walk-through World War I trench. The last exhibit shows the events around the Declaration of Independence from Yugoslavia and the Ten Day War with the Yugoslav Federal Army. All exhibits are translated to English and some to German too.
}}
* {{see
| name=Slovenian Museum of Natural History | alt= | url=http://www.pms-lj.si/en/ | email=
| address=Muzejska 1 | lat=46.052066 | long=14.499327 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 2410970 | tollfree=
| hours=F-W 10:00-18:00, Th 10:00-20:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q3666739
| lastedit=2016-11-12
| content=Features an almost complete skeleton of a 20,000 year old mammoth found near Kamnik in 1938, a 200-million-year old fossil fish skeleton found in [[Triglav National Park]], and a new, 13-m skeleton of a fin whale. Also has a large mineral collection.
}}
* {{see
| name=MGLC International Centre of Graphic Arts | alt= | url=https://mglc.si/en/ | email=info@mglc-lj.si
| address=Pod turnom 3 | lat=46.054653 | long=14.492799 | directions=In Tivoli Park
| phone=+386 1 2413800 | tollfree=
| hours=Open Tu-Sa 10:00-18:00, Su 12:00-18:00 | price=Adults €5, families €9, other discounts apply
| wikidata=Q3402462
| lastedit=2016-11-12
| content=Specialised in art shows, often in collaboration with international institutions. Normally on nearby sites but MGLC Tivoli Mansion is closed for renovation.
}}
* {{see
| name=City Museum of Ljubljana | alt=Mestni muzej Ljubljana | url=https://mgml.si/en/city-museum/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.047 | long=14.5041 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Tu–Su 10.00–18.00 | price=Adults €6; +60 &amp; other concessions €4
| wikidata=Q15645583
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=City history and temporary exhibitions.
}}
* {{See
|name=Railway Museum |alt=Železniški Muzej |url=https://www.zelezniskimuzej.si/
|address=Parmova ulica 35 |lat=46.062550393 |long=14.502834797 |directions=About 1km walk north-west of main railway station.
|hours=Tu-Su 10:00 14:00; M closed |price=Adults €8 Children, students, pensioners €4 group &amp; family prices available
|lastedit=2023-09-16
|content=Covers all aspects of the railway, Great selection of steam locos.}}
* {{see
| name=House of experiments | alt=Hiša eksperimentov | url=https://www.he.si/index.php?lang=en | email=
| address=Trubarjeva 39 | lat=46.052550 | long=14.510870 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2025-08-30
| content=A hands-on science "playground" for kids.
}}

==Do==
[[File:Ljubljanska Opera 2.jpg | thumb | 300px | Opera and Ballet Theatre]]
* {{do
| name=Hot Air Balloon Flights | alt=Balonarski center Barje | url=http://www.ballooning-bled.com/en/ | email=info@bcb.si
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+386 1 512 9220 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=From €180 pp
| lastedit=2021-06-21
| content=These launch at sunrise for one-hour flights, weather permitting. The launch spot is chosen on the day so the wind carries you over the historic centre. The whole programme is about 4 hours so reckon on a very early start. 
}}
* '''Football:''' {{do
| name=Olimpija Ljubljana | alt= | url=http://www.nkolimpija.si/ | email=
| address=Stožice Stadium | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q543404
| lastedit=2023-04-25
| content=They play soccer in PrvaLiga, the top tier. Their home ground (capacity 16,000) is off the ring road 2 km north of city centre.
}}
: '''[https://www.nk-bravo.si/ NK Bravo]''' also play in PrvaLiga, at Park Šiška (capacity 2300) 1 km northwest of the railway station.  

===Water parks===
* {{do
| name=Water City of Atlantis | url=https://www.atlantis-vodnomesto.si/en/home | email=
| address= | lat=46.063211 | long=14.548656 | directions=Located within the BTC City Shopping District, take bus 27 (27K on Sundays)
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€6–14
| lastedit=2023-09-16
| content= A water park offering 14 pools, thermal baths, slides and saunas. Special section is dedicated for children.
}}
* {{do
| name=Laguna Fun &amp; Spa | url=http://www.laguna.si/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.096760 | long=14.519409 | directions=located within the Ljubljana Resort, take bus 27 (27K on Sundays)
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Only Jun–Sep | price=€6–12
| content=Offers open-air pools during the day and themed parties at night.
}}
=== Opera &amp; Theatre === 
[[File:Drama theatre in Ljubljana, 2011.jpg | thumb | 300px | Slovene National Theatre ]]
* {{do
| name=Cankarjev Dom | alt= | url=https://www.cd-cc.si/en | email=vstopnice@cd-cc.si
| address= | lat=46.049902 | long=14.499158 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q5032503
| content=Enormous arts and convention centre with concerts and performances.
}}
* {{do
| name=Slovenian Philharmonic Orchestra | alt=Slovenska Filharmonija | url=http://www.filharmonija.si/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.050056 | long=14.504812 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q836874
| content=Orchestra dating back to 1701.
}}
* {{do
| name=Slovene National Theatre (Narodno Gledalisce) | alt= | url=http://www.drama.si/ | email=
| address=Erjavceva 1 | lat=46.048909 | long=14.5011 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q21034517
| content=
}}
* {{do
| name=Puppet Theatre (Lutkovno Gledalisce) | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Krekov Trg 2 | lat=46.050294 | long=14.509994 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{do
| name=Ljubljana Opera House | alt= | url=http://www.opera.si/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.052586 | long=14.500651 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q7541826
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=
}}
* {{do
| name=Križanke Outdoor Theatre | alt=Poletno gledališče Križanke | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.046504 | long=14.50328 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q6438656
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=used for summer festivals.
}}
* {{do
| name=Ljubljana City Theatre | alt=Mestno gledališče ljubljansko | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.052103 | long=14.504786 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q6660927
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=
}}
* {{do
| name=Ljubljana Summer Festival | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.046597 | long=14.503122 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q6660941
| lastedit=2021-05-08
| content=Opera, ballet and theatre festival held in July and August.
}}

===Cinema===
* {{do
| name=Kinoteka | url=http://www.kinoteka.si | email=
| address=Miklošičeva 28 | lat=46.056020 | long=14.507873 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Open daily, but closed on Sundays and in July and August | price=€3
| lastedit=2023-09-16
| content=Ljubljana's charming film museum where they have at least two movies a day. The movies range from classics to cult movies, from trash and horror to artistic masterpieces. All movies are presented in the original audio language, and equipped with Slovenian subtitles, sometimes also English. On Saturday mornings they have special projections for children. There are also some special events, round tables, premiers etc. all the time. It's a must visit for every film lover. It has also a nice little cafe with small prices
}}
* {{do
| name=Kinodvor | url=http://www.kinodvor.org/spored/ | email=
| address=Kolodvorska 13 | lat=46.056828 | long=14.509455 | directions=next to railway station
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= €3–5
| content=This is a small and very cool cinema that shows mostly new movies that are not playing in the blockbuster movie complexes. It has also a lot of special events, a great cafe and movies for children (Sundays).
}}
* {{do
| name=Arena Play &amp; Party | url=http://www.arena.si/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.064678 | long=14.548382 | directions=within BTC City Shopping District, take bus 27 
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Movies from €4.59–7.93
| content=A great place to spend an evening. Main features include bowling, pool, laser games and a state-of-the-art 3D XpanD cinema theatre.
}}
* {{do
| name=Cineplexx | alt= | url=https://www.cineplexx.si/kinematografi/cineplexx-ljubljana-rudnik/ | email=kino@cineplexx.si
| address=Jurčkova cesta 223 | lat=46.0213 | long=14.5372 | directions=Supernova Rudnik, take Bus 27, 3, 3B
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Every day 15:00 to 23:00 | price=€7.90; €4.90 on Tuesdays
| wikipedia=Cineplexx Cinemas
| lastedit=2023-12-13
| content=A Multiplex.
}}

=== Hiking ===
{{seealso|Hiking around Ljubljana}}

* '''Šmarna gora''' (662 m) is on the northern edge of the city, so it's popular, indeed crowded on fine weekends. For 30–60 minutes of easy climbing you will be rewarded by a nice views. Take Bus 8 to Tacenski most.
* '''Krim''' (1,107 m) was a military and civilian telecoms centre; the military post has been dismantled and the area is open to the public, with great views. The climb takes 2–3 hours (beware of bears!). Get here by car, which takes 30 min as the last 4 km of road are unpaved and narrow.

=== Cycling ===
Ljubljana is an excellent starting point for cycling adventures, offering options for all skill levels. For e-MTB enthusiasts, trails in Golovec, Rašica, and Polhograjsko hribovje provide lush forests and stunning views. Road cyclists can venture as far as Bled, Kamnik, or towards Idrija and Cerkno, enjoying scenic routes and rewarding climbs. Gravel bikers will love the peaceful countryside paths, while bikepacking enthusiasts can tackle the Western Loop of Slovenia, a popular multi-day route starting in Ljubljana that highlights the country’s diverse landscapes.
* {{do
| name=HourAway | alt= | url=http://www.hour-away.com | email=info@hour-away.com
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+386 31 796 133 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2025-01-09
| content=Houraway offers high-quality bike rentals, including e-bikes, road bikes, and gravel bikes, along with guided and self-guided cycling tours. Their expertly designed day and multi-day tours cater to all fitness levels, showcasing Slovenia’s scenic landscapes, from peaceful countryside paths to challenging mountain routes.
}}

=== Ski and snowboard ===
Ljubljana is close to several of Slovenia's most popular ski resorts including [https://ugosnow.com/review-krvavec-slovenia/ Krvavec] at the nearby [[Cerklje na Gorenjskem]] which is around 40 minutes from the city by car.

Vogel ski center can be reached in around 1.5 hours, which is situated above the beautiful Lake Bohinj.

Kranjska Gora is another option for budget ski and snowboarding which can be reached in just over an hour from Ljubljana. 

The mountains in Slovenia are called the [[Julian Alps]] and offer some great value skiing throughout the winter. While the snowfall can be unpredictable, as this relatively low altitude mountain terrain, the peak seasons of January to March can offer some great conditions.

==Learn==
[[File:University of Ljubljana Palace.jpg|thumb|300px|University of Ljubljana Palace]]
Part of the buzz around Ljubljana is from its large student population. The [http://www.uni-lj.si/ University of Ljubljana] has 64,000 students, with departments all over the city. [https://www.centerslo.net Centre for Slovene] within the Arts Faculty offers language courses.

==Work==
Quite a lot of internationals work in Ljubljana, and it continuously hosts a significant number of freelancers who like to spend some months here due to the good ratio of quality towards cost of living. Coworking options are available, one gravity centre is the former tobacco factory, for example hosting [http://www.poligon.si/en/ Poligon], Slovenia's biggest coworking space (it is located in the building Tobačna 5, which also hosts the public administration body, "Upravna enota" and a tech startup space called [http://hekovnik.com/ Hekovnik]).

==Buy==
Several department stores such as Maximarket, H&amp;M, Müller, Nama, are located in the city centre. Additionally, Čopova street and the Old town have a dense collection of small shops.

* {{buy
| name=BTC City Shopping District | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.0657 | long=14.5462 | directions=At the north-eastern edge. Take Bus 27.
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2023-04-25
| content=One of Ljubljana's two main shopping area.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Rudnik Shopping District | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=46.0197 | long=14.5353 | directions=In the south-eastern edge of the city.
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2023-04-25
| content=The second major shopping district.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Sunday flea market | url= | email=
| address=Gallusovo nabrezje | lat=46.04713 | long=14.50594| directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Daily 08:00-14:00 | price=
| content=Two dozen or so stalls selling overpriced knick-knacks. Postcards, €10. Tito and Disney memorabilia, broken Chinese-made curios, rusty military paraphernalia.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Central Market | url= | email=
| address=Vodnikov trg | lat=46.05117 | long=14.50959 | directions=right bank of the Ljubljanica river, 200 m from the Triple Bridges
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=The central, open-air market features a wide array of local produce (exact items vary depending on the season), as well as local cheeses, breads and meats in the adjacent building. If you're lucky, you may still find sellers who have wheeled in their vegetables from south of the city centre (Krakovo) by foot—although they are a dying breed. Open every morning and early afternoon except Sunday; most lively on Saturday mornings. On Fridays you can also visit the 'Open Kitchen' 08:00–21:00, March–October.}}

==Eat==

===Budget===
[[File:Horse meat hamburger at restaurant Hot' Horse, Ljubljana, Slovenia.jpg|thumb|300px|Hot Horse chain serves horse-burgers]]
* {{eat
| name=Odprta Kuhna | alt= | url=http://www.odprtakuhna.si/ | email=
| address= | lat=46.05109 | long=14.50777| directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Apr–Oct, F 10:00–21:00 | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2021-07-04
| content=Odprta Kuhna means "open kitchen". It's a collection of food stalls on Pogačarjev trg, just south of Triple Bridge.
}}

* {{eat
| name=Hot Horse | alt= | url=https://www.hot-horse.si/ | email=info@hot-horse.si
| address=BTC City, Šmartinska 152; Tivoli Park, Celovška 25 | lat=46.06723 | long=14.54366 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=M–Sa 10:00–22:00, closed Su &amp; holidays | price=€4-12
| lastedit=2021-09-04
| content=Horse-burger chain with four city outlets. Huge burgers and other dishes; you order and pay first at the machine.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Nobel Burek | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Miklošičeva 30 | lat=46.056069 | long=14.508084 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=24/7 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Open non-stop, so it's popular late at night. Different kinds of burek (a leafy dough pie filled with mince meat or cheese).
}}
* {{eat
| name=Klobasarna | alt= | url=https://www.klobasarna.si/ | email=
| address=Ciril Metodov trg 15 | lat=46.05037 | long=14.50776 | directions=next to Sokol and Mediterano
| phone=+386 51 605 017 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 11:00-16:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Hole-in-the-wall fast food restaurant serving seasonal Slovenian soups with traditional sausages and bread. You order and pay first at the machine.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Govinda's | alt= | url=http://radhagovinda.si/ | email=
| address=Žibertova 23, Ljubljana - Šiška | lat=46.063 | long=14.499 | directions=
| phone=+386 590 58381 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 11:00-17:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Self-service buffet with vegetarian and vegan Indian food, great value.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Cafe Capri | alt=Kavarna Kapri | url=https://capri.cafe | email=mail@cafecapri.si
| address=Ljubljana, Petkovskovo nabrezje, 33 | lat=46.05227 | long=14.51061 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=08:00-14:00 | price=€5-10
| lastedit=2022-09-19
| content=A cozy cafe in the very center of Ljubljana, just a few steps away from the famous Dragon Bridge, offers healthy, delicious and inexpensive breakfasts and brunches. All dishes here are made from scratch and prepared fresh. Full bar always available with variety of any drinks: fragrant coffee, tea, fresh squeezed juices and homemade lemonades, Italian and Slovenian wines, beer, spirits and cocktails.
}}
* {{Eat
|name=Restavracija Mandala |url=https://restavracija-mandala.si/
|address=Podhod Ajdovščina. close to bus stop Ajdovščina |lat=46.0534087 |long=14.50469280 |directions=Accessed down a flight of stairs.
|hours=11:00-18:00 closed Sa &amp; Su
|lastedit=2023-10-13
|content=Vegan self-service restaurant. Food sold by weight.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Falafel | alt= | url=http://www.falafel.si/en/ | email=
| address=Trubarjeva cesta 40 | lat=46.052543 | long=14.510967 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2023-09-23
| content=The name is a clue. They also offer mezze dishes.
}}
* {{Eat
|name=Roza Slon |alt=Pink Elephant |url=http://www.rozaslon.si/
|address=Trg Osvobodilne fronte 14. |lat=46.0574678 |long=14.508947 |directions=across the road from bus station.
|hours=closed Sure |price=€7.90
|lastedit=2023-10-20
|content=Restaurant/takeaway offering tasty &amp; healthy Thai meals with a choice of beers &amp; soft drinks. they are also at a few other locations in the city. Some vegan options.
}}

===Mid-range===
* {{eat
| name=Gostilna Portal | alt= | url=https://www.portal-m.si/ | email=portalm@siol.net
| address=Zaloška cesta 110 | lat=46.0558 | long=14.5469 | directions=Bus 11, 20, 25
| phone=+386 1 5400 166 | tollfree=
| hours=Su-Th 09:00-23:00, F Sa 09:00-01:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=This is a B&amp;B in the eastern burbs, known as a Serbian restaurant - good for meat lovers. Loud live music at weekends.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Da-bu-da | alt= | url=http://www.dabuda.si | email=
| address=Šubičeva 1a | lat=46.051 | long=14.502 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 425 3060 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 11:00-22:00, Sa 12:00-22:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Thai food and cocktail bar, great atmosphere.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Figovec | alt= | url=https://figovec.si/ | email=
| address=Gosposvetska 1 | lat=46.055 | long=14.504 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 426 4410 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 11:00-23:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Popular place serving pony steaks, horse goulash, and traditional Slovenian food.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Foculus | alt= | url=https://foculus.si/ | email=
| address=Gregorciceva 3 | lat=46.048 | long=14.502 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 421 9295 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 11:00-22:30 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Flamboyantly decorated pizzeria and salad restaurant.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Čad | alt=formerly Pod Rožnikom | url=http://www.gostilna-cad.si/ | email=
| address=Cesta na Roznik 18 | lat=46.055 | long=14.482 | directions=near Zoo
| phone=+386 1 251 3446 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 11:00-23:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Specialises in grilled dishes from the Balkans; good value.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Gostilna Sokol | alt= | url=https://www.gostilna-sokol.com/ | email=
| address=Ciril Metodov trg 18 | lat=46.05 | long=14.507 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 439 6855 | tollfree=
| hours=M-Sa 07:00-23:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Authentic Slovenian cuisine, with serving staff got up in traditional costume. So inevitably it's touristy, but good food in huge portions and very good value for money.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Joe Pena's Cantina | alt= | url=http://www.joepenas.si/ | email=
| address=Cankarjeva 6 | lat=46.053 | long=14.503 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 421 5800 | tollfree=
| hours=M-Sa 11:00-22:00, Su 12:00-22:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Popular Mexican restaurant.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Julija | alt= | url=https://julijarestaurant.com/ | email=
| address=Stari trg 9 | lat=46.048 | long=14.506 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 425 6463 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 11:30-00:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Filling fare of Italian pasta and risotto dishes.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Cafe Romeo | url=http://caferomeo.si/ | email=
| address=Stari trg 6 | lat=46.04793 | long=14.50598 | directions=Facing Juilija 
| phone=+386 1 40 706 070 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-Sa 10:00-01:00, Su 10:00-00:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Riverside cafe, the pancakes are their specialty. 
}}
* {{eat
| name=Jurman | alt= | url=https://www.jurman.si/ | email=
| address=Zaloška 151 | lat=46.056 | long=14.556 | directions=
| phone=+386 51 358 358 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 10:00-22:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Family-friendly reliable comfort-food place in the burbs.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Ljubljanski Dvor | alt= | url=https://ljubljanskidvor.si/ | email=
| address=Dvorni trg 1 | lat=46.049 | long=14.505 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 251 6555 | tollfree=
| hours=M-Sa 10:00-00:00, Su 12:00-23:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Pizzeria with nice patio overlooking the river, the quality of food is uneven.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Pri Škofu | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Rečna 8 | lat=46.044 | long=14.504 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 426 4508 | tollfree=
| hours=W Th 12:00-21:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Mostly trad and Med fare, with vegetarian options.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Šestica | alt= | url=http://www.sestica.si/ | email=
| address=Slovenska 40 | lat=46.053 | long=14.504 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 242 0855 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 10:00-23:00, Sa 12:00-23:00, Su 12:00-17:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Serves hearty meat dishes such as sausages, horse fillets, and steak as well as pasta and risotto.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Špajza | alt= | url=http://sorbararestaurants.si/menu/menu_15122020.pdf | email=
| address=Gornji trg 28 | lat=46.046 | long=14.509 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 425 3094 | tollfree=
| hours=M-Sa 11:00-21:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=It's larger than it looks from the street, with several candlelit rooms leading to the outside terrace. Trad cuisine, good reviews for quality and service.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Zhong Hua | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Trubarjeva 50 | lat=46.052 | long=14.512 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 230 1665 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 11:00-21:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Decent Chinese restaurant near Dragon Bridge.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Gostilna Pod Vrbo | alt= | url=http://podvrbo.si/ | email=gostilna@podvrbo.si
| address=Ziherlova 36 | lat=46.041 | long=14.503 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 280 8892 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 11:00-22:00, Sa 12:00-22:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Huge range of Slovenian fare, generous portions.
}}

===Splurge===

* {{eat
| name=AS Aperitivo | alt= | url=http://asaperitivo.com/ | email=
| address=Copova Ulica 5A | lat=46.05162 | long=14.50442 | directions=north side of Triple Bridge.
| phone=+386 1 425 4168 | tollfree=
| hours=Su-Th 10:00-01:00, F Sa 10:00-02:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Trendy spot with two areas, for casual dining or the restaurant. Mostly positive reviews.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Cubo | alt= | url=https://www.cubo.si/ | email=
| address=Šmartinska 55 | lat=46.064 | long=14.527 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 521 1515 | tollfree=
| hours=M-Sa 12:00-22:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Med cuisine, earns consistent good reviews.
}}
* {{eat
| name=JB | alt= | url=https://www.jb-slo.com | email=info@jb-slo.com
| address=Miklošičeva 17 | lat=46.05726 | long=14.50823 | directions=south flank of railway station
| phone=+386 1 430 7070 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 12:00-15:00, 18:00-23:00, Sa 18:00-23:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Modern international fare, pricey by local standards, and mixed reviews on food quality.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Krpan | alt= | url=http://gostilna-krpan.si/ | email=
| address=24 Ob Ljubljanici | lat=46.054 | long=14.53 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 521 1220 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Good seafood restaurant.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Manna | alt= | url=https://www.restavracija-manna.si/ | email=
| address=Eipprova 1A | lat=46.043 | long=14.505 | directions=
| phone=+386 31 592 974 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=W-Sa 12:00-23:00, Su 12:00-17:00 | price= | lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=Excellent traditional dishes with slick friendly service. 
}}
* {{eat
| name=Strelec | alt= | url=https://strelec.kaval-group.si/ | email=strelec@kaval-group.si
| address=Grajska planota 1 | lat=46.04902 | long=14.50916 | directions=Within castle
| phone=+386 31 687 648 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-F 18:00-23:00, Sa 12:00-22:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-20
| content=This is within Archer's Tower of the castle, with a terrace overlooking the city. So you're paying for the great location but the food also scores.
}}
* {{Eat
|name=Gaudi&amp;Naan |url=https://www.gaudi.si/
|address=Trubarjeva cesta 7 vhod iz Malega trga |lat=46.052187516 |long=14.50724312 |directions=In Mali Trg off Mala Ulica
|lastedit=2023-10-19
|content=Fine quality vegan restaurant
}}

==Drink==
[[File:Slovenian Philharmonic Orchestra (Ljubljana).jpg | thumb | 300px | Philharmonic Hall with castle behind]]
Most of Ljubljana’s bars tend to cluster on the streets running parallel to the river, radiating from Prešernov trg, which is the main square in Ljubljana. The more interesting bars tend to be on the backstreets, rather than directly facing the river. Part of the joy of this city is stumbling across these places, but these are few to start you off.

Cheaper bars can already be found just outside the old town and near university buildings.

=== Free tap water locations ===

The application [https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/tap-water-ljubljana/id563888400?mt=8 Tap Water Ljubljana] is intended for all who wish to quench their thirst and refresh themselves during the spring and summer months with freely available water from fountains found in 17 locations throughout Ljubljana, mostly they are in city centre. Application is available on App Store.

===Cafes===

* {{drink
| name=Cafe Antico | url= | email=
| address=Stari Trg 17 | lat=46.04735 | long=14.50644 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Great ambiance - bare wooden floors, high tables and stools, and vaulted ceiling.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Čajna Hiša | alt=The Tea House | url=https://www.cha.si/ | email=
| address=Stari trg 3 | lat=46.04823 | long=14.50625 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Closed Su | price=
| content=This is a quirky little coffee and tea room, offering many variations on those warm beverages as well as basic breakfasts and lunches. The background music is impeccably cool, and the atmosphere is ideal for some elegant loafing. Linked to the café is a teashop selling drinking paraphernalia and loads of different fruity flavoured teas by the 100g.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Le Petite Cafe | url=https://www.lepetit.si/ | email=
| address=Trg Francoske Revolucije 4 | lat=46.04727 | long=14.50244 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Very popular corner cafe.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Sax Hostel &amp; Sax pub | url= | email=
| address=Eipprova 7 | lat=46.04318 | long=14.50458 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Really cool colourful spray-painted cafe/bar along the canal. The place also serves as a hostel.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Zvezda | url=https://www.facebook.com/KavarnaZvezdaWolfova/ | email=
| address=Wolfova 14 | lat=46.05054 | long=14.50457 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Cafe with great ices and pastries.
}}

===Bars===

* {{drink
| name=Cutty Sark | url=http://www.cuttysarkpub.si/en/home/ | email=
| address=Knafljev Prehod 1 | lat=46.05132 | long=14.50470 | directions=Opposite Cantina Mexicana
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Lively pub with raucous atmosphere. Usually has live music.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Lepa Žoga | url=https://www.facebook.com/LepaZoga | email=
| address=Celovška 43 | lat=46.06134 | long=14.49605 | directions=Near Tivoli Park
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Main sports cafe/bar with sports regalia along the wall and a good, mixed crowd on most nights. Shows international rugby, all sorts of football games (European, English, Italian and other leagues) and other live sports. Has the best TV coverage in the city, ranging from Sky Sports to local TV stations.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Od Žmavca sosed pa ud brata prjatu | alt=Žmavc's neighbor and my brother's pal aka Žmavc | url=http://barzmauc.sqwiz.si/ | email=
| address=Rimska cesta 21 | lat=46.04772 | long=14.49830 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 251 0324 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Markets to the "creative urban type." Burgers, coffee and alcoholic drinks.&lt;!--according to photos on their website --&gt;
}}
* {{drink
| name=Pod Skalco | url= | email=
| address=Gosposka 19 | lat=46.04665 | long=14.50400 | directions=just opposite to the Križanke auditorium, next to the City Museum of Ljubljana, on the back of the National &amp; University Library
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 06:30-03:00, Sa Su 17:30-03:00 | price=
| content=Popular student pub with an almost 150-year-long tradition, frequented almost exclusively by locals. Loud music.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Vinoteka Movia | url=https://www.movia.si/en | email=
| address=Mestni trg 2 | lat=46.04971 | long=14.50680 | directions=Next to the Town Hall
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Anyone with any interest in wine should visit here. The cosy, candlelit wine bar comes with knowledgeable barmen who can recommend a wine based on your tastes. The wine glasses are huge, so it's hard to tell if they were being stingy or if it has simply spread out. Be careful about asking for ‘samples’, as they will charge you full price. The prices can vary from modest to a remortgage.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Sir William's pub | alt= | url=https://untappd.com/v/sir-williams-pub/257535 | email=sirwilliamspub@gmail.com
| address=Tavčarjeva ulica 8a | lat=46.05431 | long=14.50739 | directions=
| phone=+386-599-44-825 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 08:00 - 01:00, Sa 10:00 - 14:00 and 19:00 - 01:00, Su 17:00 - 24:00 | price=
|lastedit=2023-10-20
| content=Located in the Art Nouveau part of Ljubljana city centre, offers more than 120 beer varieties and a large choice of teas and wines. It is vibrant in the evenings, particularly when it hosts themed events and beer tastings, while during the day it has a more coffee house-like atmosphere, offering its guests an opportunity to browse through a newspaper or read a book in peace. The staff speak several languages. Free wireless internet access is available.
}}
* {{Drink
|name=Lajbah |url=https://lajbah.si/en |email=info@lajbah.si
|address=Grudnovo nabrežje 15 |lat=46.0442077 |long=14.506701553 |directions=bus 2, 3, 3B, 11, 19, 19I, 27 stop Gornji trg then walk down Grudnovo nabrežje alongside river.
|lastedit=2023-10-20
|content=Beer hall with outdoor area. Large choice of craft beers &amp; mainly Asian food.
}}
* {{Drink
|name=Tozd |url=
|address=Cankarjeva cesta 8 |lat=46.0528281 |long=14.5020837
|phone=+386 40 728 882
|lastedit=2023-09-23
|content=Bar with coffee &amp; craft beers}}
* {{Drink
|name=Tektonix Craft Brewery |url=https://tektonik.beer/ |email=info@tektonik.beer
|address=Likozarjeva ulica 1 |lat=46.059870730 |long=14.50524128
|phone=+386 69 774 211
|lastedit=2023-10-19
|content=Microbrewery &amp; bar close to railway station. Brewery tours available.
}}
* {{Drink
|name=Union Pub |url=https://www.union-experience.si/en/experience-union-pub
|address=Celovška cesta 22 |lat=46.0597672 |long=14.498520462
|lastedit=2023-09-16
|content=Pub at the Union brewery. food available. This is the opposite of a micro brewery.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Gas Station | alt= | url=https://m.enjoi.si/c/EvaylL9EZl102 | email=
| address=Savska cesta 5 | lat=46.065 | long=14.525 | directions=North-East of main railway station. Bus 2 Savsko Naselje or 12, 12D, 27, 27K Središka
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2023-11-06
| content=Popular quirky bar with a 1961 Chrysler Newport as part of the seating.
}}

===Clubs===
Ljubljana has several good nightclubs (discothèques). The clubs hold special events, they will play a certain syle of music on certain nights, etc. Some will also impose a strict dress code and age limits.

* {{drink
| name=Metelkova mesto | url=http://www.metelkovamesto.org/ | email=
| address=Metelkova 8 | lat=46.05700 | long=14.51691 | directions=next to the train station
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Daily 22:00-04:00 | price=free or up to €10
| content=It's a squat with 6 clubs, each with its own style of music and programme. Gala Hala is the biggest and the music is very diverse - from funk nights to hip-hop and indie to rap and strange fun music. It has also concerts and an outside garden where they also grill in the summer. Gromka is a smaller one usually admission free and the music also differs from night to night. Usually it's rock/alternative hits or rockabilly or fun 90s music. It has also concerts. Menza pri Koritu is the most alternative and it has mainly alternative, metal, punk concerts and after parties. Channel Zero is more about electronics (also concerts) - d'n'b, dub, electro, house. Jalla Jalla is the smallest one with sometimes obscure, experimental music. Tiffany is a gay club with usually electronic parties. In Metelkova everybody can find a place for himself (usually the most is happening on weekends) and you can just walk from one to another club and see what is going on (if there is no admission).
}}
* {{drink
| name=K4 | alt= | url=https://lok4cija.si/ | email=
| address=Kersnikova 4 | lat=46.0557 | long=14.50403 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-Su 22:00-02:30/04:00 | price=
| content=National and international DJs play electronic music.
}}

==Sleep==
[[File:Ljubljana BW 2014-10-09 10-59-33.jpg | thumb | 300px | Ursuline Church on Congress Square ]]
=== Budget ===
* {{sleep
| name=Aladin Hostel | alt= | url=http://www.aladin-hostel.com | email=info@aladin-hostel.com
| address=Tugomerjeva 56 | lat=46.071 | long=14.4845 | directions=
| phone=+386 41 666 477 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Dorm €15
| lastedit=2021-06-19 
| content=Small friendly hostel. 
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Celica | alt= | url=https://www.hostelcelica.com/en/ | email=
| address=Metelkova 8 | lat=46.0566 | long=14.5165 | directions=south side of railway station 
| phone=+386 1 230 9700 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Dorm €20 | checkin= | checkout=
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=This was the military brig, get caught in town without a pass and The Cells was where you'd spend the night. Then they got the designers in, how come Guantanamo never cottoned on to this concept? Good to know: each cell was individually designed by a Slovenian artist. 
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hostel Tabor | alt=Dijaški dom | url=https://hostel.ddt.si/ | email=hostel@ddt.si
| address=Kotnikova 4 | lat=46.054 | long=14.513 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 234 8840 | tollfree= | fax=+386 1 234 8855
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €54
| lastedit=2023-12-14
| content=Clean friendly place in student residence, only open July and Aug. In 2023 the dorm is not available.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Fluxus Hostel | alt= | url=http://www.fluxus-hostel.com/en/home.php | email=
| address=Tomšičeva 4 | lat=46.052 | long=14.503 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Dorm €21 ppn
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Small clean central place with 8- and 6-bed dorm.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Most Hostel | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Petkovškovo nabrežje 41 | lat=46.0522 | long=14.5118 | directions=by Dragon Bridge
| phone=+386 41 662 266 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Dorm €21 ppn, double €60
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Cute friendly hostel, very central.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Vila Veselova | alt= | url=https://vilaveselovahostel.com/ | email=
| address=Veselova 14 | lat=46.051 | long=14.497 | directions=by Tivoli Park
| phone=+386 5165 5254 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Budget / hostel rooms in a 100-year-old villa west side of town.
}}
* {{Sleep
|name=The Fuzzy Log |url=https://all.accor.com/hotel/C0Q0/index.en.shtml
|address=Miklošičeva cesta 9 |lat=46.055624952 |long=14.50723709 |directions=550 metres from Railway station
|checkin=3PM |checkout=11AM
|lastedit=2023-11-06
|content=Unusual hostel on 7th floor of Ibis Styles hotel. featuring tents, cabins, and capsules. Buffet breakfast available.
}}

=== Mid-range ===
* {{sleep
| name=BIT Center Hotel | url=https://www.bit-center.net/ | email=
| address=Litijska 57 | lat=46.049 | long=14.549 | directions=2 km east of centre, take bus 5, 9, 13 or 22
| phone=+386 1 548 0055 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Dorm €15, B&amp;B double €50 
| checkin= | checkout=
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Basic functional place which also contains a hostel. 
}}
* {{sleep
| name=City Hotel | alt= | url=https://www.cityhotel.si/ | email=
| address=Dalmatinova 15 | lat=46.054 | long=14.508 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 239 0000 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €110
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Decent central place with clean rooms, thin walls.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Park | alt= | url=https://www.hotel-bb.com/en/hotel/ljubljana-park | email=info@hotelpark.si
| address=Tabor 9 | lat=46.054 | long=14.515 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 300 2500 | tollfree= | fax=+386 1 433 0546
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €90
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Clean central mid to budget hotel with 145 rooms. They formerly also offered "hostel" rooms, cheaper but bare; these are not on offer in 2021.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Katrca 1905 | url=http://www.katrca.si/ | email=
| address=Rožna Dolina I/26 | lat=46.051 | long=14.485 | directions=Tivoli district 
| phone=+386 1 422 8840 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=B&amp;B double €80
| checkin= | checkout=
| lastedit=2021-06-19 
| content=Pleasant place in a quiet district, has only five rooms.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=M Hotel | alt= | url=https://www.m-hotel.si/ | email=
| address=Derceva 4 | lat=46.069 | long=14.489 | directions=Bus 1, 3, 15 or 16 to Kino Siska
| phone=+386 1 513 7000 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €90
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Boxy modern place 2 km northwest of centre with neat, spacious rooms.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Pension Tavcar | alt= | url=http://www.penzion-tavcar.si/gb/index.htm | email=
| address=Cesta v Šmartno 7 | lat=46.075 | long=14.559 | directions=Bus 12 to Hrastje, walk back 200 m and make a right
| phone=+386 1 546 6970 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Clean well-run place northeast edge of city.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Mrak | alt= | url=https://hotelmrak.si/ | email=
| address=Rimska 4 | lat=46.047 | long=14.502 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 421 9650 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Colourful rooms, nice restaurant, and great central location. Doesn't have a parking lot so you'd pay pricey central parking rates.
}}

=== Splurge ===
[[File:Ljubljana castle - inner court 2.jpg | thumb | 300px | Ljubljana castle often hosts events ]]
* {{sleep
| name=Austria Trend Hotel | alt= | url=https://www.austria-trend.at/en/hotels/ljubljana | email=
| address=Dunajska cesta 154 | lat=46.082 | long=14.514 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 588 2525 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €140
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Modern slab with 214 rooms, spacious and good sound-proofing. All rooms have air-con, safe, minibar, hair dryer, flat screen, satellite TV and radio.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Best Western Premier Hotel Slon | alt= | url=https://www.hotelslon.com/ | email=sales@hotelslon.com
| address=Slovenska 34 | lat=46.053 | long=14.504 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 470 11 00 | tollfree= | fax=+386 1 251 71 64
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €120 | lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Modern chain hotel with clean and comfy rooms. Their website is uninformative about pets, but it's said that in 1552 Archduke Maximilian stayed at an inn on this spot in the company of an elephant.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Grand Hotel Union | alt= | url=https://www.uhcollection.si/grand-hotel-union | email=
| address=Miklosiceva 1 | lat=46.053 | long=14.506 | directions=
| phone=+386 1 308 12 70 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €140
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Splendid Art Nouveau building. Large comfy rooms though showing their age, some have views of the castle. Restaurant, fitness centre, sauna, and rooftop pool.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Lev | alt= | url=https://www.uhcollection.si/hotel-lev | email=
| address=Vošnjakova 1 | lat=46.056 | long=14.503 | directions=by Tivoli Park
| phone=+386 1 433 21 55 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €100
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Glassy high rise building, smart and comfy. In 2020 / 21 it was mothballed and guests were shifted elsewhere - "re-protected" is their splendidly unctuous euphemism for this.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Central Hotel | alt= | url=https://www.uhcollection.si/central-hotel | email=
| address=Miklosiceva 9 | lat=46.056 | long=14.507 | directions=300 m south of bus &amp; train stations
| phone=+386 1 308 43 00 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €90
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Central boxy modern hotel, comfy and brightly decorated. Reception is on the 7th floor: it's a "concept" apparently.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Four Points by Sheraton | alt=formerly Hotel Mons | url=https://www.marriott.com/hotels/travel/ljufp-four-points-ljubljana-mons/ | email=
| address=Pot za Brdom 4 | lat=46.052 | long=14.453 | directions=5 km west of centre
| phone=+386 1 470 2700 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €110
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=4-star business hotel by the forest west edge of town, convenient for motorists. With spa and fitness centre.
}}

=== Farther out ===
* {{sleep
| name=Ljubljana Resort | alt=formerly Avtokamp Ježica | url=https://www.ljubljanaresort.si/en/ | email=resort@gpl.si 
| address=Dunajska 270 | lat=46.098 | long=14.519 | directions=5 km north of centre, take bus 6, 8 or 11
| phone=+386 1 589 0130 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Camping €12 ppn
| lastedit=2021-06-19 
| content=Camping and tourer caravan site edge of town by River Sava. Also has rooms for B&amp;B plus swimming pool, sauna, fitness centre, badminton, volleyball, bowling, play area and restaurant.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Grandvid | alt= | url=https://grandvidhotel.si/ | email=info@granvidhotel.si
| address=Dolenjska 336, Lavrica | lat=46.000 | long=14.555 | directions=7 km southeast of centre
| phone=+386 1 360 2200 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €85
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=Clean modern place with restaurant, on bus route to city. 
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Kongo Hotel &amp; Casino | alt=formerly Motel Grosuplje | url=https://www.admiral.si/si/hotel-casino-kongo | email=info@kongo.si
| address=Ljubljanska 65, 1290 Grosuplje | lat=45.9679 | long=14.6567 | directions=15 km southeast of Ljubljana on A2, city bus 3G
| phone=+386 1 781 0200 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=B&amp;B double €80
| lastedit=2021-06-19
| content=4-star hotel handy for motorists and business travellers. Comfy rooms, restaurant, and of course the casino.
}}

==Stay safe==
Ljubljana is one of the safer capitals you'll visit in Europe. Remarkably safe during the day, you should have no problems wandering at night, provided you are not desperately looking for trouble.

With that said, be wise to not wander into the rougher parts of Ljubljana at night, though they are located far from the city centre and not commonly frequented by tourists. Areas to avoid include Fužine, Rakova Jelša, Štepanjsko naselje, southern Vič (near and south of the motorway), western parts of Šiška, and Moste. The streets immediately south of the train station have become seedier since 2020 but still remain relatively safe in comparison to other European cities.

Tivoli Park is generally safe and a very popular destination for picnics or taking an afternoon stroll for an average Ljubljanian, but just as anywhere in the world it is recommended that you don't put your guard down and avoid larger groups of teenagers hanging around in the park late at night, as thefts and sexual assaults have been reported.

After a long time there were reports in 2023 of new attacks on LGBT+ people in the center of Ljubljana on the Pride day.

==Connect==
[[File:Postcard of Ljubljana 1900.jpg | thumb | 300px | Poor internet? Send a postcard. ]]
As of 2025, Ljubljana has excellent 5G and 4G coverage from Telekom (Mobitel), A1, and Telemach with speeds up to 1 Gbps.

===Internet===
Free internet access is available at:
*{{listing
| name=Faculty of Computer and Information Science and the Faculty of Electrical Engineering | url=http://www.fri.uni-lj.si | email=
| address=Tržaska 25 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}

Almost free internet access is available at:
*{{listing
| name=Slovenian Tourist Information Centre | url= | email=
| address=Krekov trg 10 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}

== Cope ==
[[File:Veleposlanistvo ZDA v Ljubljani Embassy of USA in Ljubljana Slovenia.jpg | thumb | 300px | US Embassy by Tivoli Park ]] 
=== Embassies ===

* {{flag|Greece}} {{listing
| name=Greece | url=http://www.mfa.gr/ljubljana | email=gremb.lju@mfa.gr
| address=Trnovski pristan 14, Ljubljana 1000 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+386 1 420 1400, +386 1 410 1410, +386 51 449 956 (Emergencies) | tollfree= | fax=+386 1 281 1114
| hours=M-F 08:30-16:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-21 
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Romania}} {{listing
| name=Romania | alt= | url=http://ljubljana.mae.ro/en | email=ljubljana@mae.ro
| address=Smrekarjeva 33a | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+386 1 505 7335 | tollfree= | fax=+386 1 505 5432
| hours=M-F 9:00-17:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-12-03
| content=
}}
* {{flag|United Kingdom}} {{listing
| name=United Kingdom | url=http://ukinslovenia.fco.gov.uk/en | email=
| address=4th floor Trg Republike 3, Ljubljana 1000 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+386 1 200 3910 | tollfree= | fax=+33 7 1425 0174 (France)
| hours=M-F 08:00-16:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-06-21 
| content=
}}
* '''Other nations''' with embassies in the city include [https://si.usembassy.gov/ United States] cheek-by-jowl with [https://rus-slo.mid.ru/ Russia] and [https://laibach.diplo.de/ Germany] by Tivoli Park, plus Turkey, India, Egypt, Austria, Belgium, Netherlands, Ireland, Spain, Italy, France, Sweden and Switzerland.

== Go next ==
Ljubljana is at the hub of transport routes across this relatively small country, so you can easily reach anywhere else in Slovenia and across its borders. Here's a selection:
* [[Bled]] is a picturesque town 1 hour away. Hire a rowboat on the lake to visit the island church, then see the castle. 
* [[Triglav National Park]] and the [[Julian Alps]] near Bled for outdoor activities: hiking, mountaineering, rafting, canyoning, paragliding, skydiving and so on. 
* [[Postojna]] has the vast Postojna Caves and Predjama Castle, an Škocjan Caves are in nearby [[Divača]].
* The coast is short, sandwiched between Croatia's Istrian resorts and the industry and marshes of Italy. [[Koper]] is the largest coast resort, [[Piran]] is the prettiest.
* [[Kamnik]] is a button-cute little town 45 min north of Ljubljana, just below the Kamnik Alps. It has a perfectly preserved medieval town centre, with the ski resort of Krvavec above.
* [[Zagreb]] in Croatia, 2 hr 30 min away, has an extensive medieval centre. 
* [[Trieste]] (1½–2 hr) is in Italy yet redolent of the last days of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. 
* [[Rijeka]] in Croatia (2 hr 30 min) for the Istrian peninsula, ferries to the Adriatic islands, and transport south to [[Zadar]] and [[Split]]. 


{{guidecity}}
{{geo|46.05|14.50}}
{{IsPartOf|Central Slovenia}}</text>
      <sha1>qz15d1xy27uka8z2e6c4lupzzhiaez5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
