<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikivoyage</sitename>
    <dbname>enwikivoyage</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.46.0-wmf.24</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="1728" case="first-letter">Event</namespace>
      <namespace key="1729" case="first-letter">Event talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sofia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33157</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5232055</id>
      <parentid>5212631</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T00:24:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Renamed user 1e2b4586bbfd0bf65c1fd30d2247ed9b</username>
        <id>2327039</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rewrote this.</comment>
      <origin>5232055</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="91586" sha1="30653b6z1h5celfcez7g8kh20y4rr3j" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Sofia banner.JPG|unesco=yes|caption=Independence Square lit up at night|unesco_cc=yes}}
'''Sofia''' (София) is the capital and largest city of [[Bulgaria]], with about 2 million citizens (including suburbs). It is a dynamic European capital, distinguished by its unique combination of European and communist-style architecture as well as many beautiful Orthodox churches, including the grand Alexander Nevsky Cathedral and the medieval frescos of Boyana Church (a [[UNESCO World Heritage Site]]). Furthermore, it claims to be one of the few European capitals with beautiful scenery and a developed ski-resort so close to it, the Vitosha mountain.

==Understand==
{{climate chart
|Sofia
|-3.9 |3.5 |35.9
|-2.4 |6.5 |35.5
|1.1 |11.4 |45.3
|5.3 |16.7 |52.3
|9.8 |21.4 |73.1
|13.4 |25.2 |81.6
|15.3 |27.8 |64.7
|15.0 |28.3 |53.1
|10.9 |23.3 |52.3
|6.3 |17.6 |53.9
|1.9 |10.7 |38.1
|-2.4 |4.6 |39.9
|jansnow=249.0 |febsnow=210.0 |marsnow=154.0 |aprsnow=30.0 |maysnow=0.0 |junsnow=0.0 |julsnow=0.0 |augsnow=0.0 |sepsnow=0.0 |octsnow=15.0 |novsnow=107.0 |decsnow=210.0
|float=right
|clear=right
|source=[[:w:Sofia]]
|description=
}}
[[File:Russian church (37591925970).jpg|thumb|Aerial view towards snow-covered Vitosha]]

The city has had several names over the past 2,500 years: the Romans called it ''Serdika'' when they took it from a Thracian tribe with a similar name, the Slavs called it ''Sredets'' when they integrated it into the first Bulgarian Empire, and the Ottomans called it ''Sofia'', the Greek word for "wisdom", when they made it their base for the Balkans. You can still find remnants from each of these societies in parts of the city.

People first came here for the hot water springs that still flow abundantly in the centre of the city. Many of the later Roman emperors took a liking to these thermal baths, and developed the city into a regional capital; Emperor Constantine even considered building his imperial capital here instead of [[Constantinople]].

From there, Sofia has had ups and downs; sacked by the Huns, then a fortress for the first Bulgarians, then sieged and rebuilt by the Ottomans. The decline of Sofia towards the end of the Ottoman Empire was followed by the rejuvenation after the Russian liberation in 1878, when Sofia was chosen as the capital of Bulgaria at the First National Constituent Assembly, and followed by a brisk and straightforward period of construction. During the Second World War, thousands of buildings were destroyed or damaged by bombing campaigns, until the Soviet Red Army occupied Sofia and established a Communist government, which constructed Stalinist Gothic public buildings and concrete tower blocks. Newer construction has led to glass-fronted office buildings and top-class residential neighbourhoods.

===Tourist information===
*[https://www.visitsofia.bg/en/ VisitSofia.bg], Sofia's official tourist information website. Available in several languages, including English.
*{{Listing|name=Main tourist information centre|address=22 Tsar Osvoboditel Blvd|lat=42.6932596|long=23.3343331|directions=in the underpass of Sofia University, under the intersection south of the main building|phone=+359 2 491 83 44|hours=M-F 09:30 – 18:00|lastedit=2024-06-18}}
*{{Listing|name=Tourist information centre (the Largo)|address=Nezavisimost Sqr|lat=42.6979560|long=23.3219135|directions=in the pedestrian underpass/entrance to the Serdika II metro station|phone=+359 2 49 49 315|hours=M–F 09:30–18:00|lastedit=2024-06-18}}
*{{Listing|name=Tourist information kiosk|alt=''Chitalnyata'' (The Reading Room)|url=https://www.chitalnyata.bg/|lat=42.6949271|long=23.3247443|directions=kiosk in the City Garden, the small park in front of the National Theatre|phone=+359 885 921 620|hours=10:00 – 20:00 (every day)|lastedit=2024-06-18|content=A small reading room/library in a glass kiosk that also serves as a tourist information point. (You can get a library membership by donating at least one book, but the books are only in Bulgarian.)}}

==Get in==
===By plane===
* {{listing
   | type = go
   | name = Sofia Airport
   | alt = Летище "Васил Левски" - София {{IATA|SOF}}
   | url = https://sofia-airport.eu/en/
   | email = 
   | address = 
   | lat = 42.695
   | long = 23.408333
   | directions = 9 km east of the city center
   | phone = 
   | tollfree = 
   | fax = 
   | hours = 
   | price = 
   | wikipedia = Sofia Airport
   | lastedit = 2025-07-23
   | image = Inside Sofia Airport 20090409 033.JPG
   | wikidata = Q127951
   | content = It is the busiest airport in Bulgaria, with annual passenger traffic of approximately 4 million.
}}

Over 20 airlines operate service to/from Sofia, with direct flights to/from [[Athens]], [[Paris]], [[Vienna]], [[London]], [[Rome]], [[Amsterdam]], [[Munich]], [[Warsaw]] and other European cities. There are also domestic flights from [[Varna]] and [[Burgas]].

Along with traditional carriers, some low-cost companies serving Bulgaria are [http://www.easyjet.com/ EasyJet] (to/from London-Gatwick, Madrid, Manchester) and [http://www.wizzair.com/ Wizz Air ] (to/from Paris-Beauvais, Barcelona, Brussels-Charleroi, Dortmund, Eindhoven, London-Luton, Milan-Bergamo, Rome-Fiumicino, Valencia) and RyanAir. [http://www.air.bg/en Bulgaria Air], the national carrier operates service to/from [[Alicante]], [[Amsterdam]], [[Athens]], [[Barcelona]], [[Beirut]], [[Berlin Brandenburg Airport|Berlin]], [[Brussels]], [[Bucharest]], [[Frankfurt]], [[Istanbul]], [[Larnaca]], [[London]] (Gatwick &amp; Heathrow), [[Madrid]], [[Málaga]], [[Manchester]], [[Palma de Mallorca]], [[Paphos]], [[Paris]], [[Rome]], [[Skopje]], [[Tel Aviv]], [[Tirana]], [[Tripoli]], [[Valencia]], [[Vienna]] and [[Zürich]].

Budget airlines including EasyJet, Eurowings and Wizz Air operate from Terminal 1, while the traditional carriers including Bulgaria Air but also Ryanair operate from Terminal 2.

There is a [https://sofia-airport.eu/en/access/transportation/#shuttle-bus free shuttle bus] operating between Terminals 1 and 2 every 15–30 minutes between 05:00 and 23:00. Outside of those hours, a free shuttle bus can be requested at the information desk or you can use Busses #84 or 184 depending on direction (see below). After midnight you might asked to book a cab for such ride.

There are shops, cafes, post offices, ATMs, and money exchange offices at the airport.

To travel between the airport and the city centre:

* '''[http://www.metrosofia.com/en/sofia-airport Sofia Metro Line 4 (Yellow)]''' operates service to the airport between 05:30 and 24:00. The stop is a few metres outside of Terminal 2; follow signs for "Subway" until you leave the southeast corner of the building. The journey to the city centre takes 20–30 minutes. The journey to the central bus station takes approximately 35 minutes and a transfer is required. A single ticket costs 1.60 лв. You no longer need an extra ticket for each piece of large luggage. You can also buy a day ticket for all modes of public transport for 4 лв. The access gates as well as some ticket vending machines also accept credit cards and payment apps such as Apple Pay.
* '''Public Busses #84 and 184''' operates service between both terminals and the city centre. The journey takes 30–40 minutes. Tickets can be purchased from news stands or ticket machines in the airport as well as by contactless payment aboard. A single ticket costs 1.60 лв. An extra ticker for large luggage is no longer needed. The bus makes a stop at Orlov Most (Sofia University metro station), where you can transfer to the metro.
* '''Taxi''' service from the airport is regulated. [https://www.oktaxi.net/ OK Supertrans AD] is the only contracted taxi operator from the airport. It is best to request a taxi either from the taxi stand to the right when you leave the arrivals area or the taxi office right adjacent to the exit from the baggage reclaim. Beware of touts offering taxi service as well as non-contracted taxis with the fake "OK" logo which usually wait in front of the terminal instead on the official taxi rank besides it. A taxi to the city center will cost approximately 15 лв. The regulated taxi fare is: initial fee of 0.70 лв, price per km 0.79 лв in the day or 0.90 лв at night, price per minute of stay of 0.22 лв, price for ordering a taxi via phone of 0.50 лв. You can also use the [https://ridenow.taxi/en Ridenow Taxi app].

===By bus===
* {{go
| name=Central Bus Station | alt=''Tsentralna Avtogara'', Централна автогара | url=http://www.centralnaavtogara.bg/ | email=
| address=bul. "Knyaginya Maria-Luiza" 100 | lat=42.710278 | long=23.323333 | directions=in the north part of the city centre; on the same large boulevard that passes through Independence Sqr and Lion's Bridge
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2985753
| lastedit=2024-02-10
| content=Serves both national and international lines, but mainly the former. Schedules and fares are available in Bulgarian online. Next to the Central Railway Station, so it's served by the same metro station on Metro Line 2 (Blue). Also accessible via busses № 78, 85, 213, 305, 404, 413, and trams № 1, 3, 6, 7.
}}
* {{go
| name=International Bus Station / Bus Station Serdika | alt=Автогара Сердика | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.710984 | long=23.322164 | directions=right between the Central Railway Station and the Central Bus Station
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2024-02-10
| content=A parking lot with two low buildings with ticket offices on the sides. Used by international lines. The large Bulgarian company [https://union-ivkoni.com/en/ Union-Ivkoni] also uses it for some of its national lines, e.g. to [[Pernik]], [[Radomir]] and [[Kyustendil]].
}}

Three smaller bus stations serve national and local lines:
* {{go
| name=Bus Station West (Ovcha Kupel) | alt=''Avtogara Zapad'', Автогара Запад (Овча купел) | url= | email=
| address=bul. "Ovcha Kupel" 1 | lat=42.6726611 | long=23.2718127 | directions=in the Ovcha Kupel neighbourhood, several kilometres south-west of the city centre
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2024-02-10
| content=Mainly used by smaller companies serving local lines around Sofia (and the appearance matches), but also to [[Blagoevgrad]], [[Dupnitsa]] and [[Kyustendil]]. Accessible by trams № 4 and 11, and buses № 103, 107 and 260. The nearest metro station, Ovcha Kupel on Line 3 (Green), is {{km|1.4}} north along the same boulevard.
}}
* {{go
| name=Bus Station South | alt=Автогара Юг | url= | email=
| address=bul. "Dragan Tsankov" 23 | lat=42.668767 | long=23.352469 | directions=in the Iztok neighbourhood, several kilometres south-east of the city centre - beyond the Borisova Garden
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q12271078
| lastedit=2024-02-10
| content=A small prefab building huddled under the overpass where Dragan Tsankov Blvd goes over Samokov Blvd. Buses to [[Samokov]] and [[Velingrad]]. Accessible via buses № 67 and 413 ("Interpred" stop), as well as metro station Zholio Kyuri (Joliot-Curie) on Lines 1 and 4 (Red, Yellow) - 400 m/yd to the north of Bus Station South along the same boulevard.
}}
* {{go
| name=Bus Station Poduyane | alt=Автогара Подуяне | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.703373 | long=23.360053 | directions=between the neighbourhoods of Poduyane and Suha Reka, close to Georgi Asparuhov Stadium, several kilometres north-east of the city centre
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2024-02-10
| content=Another questionably looking shack. Buses to [[Botevgrad]], [[Etropole]] and [[Pravets]] north of Sofia (but there are also some that start from the Central Bus Station). Accessible via trolleybus № 1 and buses № 78, 79, 90, 100, 120 (but only 79 stops right in front of it). The nearest metro station is Hadzhi Dimitar, the end point of Line 3 (Green) - a 10-15 min walk; follow the large Vladimir Vazov Blvd east along the river until you reach a large intersection, then make sure you cross to the eastern side and head south - look to your left for the bus station's parking lot.
}}

Buses operate to/from [[Belgrade]] (5 hr, {{EUR|23}}) and other cities in [[Serbia]], [[Vienna]] (15½ hr, {{EUR|59}}) and other cities in [[Austria]], [[Paris]] (36 hr, {{EUR|120}}) and other cities in [[France]], [[Berlin]] (28 hr, {{EUR|110}}) and other cities in [[Germany]], [[Budapest]] (11-13 hr, {{EUR|48}}), and [[Prague]] (21 hr, {{EUR|63}}).

Nearby destinations like [[Bucharest#By bus|Bucharest]] (6 h from €15) and [[Skopje#By bus|Skopje]] (5 hr, €25) are also served &amp;mdash; see there for details.

===By train===
Sofia is perhaps the largest railway hub in the country. A list of all the available daily trains would resemble a description of Bulgaria's railway network. Nevertheless: 

A major line through North Bulgaria connects Sofia to '''[[Varna]]''' on the [[Bulgarian Black Sea Coast|Black Sea coast]] (8-8½ hr, sleeper cars available on overnight trains). It passes through [[Shumen]] (about 7 hr), [[Targovishte]] (6½ hr) and [[Pleven]] (3-3¾ hr). Off the line, [[Ruse]] (about 7 hr) and '''[[Veliko Tarnovo]]''' (5-6½&amp;nbsp;hr) require changing at Gorna Oryahovitsa. In the North-West, [[Vidin]] (5-6½ hr) and [[Vratsa]] (2-3 hr) require changing at Mezdra. The line crosses the Balkan Mountains through the scenic Iskar Gorge, about an hour away from Sofia, so keep your camera ready.

South of the [[Balkan Mountains]], another major line connects Sofia with '''[[Plovdiv]]''' (2½-3 hr) and with '''[[Burgas]]''' on the Black Sea (7-8 hr, sleeper cars on late trains). There's also the smaller Sub-Balkan Line which runs below the southern slopes of the mountains, through the Sub-Balkan Valleys. The network ensures direct trains from [[Yambol]] (6-6½ hr), [[Stara Zagora]] (5 hr), [[Svilengrad]] by the Greek/Turkish border (5 hr), and [[Pazardzhik]] (2-2½ hr).

Another line descends south from Sofia towards the Greek border, with direct trains from [[Pernik]] (40 min), [[Kyustendil]] by the North Macedonian Border (3 hr), [[Blagoevgrad]] (2-3 hr), [[Sandanski]], and [[Petrich]] (4 hr). Further [https://razpisanie.bdz.bg/en/sofia timetables can be found on the BDZ website] (in English).

There are several train stations and stops in Sofia, but of interest to travellers are mostly two. '''Since May 2024''', due to track renovations, most trains to destinations in Northern Bulgaria '''arrive at/depart from Sofia North station'''. This most notably affects ''some'' of the "tourist trains" to Varna (a couple direct ones remain). Nevertheless, it's still possible to buy tickets for those destinations at Sofia Central, as there are shuttle trains from Sofia Central to Sofia North, and you'll have to change trains there. Renovations are expected to last about a year.

* {{go
| name=Sofia Central Station | alt=Централна железопътна гара София/Tsentralna zhelezopatna gara Sofiya/Tsentralna Gara | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.711943|long=23.321038 | directions=on the northern end of the city centre
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2095010
| lastedit=2021-12-09
| content=The station can be somewhat confusing. Domestic departures go from the main terminal and that is where you can buy tickets for domestic travel. If you want to travel to an international destination, use ticket windows 21 or 22 on ground floor. It's opened 06:30-18:15. They speak some English and to book a ticket, you will need your passport. They only take cash. Platforms can be accessed from the main floor down the escalators at the far left corner. Platform numbering is somewhat confusing: Roman numerals indicate the platform number (I to VI), and Arabic numerals (1 to 12) indicate the actual track. Each platform is divided into East and West. Departures and arrivals are indicated on reliable electronic panels, but, beware, they indicate the track number, not the platform!
}}
* {{go
| name=Sofia North Station | alt=София Север, '''''Sofia Sever''''' | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.726337 | long=23.316479 | directions=about {{km|3}} north-west of Sofia Central: follow Knyaginya Maria Luiza Bld west, then Rozhen Bld north, turn east at the tram tracks T-intersection
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q97324846
| lastedit=2024-05-08
| content=A secondary station used by few passengers under normal circumstances. There's a tram turnaround in front of the station; tram lines 3 and 27 start there and pass through Sofia Central Station and its public transport hub (incl. a metro station). Alternatively, you can ride them further: Tram 3 stops at Pirotska Str (close to the Women's Market) and Vazrazhdane Sqr (close to Nezavisimost Sqr and Mall of Sofia); Tram 27 stops at Lion's Bridge, Sveta Nedelya Sqr (close to Nezavisimost Sqr), Vitosha Blvd, and the National Palace of Culture. You can also use Bus 413 to get to Sofia Central.
}}

====International====
From '''Romania''', a train runs daily from [[Bucharest]] at noon, taking ten hours; the return train leaves Sofia at 09:00. June to Sept this is a through-train, Oct-May you have to change at [[Ruse]] on the border. There's no longer an overnight train.

From '''Turkey''', a sleeper train departs Istanbul Halkalı at 21:40, running via Edirne, Kapikule on the border where you get out for passport control, and Plovdiv, to reach Sofia by 09:00. The eastbound train leaves Sofia at 18:30 to reach Istanbul for 05:40. Fares are quoted in euros: in 2022 you pay {{EUR|31.68}} for the basic single from Istanbul. Add {{EUR|10}} for a couchette, {{EUR|15}} for a bed in a shared 2-person cabin or {{EUR|35}} for the entire cabin.

===By car===
The motorway network in Bulgaria is still under construction.

Access to Bulgaria's capital is via several entry points:

* From the north ([[Vidin]]) &amp; south ([[Thessaloniki]]) via E79.
* From the east - via Thrace Highway E80/A1.
* From the west - from the Bulgarian-Serbian border point of [[Kalotina]].

The following motorways heading for Sofia are already in service:

* A1 connects Sofia to Burgas and the Black Sea coast, as well as Istanbul.
* A2 ends about 80&amp;nbsp;km from each city; the rest of the route is a regular 2-lane road. Extensions into the cities are planned.
* A3 is planned to be from Sofia to Thessaloniki, about 2/3 of the route is already in service.

Coming from [[North Macedonia]], via [[Kyustendil]] the roads are relatively good but driving within speed limits would avoid you much hassle caused either by traffic police, or road conditions. From Central Europe you can drive almost the whole length on highways (via Slovenia-Croatia-Serbia or Hungary-Serbia), with only the last 100&amp;nbsp;km between [[Niš]] in Southern Serbia and Sofia being heavily trafficked mountain roads around the Nishava ravine in not the best shape.

==Get around==
=== By public transport ===
[[File:Sofia Metro-Map.png|thumb|Map of Sofia Metro]]
Sofia has a well-developed, cheap, and efficient [https://www.sofiatraffic.bg/en/ public transport system] that consists of buses, trolleybuses, trams, and subway lines. The transport network can be confusing for visitors who do not know it well, but there is a [https://www.eway.bg/en/cities/sofia journey planner].

[[File:Sofia metro at Musagenitsa.jpg|thumb|A metro/subway train in Sofia]]
The price of a '''single metro ticket is 1.60 лв''', while a '''bus/tram/trolleybus ticket is 2 лв'''. There are also daily travel cards (4 лв). If you are staying for 4 or more days, or 3+ days and arriving directly in the city centre, you can also buy a 3-day ticket on an electronic card from the public transport offices (not from metro stations or at the airport). Fare inspectors ambush and board buses and trams in groups (and their attitude is generally not friendly at all), sometimes accompanied by police, and make no exceptions. The fine is 40 лв.

Tickets can be purchased using '''contactless bank cards and payment apps''' such as Apple and Google Pay, which might be the easiest solution for foreign visitors. In the metro, the ticket gates have a contactless symbol indicating the location of the reader (it's on the left side, not the right). On buses and trams, there are blue electronic readers with the same contactless symbol. Contactless purchases will be capped to the cost of the daily travel pass.

Paper tickets and daily cards can be bought at most newspaper stands especially ones adjacent to public transport stops, and from the driver. Validate your card/ticket as soon as you get on the bus/tram/trolleybus. The day ticket needs to be shown to the person at the ticket office before every metro trip, as they are supposed to check the date stamp (manually applied at the time of sale) before activating the ticket barriers to accept it.

[[File:Bus Number 284 at Sofia Airport 20090409 001.JPG|thumb|A bus in Sofia]]
There are 15 tram lines, 9 trolley lines, 93 bus lines and [https://www.metrosofia.com/en/maps 4 metro lines]. Some of the buses cover the area outside the city centre including neighboring villages. Useful routes include:
* bus #84 from both terminals of the airport to the center
* from the train/bus station to Orlov most - bus #213 or #214 or tram #1, #7 and #18 to Vitosha Street and Sv. Nedelya Square
* #1, #6, #7 to the National Palace of Culture
* #18 to Slaveykov square
* #6 to Macedonia square. 

The public transport operates from 05:00–23:00, [https://sofiatraffic.bg/en/info-center/noshtniiat-transport-v-sofiia-se plus four night lines]:
* N1 (zh.k. Lyulin 0650) to Mladost 4 0669)
* N2 (Obelya quarter 0874 to zh.k. Studentski grad 1694)
* N3 (zh.k. Levski G 2430 to zh.k. Ovcha Kupel 2 0684)
* N4 (zh.k. Druzhba-2 0612 to zh.k. Gotse Delchev 0600)

=== On foot ===
Streets have adequate tiled pavements, especially in the city centre. However, they are frequently uneven and potholed, and walking is further made difficult by parked cars, street vendors and cafes. Except for areas in the very centre, pavements rarely have slopes for wheelchair access or designated lanes for bicycle riders. Pedestrian crossings are numerous and are relatively respected by drivers. Use pedestrian underpasses to cross large intersections, though avoid ones in the suburbs as these are usually derelict.

=== By mini-bus ===
Mini-buses (marshrutki) stop if you just wave a hand and are usually fast way to go somewhere without need to change the car, but they aren't common anymore. You pay to the driver when you get on the car. Prices are 1.50 лв. You must tell the driver if and when you want to get off.

=== By taxi ===
Taxis in Sofia are yellow. Taxis can be caught on the streets or can be ordered by phone, they arrive fast and are reliable. A drive inside Sofia will rarely exceed 10 лв and a trip from the airport to the city center 8-15 лв.

There are many companies offering taxi services, some of them are OK Supertrans taxi (973 2121), {{EUR|1}} Taxi, "962-22-26", Yellow Taxi (91119) and Radio CV Taxi (91263) with fares around 0.80 лв/km. Some taxi companies have smartphone apps available that allow you to register and order taxis to your specific address in real time, thus eliminating the risk of falling prey to scams. As of June 2017, Yellow Taxi has the most user-friendly app for foreigners.

There are some taxis trying to imitate the most popular ones but with outrageous prices (up to 5.90 лв/km) so check before you board, these taxis usually hang around hotels and tourist spots picking on unsuspecting customers, The general rule is that if a taxi driver comes to you and offers you a drive, never accept it because they will try to rip you off. Also make sure the taxi has the driver's card on the front with his name.

Taxi drivers may not stop if you hail them on the street and often don't have much change, so plan accordingly (or leave tips!)

The TaxiMe app (similar to Uber) works well in Sofia.  It is possible to use a US phone number and to have a credit card entered so that the taxi hail and payments are all automatic.

Regular taxis will not take more than 4 passengers, so do not count on small children sitting in laps or otherwise squeezing extra people in a taxi.


=== By car ===
Renting a car is not necessarily a good idea if your plans are restricted to visiting only Sofia and not travelling elsewhere in the country. Driving here can be strenuous for those with less experience behind the wheel - be prepared for traffic jams and disorganized traffic. Those of you who plan on visiting more of the country can rent a car from a local company (much cheaper than the big brands) or use a broker as some of the local companies do not even have websites.

If you need to park your car, you are recommended to do it in a paid guarded lot. Parking in the center is difficult and you may be parked illegally without knowing it; foreign license plates may attract unwelcome attention of Bulgarian police and of criminals. Even if there are other cars parked in the area, double check that there are no signs or pavement markings prohibiting it. [https://www.sofiatraffic.bg/en/parking Parking in the central city area on working days is paid], it is divided in a so-called Blue Zone ("Синя зона") — 2 лв per hour, and a Green Zone ("Зелена зона") — 1 лв per hour. If you have a Bulgarian mobile number, you can also pay by SMS: send the vehicle registration plate number to "1302" for the "Green zone" or 1303 for the "Blue zone". This will charge parking for an hour through your phone bill. Five minutes before the prepaid time is up you will receive a warning SMS. You can either send another message for another hour or move your car.

Pay attention to trams or buses stopping in the middle of the road. If you see a stopped tram or bus on your left, you must stop and let the passengers get on/off, according to the Bulgarian traffic code. Failing to stop in this manner may be very dangerous.

Driving with your lights on is compulsory, day and night, all year long.

=== By bicycle ===
Sofia is one of the greenest capitals in Europe, with the big park zones ideal for biking. Slow traffic in downtown is perfect for cycling. On a bike you will save time and will enjoy sport activity. Sofia also has a few bike paths around the downtown area and in districts such as Mladost, Nadezhda, Hipodruma. Be careful as many cars double park and may open doors without noticing you.
* {{go
| name=Sofia Bike Rental | alt= | url=https://www.sofiabike.com/en/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=10:00-20:00, April to November | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-23
| content=Discover Sofia by bike map or joint to an experienced bike guide.
}}

==See==
{{mapframe|42.6962452| 23.3271|zoom=14}}
{{mapshapes|Q234707}}
[[File:AlexanderNevskyCathedral-Sofia-6.jpg|thumb|Alexander Nevsky Cathedral]]
In the administrative center of Sofia, the streets are paved with specific '''yellow bricks'''. They were laid in the beginning of the 20th century, purportedly as a present to the Bulgarian Tsar Ferdinand for his wedding from the Austria-Hungarian royal family (though many historians consider it a vanity project of Sofia's mayor). They are not a great material for wet weather, but they continue to add colorful flair.

===Museums===
* {{see
| name=Sofia History Museum | alt=Central Mineral Baths | url=https://sofiahistorymuseum.bg/en/home | email=
| address= | lat=42.6994 | long=23.3237 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=10 лв
| wikidata=Q190435
| lastedit=2025-03-01
| content=Museum of the history of Sofia itself, housed in the colourful old building of the Central Mineral [Water] Baths (built 1913). Exhibits include many luxurious items formerly belonging to Bulgaria's last monarchs.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum of Military History | alt= | url=http://www.militarymuseum.bg | email=m.museum@bol.bg
| address=92 Cherkovna Str. | lat=42.688397 | long=23.350711 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 946 18 05 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 946 18 06
| hours=10:00-18:00 | price=Adults 8 лв | lastedit= 2025-01-10
| wikipedia=National Museum of Military History (Bulgaria) | image=National Museum of Military History, Bulgaria, Sofia 2012 PD 039.jpg | wikidata=Q1066518
| content=Huge outdoor display of Warsaw Pact tanks, planes, APCs and other equipment, and indoor displays on the Bulgarian military history going back several centuries.
}}
* {{see
| name=Institute of Ethnology and Folklore Studies with Ethnographic Museum | alt= | url=http://ethnography.cc.bas.bg/ | email=eim_bas@mail.bg
| address=6A Moskovska Str | lat=42.696111 | long=23.327222 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 988 41 91 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 980 11 62
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q12279993
| content=Has a permanent collection of traditional Bulgarian costumes and a changing exhibition.
}}
* {{see
| name=Earth and Man National Museum | alt=Национален музей | url=https://www.earthandman.org/language/en/front/ | email=earth.and.man@gmail.com
| address=4 Cherni Vruh Blvd | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 2 865 66 39 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 866 14 57
| hours=10:00-18:00 | price=2 лв
| wikidata=Q5327147
| content=A large mineralogical museum. In the main hall is the world's biggest collection of Giant Crystals, with dazzling jagged rocks the size of refrigerators.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum of History | alt=Национален исторически музей | url=http://www.historymuseum.org/ | email=nim1973@abv.bg
| address=16 Vitoshko lale str. (ул. Витошко лале 16) | lat=42.654972 | long=23.270778 | directions=Take trolley #2 to the roundabout at the end of the bus line. Cross the busy Okolovrustino Shosse (ring road) and walk through the trees. The museum is not visible from the road, nor are there any signs.
| phone=+359 2 955 42 80 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 955 76 02
| hours=09:30-18:00 | price=10 лв, 1 лв for students
| image=Sofia - National Museum of History.jpg | wikidata=Q1968325
| content=The National Museum of History in the Rezidentsia Boyana provide a comprehensive view on Bulgarian history from the prehistory to present, in as broad of a European context as possible. With more than 650,000 exhibits, it is one of the largest history museums on the Balkans, so be prepared to spend several hours. One main attraction are golden and silver mugs and jewellery from Thracian (around 4th century BC) and Roman periods. About half of the exhibits have English captions.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Institute of Archaeology and Museum | alt= | url=http://www.naim.bg/ | email=aim-bas@aclubcable.com
| address=2 Saborna Str. | lat=42.696331 | long=23.324564 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 988 24 06 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 988 24 05
| hours=10:00-18:00 | price=10 лв
| wikipedia=National Archaeological Museum (Bulgaria) | image=Sofia Archaeological museum.jpg | wikidata=Q1497827
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=National Polytechnic Museum | alt= | url= | email=polytechnic@abv.bg
| address=66 Opalchenska Str | lat=42.70405 | long=23.31199 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 831 30 04 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 931 40 46
| hours=09:00-17:00 | price=
| wikipedia=National Polytechnical Museum | image=Politechnical-museum-interior.jpg | wikidata=Q6974996
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum of Natural History | alt= | url=http://www.nmnhs.com/ | email=
| address=1, Tzar Osvoboditel Blvd | lat=42.695683 | long=23.328464 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 987 41 95 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 988 28 94
| hours=10:00-18:00 | price=
| wikipedia=National Museum of Natural History (Bulgaria) | image=Natural-history-sofia-ifb.JPG | wikidata=Q6974486
| content=Has four floors of everything from rocks and minerals to insects and stuffed bison. It is a nice way to spend a rainy afternoon.
}}
* {{see
| name=The Red Flat | alt= | url=https://redflatsofia.com/ | email=
| address=24 Ivan Denkoglu Str | lat=42.693911 | long=23.319845 | directions=
| phone=+359 98 825 2032 | tollfree=
| hours=Daily 10:30–19:30 | price=18 лв
| lastedit=2025-12-23
| content=Half tour, half experience. Walk around a house setup like an old communist flat from the 1980s. You're allowed to touch and play with just about anything. There's an audio guide in English, Spanish and Bulgarian.
}}
* {{see
| name=House-Museum of Ivan Vazov | alt= | url=http://nlmuseum.bg/index.php/filiali/otdel-ekspozitzii/ivan-vazov/kashta-muzei-ivan-vazov | email=
| address= | lat=42.69301 | long=23.32758 | directions=On the corner of the streets G. Rakovski and Ivan Vazov.
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q61412859
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Sport | alt= | url= | email=
| address=1A Bulgaria Blvd | lat=42.688057 | long=23.334656 | directions=National Stadium Vasil Levski
| phone=+359 2 930 07 61 | tollfree=
| hours=09:00 to 17:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q12287455
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Paleontology and Historical Geology | alt= | url=https://gpff.gea.uni-sofia.bg/facilities/museum/ | email=
| address=15 Tzar Osvoboditel Blvd | lat=42.6934 | long=23.33523 | directions=Inside Sofia University.
| phone=+359 2 930 82 00 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q110779966
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=National Literature Museum | alt= | url=http://nlmuseum.bg/ | email=
| address=138 G. S. Rakovski Str., floor 2 | lat=42.689167 | long=23.323056 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 988 24 93 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q61411527
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=National Agricultural Museum | alt= | url= | email=
| address=30 Suhodolska Str | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 2 929 67 53 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q108666396
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=National Ecclesiastical History-Archeological Museum | alt= | url=https://bg-patriarshia.bg/church-arch-instit | email=nciam@bg-patriarshia.bg
| address=19 Sveta Nedelya Sq | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 2 988 13 43 | tollfree=
| hours=09:00 to 17:00 | price=
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Regional History Museum of Sofia | alt= | url=https://www.sofiahistorymuseum.bg/en/ | email=
| address=1 Banski Sq | lat=42.69937 | long=23.32356 | directions=Behind Banya Bashi Mosque
| phone=+359 2 985 44 55 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-Su 10:00-18:00 | price=6 лв, 2 лв for students
| lastedit=2024-10-09
| content=
}}

===Galleries===
* {{see
| name=Museum of Socialist Art | alt= | url=https://nationalgallery.bg/visiting/museum-of-socialist-period/ | email=
| address=7, Luchezar Stanchev St. | lat=42.7 | long=23.33 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Tu - Su, 10:00 - 18:00 | price=6 лв
| image=Museum of Sozart 5.jpg | wikidata=Q4306473
| lastedit=2025-12-23
| content=After the Soviet Union fell and Bulgaria moved on from communism, much of the country's communist artwork was eventually collected here. Outside the museum (and free to access) is a small park crammed with statues of notable communists, with every flavor of Lenin.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Art Gallery | alt= | url=https://nationalartgallerybg.org/ | email=
| address=1 Batenberg Sq. | lat=42.696481 | long=23.326786 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 980 00 93 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=10:30 to 18:00 | price=4 лв
| wikipedia=National Art Gallery (Bulgaria) | image=Royal Palace Sofia.jpg | wikidata=Q2991178
| content=Has old Bulgarian art, icons, etc. Also includes collections of the former National Gallery for Foreign Art, which are exhibited along with the 19th- and 20th-century collections of the National Art Gallery at National Gallery Square 500 ([https://nationalgallery.bg/visiting/kvadrat-500/ Kvadrat 500] in Bulgarian), which is at 1, 19th February St., St Alexander Nevsky Sq. and is open Tu-Su 10:00-18:00 and closed Mondays and holidays.
}}
* {{see
| name=Sofia City Art Gallery | alt=Софийска градска художествена галерия | url=http://www.sghg.bg/ | email=
| address=1 General Gurko St | lat=42.694489 | long=23.32428 | directions=The entrance is from Kniaz Al. Batenberg St
| phone=+359 2 987 2181 | tollfree=
| hours=10:00 to 19:00 | price=4 лв; free entrance every second and fourth Thursday
| wikidata=Q12294210
| content=
}}

===Churches===
[[File:Alexander Nevsky Cathedral 31.jpg|thumb|Alexander Nevsky Cathedral]]
* {{see
| name=St. Alexander Nevsky Cathedral | alt=Свети Александър Невски, Aleksandar Nevski | url=https://www.cathedral.bg/en/home/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.695839 | long=23.332969 | directions=Alexander Nevsky Square
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q43282
| lastedit=2025-12-28
| content=The largest church in the Balkans, and one of the largest Christian churches worldwide, able to hold 5,000 worshipers. Saint Alexander Nevsky was a Russian prince, and the cathedral was built to honour the Russian soldiers who died during the Russo-Turkish War of 1877–1878, liberating Bulgaria from Ottoman rule.
}}
* {{see
| name=St. Sophia Church | alt=църква „Света София“ | url= | email=
| address=2 Paris str. | lat=42.6965 | long=23.3315 | directions=across the square and to the right from Alexander Nevsky Cathedral
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q602853
| lastedit=2025-12-28
| content=It was built in the 6th century, in the same wave of construction as the Hagia Sophia in [[Constantinople]]. In 1329 it gave its name to the city. It was destroyed several times and during the Ottoman rule it was used as a mosque. It was built over an even older 4th century church, which can be explored through its excavated crypts and tombs. 
}}
[[File:Boyana Church.JPG|thumbnail|Boyana church]]
* {{see
| name=Boyana Church | alt= | url=https://boyanachurch.org/indexen.htm | email=
| address=1-3 Boyansko Ezero Str. | lat=42.644672 | long=23.266172 | directions=From metro station Vitosha, take bus 64 to Boyana Church stop, a small plaza with a few shops and a newly-built 5-star "All Seasons Residence" hotel
| phone=+359 2 959 09 39 | tollfree=
| hours=09:30-16:00 Apr-Oct, 9:00-5:30 Nov-Mar | price=10 лв, 2 лв for students
| wikidata=Q276553
| lastedit=2025-12-28
| content=This small 11th-century church and garden is on the [[UNESCO World Heritage List]] for its well-preserved murals. The layer of fresco from 1259 shows realism and emotion evocative of the early [[Renaissance]], but painted a century earlier. No photos are allowed inside, as the interior is dark and cramped. There is little interpretive information inside; you can hire an on-site tour guide or ask questions to the docent. Only 8 people are permitted inside at a time, for a maximum of 10 minutes. During busy periods you may have to wait for over an hour, yet the queue is self-policed so be prepared to stand outside doing nothing for a while and don't forget who arrived after you! This is at the foot of [[Vitosha]] mountain and is a good starting point for day trips in the mountain.
}}
* {{see
| name=Church of St. George | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.696861 | long=23.322861 | directions=Behind the Sheraton Hotel
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Church of St. George, Sofia | image=StGeorgeRotundaSofia.JPG | wikidata=Q2598073
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Catholic cathedral St. Joseph | alt= | url=http://www.catholic-bg.org | email=
| address=125, Knjaz Boris I | lat=42.698611 | long=23.319722 | directions=next to Sheraton Hotel
| phone=+359 2 9815548 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Cathedral of St Joseph, Sofia | image=| wikidata=Q598811
| content=Holy Masses: Sa 17:30 &amp; Su 10:30 in Bulgarian; 12:00 in Latin; 18:00 Bulgarian
}}
* {{see
| name=Saint Nedelya | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.696778 | long=23.321551 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=St Nedelya Church | image=P7120041.JPG | wikidata=Q520753
| lastedit=2016-07-31
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=St. Nicholas Orthodox Church | alt= | url=http://podvorie-sofia.bg/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.6957 | long=23.3291 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Russian Church, Sofia | image=The Russian Church in Sofia.jpg | wikidata=Q873892
| lastedit=2017-08-24
| content=
}}

===Other places of worship===
The city has been described as the "triangle of religious tolerance", because temples of three major world religions—Christianity, Islam and Judaism—are situated within two blocks of each other.
* {{see
| name=Banya Bashi Mosque | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.699511 | long=23.322575 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Banya Bashi Mosque | image=Banyabaşı Mosque, Sofia 2007.jpg | wikidata=Q790052
|lastedit=2021-12-03| content=Beautiful yet simple Ottoman-mosque. Built by Mimar Sinan. It's active and there is a guide inside.
}}
* {{see
| name=Sofia Synagogue | alt= | url=http://www.sofiasynagogue.com/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.700278 | long=23.321011 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=09:00 to 16:30 | price=
| wikipedia=Sofia Synagogue | image=Sofia Synagogue 11c.jpg | wikidata=Q942127
| content=One of the largest in Europe.
}}

===Historical buildings===
[[File:Battenberg Mausoleum Sofia 7.jpg|thumb|Battenberg Mausoleum]]
Sofia is one of the oldest cities in Europe and has ancient ruins throughout the city center.
* {{see
| name=Amphitheatre of Serdica | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=in the geographical center of the city under the flags of the EU
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q980970
| content=
}}

When Bulgaria gained autonomy from the Ottoman Empire in 1878, Alexander of Battenberg was elected the first prince of Bulgaria.
* {{see
| name=Battenberg Mausoleum | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.69143 | long=23.33264 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3137068
| content=The mausoleum and final resting place of Prince Alexander I of Bulgaria (1857–1893), the first Head of State of modern Bulgaria.
}}
* {{see
| name=Knyaz Battenberg's Palace | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.696481 | long=23.326786 | directions=in front of the City Garden
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q6057793
| content=
}}

===Monuments===
* {{see
| name=Monument to Vasil Levski | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6967 | long=23.3353 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1703313
| content=It commemorates the hanging of Bulgarian national hero and major revolutionary figure Vasil Levski in the city on 18 February 1873.
}}
* {{see
| name=Monument to the Tsar Liberator | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6937 | long=23.3323 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2037523
| content=Representing the power of freedom and across from it are the National Assembly and the Bulgarian Academy of Sciences.
}}
* {{see
| name=Monument to the Unknown Soldier | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.69625 | long=23.33153 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q585900
| content=Across from Alexander Nevsky cathedral; on the side of Hagia Sofia's Church.
}}
* {{see
| name=Tsar Samuil Monument | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.69628 | long=23.33053 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-07-31
| content=A statue of the Bulgarian warlord and tsar Samuil, who ruled Bulgaria between 997 and 1014.
}}
* {{see
| name=Russian Monument | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6923 | long=23.3105 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2042926
| lastedit=2016-07-31
| content=An obelisk built by the Russians.
}}
* {{see
| name=Monument to the Soviet Army | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.69055 | long=23.33444 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q153525
| lastedit=2021-09-22
| content=
}}

===Public squares===
* {{see
| name=Largo | alt=Ларго, Independence Square | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6977 | long=23.3233 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q6489272
| content=3 buildings of Socialist Classicism architecture, around what was designed to be the city's representative centre. The buildings are Council of Ministers and the TSUM department store on the north side, the National Assembly (former Communist Party headquarters) with its iconic spire on the east side, the Presidential Administration (former Council of State) and the Balkan Hotel to the south side.
}}
* {{see
| name=Prince Alexander of Battenberg Square | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.696111 | long=23.326389 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3400979
| content=The largest square in Sofia. Includes the National Art Gallery.
}}
* {{see
| name=Petko R. Slaveykov Square | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.69192 | long=23.3243 | directions=along Graf Ignatiev Str. , between Solunska Str. and Rakovski Str.
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=Free
| wikidata=Q3401326
| content=A famous square, real Sofia center with a monument of writers father and son Slaveykov. It`s a biggest open-air book market in the Balkans.There are round benches and street musicians act very often.
}}
* {{see
| name=Patriarh Evtimiy Square | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6883 | long=23.3285 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3400915
| content=A popular meeting place.
}}
* {{see
| name=Park National Palace of Culture | alt= | url=http://www.ndk.bg | email=
| address= | lat=42.684722 | long=23.318889 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3269914
| lastedit=2016-07-31
| content=
}}

===Parks and gardens===
* {{see
| name=Borisova Gradina (Boris Garden) | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6886 | long=23.3379 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q893826
| content=The oldest and best known park in the city. Includes the Ariana Lake.
}}
* {{see
| name=City Garden | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6952 | long=23.3256 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q5123174
| content=It's the oldest and most central public garden, in existence since 1872.
}}
* {{see
| name=Sofia Zoo | alt= | url=http://www.zoosofia.eu/ | email=
| address=1 Srebarna Str | lat=42.6582 | long=23.3297 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=09:00 to 17:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q966676
| content=
}}

[[File:Sofia South Park.jpg|thumb|Yuzhen Park (South Park)]]
* {{see
| name=Yuzhen Park (South Park) | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.670153 | long=23.308414 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q12299485
| content=A nice park in the south-east part of the city, although a bit too crowded on weekends. Vibrant with open area cafes, entertainment for children and grown-ups, and a few ponds with ducks.
}}
* {{see
| name=Oborishte Park | alt=Zaimov Park | url= | email=
| address=Yanko Sakazov blvd | lat=42.697458 | long=23.342344 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q12280284
| lastedit=2016-07-31
| content=A park near the center of the city with places to eat and drink.
}}

===Architecture===
* {{see
| name=Orlov Most | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.690556 | long=23.3375 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Eagles' Bridge, Sofia | image=Adlerbrücke Sofia c 014.JPG | wikidata=Q358267
| content=A bridge over the Perlovska River near the centre of Sofia
}}
* {{see
| name=Lavov Most | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.705 | long=23.323889 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Lions' Bridge, Sofia | image=Lion's Bridge, Sofia 1.jpg | wikidata=Q1138538
| lastedit=2016-07-31
| content=A bridge over the Vladayska River near the central train station.
}}
* {{see
| name=Snail House | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Boulevard "Simeonovsko Shose 187, 1434 Simeonovo | lat=42.6173 | long=23.3348 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2025-12-23
| content=A five story residential building in the shape of a giant pastel-striped snail, complete with two antennae.
}}

===Other sights===
[[File:Bulgarian Parliament TodorBozhinov 041009.jpg|thumb|National assembly of Bulgaria]]
* {{see
| name=National Assembly of Bulgaria | alt= | url=http://www.parliament.bg/ | email=infocenter@parliament.bg
| address=2 Narodno Sabranie Sq | lat=42.694444 | long=23.332778 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 939 39 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 981 31 31
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q18543007
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Sofia University | alt= | url=https://www.uni-sofia.bg/ | email=
| address=15 Tsar Osvoboditel Blvd | lat=42.693611 | long=23.335 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 9308 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 946 02 55
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q841581
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Bulgarian Academy of Sciences | alt= | url=http://www.bas.bg/ | email=
| address=1 15 November Str | lat=42.694444 | long=23.331667 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 979 53 33 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 981 72 62
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1003730
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=SS. Cyril and Methodius National Library | alt= | url=http://www.nationallibrary.bg/ | email=
| address=88 Vasil Levski Str | lat=42.6948 | long=23.33599 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 988 28 11 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 843 54 95
| hours=08:30 to 20:30 | price=
| wikidata=Q631641
| content=
}}

==Do==
* {{do
| name=Sofia Bike Tour | alt= | url=http://www.sofiagreentour.com/ | email=
| address=Dyacon Ignatiy, 5 | lat= | long= | directions=Start Point: National Theater "Ivan Vazov".
| phone=+359 885523630 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=April–November | price=
| content=Visit Sofia and the countryside around on a "free" bike tour, every day at 11:00 and 17:00. Note, for the ride you will need to rent a bicycle with the tour operators. And like always, the word "free" is a euphemism for "tips strongly appreciated". Also, this tour might in addition be a way to market their chargeable tours; always compare before committing to anything.
}}
* {{do
| name=Playgrounds | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=If you're travelling with kids, they might love playgrounds. The "rich" one is in the park that holds Vasil Levski stadium (close to the corner with Orlov Most; there are actually two playgrounds close to this corner and you'd look for the one more inside the park).
}}
* '''Football''' – The men's national football team plays at Vasil Levski stadium (capacity 43,000) 1&amp;nbsp;km southeast of city centre. Five city clubs play in First League, Bulgaria's top tier:
** [https://cska.bg/ CSKA Sofia] play at Bulgarian Army Stadium (capacity 23,000) just south of the national stadium. 
** [https://bg.cska1948.bg/ CSKA 1948] were formed in 2016 after a bust-up at CSKA Sofia. They play at Stadion Bistritsa (capacity 2500) 15 km south, and shared with Septemvri in the Second League. 
** [https://levski.bg/ Levski Sofia] play at Stadion Georgi Asparuhov (capacity 25,000, aka Vivacom stadium) 3 km east of the centre.
** [http://www.pfcslavia.com/ Slavia Sofia] play at Alexander Shalamanov Stadium (capacity 25,500) 4 km southwest.
** [https://www.fclokomotiv1929.com/ Lokomotiv 1929] play at Stadion Lokomotiv (capacity 17,500) 4 km north.

===Theatre and performing arts===
[[File:IvanVazov National Theatre 7.jpg|thumb|Ivan Vazov National Theater]]
* {{do
| name=Sofia Opera and Ballet | alt= | url=http://www.operasofia.bg/ | email=reservations@operasofia.bg
| address= | lat=42.6975 | long=23.3305 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 8006266 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=National Opera and Ballet of Bulgaria | image=National Opera Sofia 2009 20090406 003.JPG | wikidata=Q2915220
| content=During summer, open air shows in the evenings are offered.
}}
* {{do
| name=Arena Cinema | alt= | url=http://www.kinoarena.com/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.66044 | long=23.38229 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| content=One of the biggest Bulgarian cinema multiplex. Cinemas in Sofia play all films except children's films in their original language with Bulgarian subtitles.
}}
* {{do
| name=Ivan Vazov National Theatre | alt= | url=http://www.nationaltheatre.bg/ | email=info@nationaltheatre.bg
| address=5 Dyakon Ignatiy Str | lat=42.69415 | long=23.32653 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 811 92 19 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 987 70 66
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1858012
| content=
}}
* {{do
| name=National Palace of Culture | alt= | url=http://www.ndk.bg/ | email=
| address=1 Bulgaria Sq | lat=42.6852 | long=23.319 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 916 63 00 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 865 70 53
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3269914
| content=The biggest congress center in the Balkans (a massive monolithic communist-style building). If asking for directions, ask for NDK (en-de-ka), as most Bulgarians refer to it by this acronym.
}}
* {{do
| name=Central Military Club | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6952 | long=23.3299 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q190381
| content=It`s a multi-purpose monument of culture building in the city center. Also known under the name Kristal.
}}

===Vitosha===
{{main|Vitosha}}
[[file:Витоша, мост Морените.JPG|thumb|Golden Bridge]]
A magnificent landmark mountain very popular with the locals and rising just south of the capital. It is easily accessible by public transportation, bus 63 (from stop ''Tsar Boris III'') or 66 (from ''Metrostantsiya Vitosha'' metro stop), or by car. Day trips in Vitosha on a sunny day are highly recommended.

In the winter, it is well suited for skiing and its proximity allows one day ski-trips; in the summer it is great for hiking. A great way to spend few days in Sofia, being on its "balcony," enjoying sunny days on the mountain with a spectacular view on the capital. It is a unique chance to witness the rare symbiosis of a metropolitan city with its nature park.

==Buy==
It is strongly advisable to skip exchange offices on the street and use exclusively banks for exchanging money. Some exchange stalls will try to scam you by buying your currency at very unfavorable rates. See [[Bulgaria#Money]] for exchange rates.) It's also possible to change money at a good rate in casinos if you play there. Ignore anyone on the street wanting to change money; you will get an awful exchange rate, or a handful of fake banknotes.

ATMs are widely available and accept all major credit cards (Visa, MasterCard, Amex, Diner's, etc.), although you have to check your daily limit with your bank. ATMs will let you withdraw at most 400 лв in one go, but if your card limit allows it, you can make two or more withdrawals.

Credit cards are widely accepted in larger stores and supermarkets, but in small souvenir shops or restaurants you will definitely need to carry some cash.

'''Souvenirs''' can be bought many small shops in the subways in front of the old Party House and in the metro station at the Largo. The Ethnographic Museum has a small shop tightly crammed with souvenirs of all kinds from all over Bulgaria (on the right, just as you enter the main entrance). Antiques and souvenirs can also be found in Alexander Nevsky square, in stalls just opposite the church.

* {{buy
| name=Vitosha Boulevard | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.691331 | long=23.319661 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q7937209
| content=It`s the main commercial street in the centre of Sofia. Its pedestrian part is a popular place for walks. It is known as the most expensive street in Sofia.
}}
* {{buy
| name=The Mall | alt= | url=http://www.themall.bg/ | email=
| address=115 Tzarigradsko Shose Blvd | lat=42.6702 | long=23.3664 | directions=Many bus lines stop at THE MALL. Choose between bus no. 1, 3, 5, 6, 76, 84, 114, 204, 213, 214, 284, 305, 306, 313 and 604.
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=10:00 to 22:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q6463472
| content=a convenience store, Largest shopping mall in Bulgaria; contains also a Carrefour store, large Arena cinema, a lot of cafes and restaurants, etc.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Central Sofia Market Hall | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Knyaginya Maria Luiza Blvd | lat=42.7 | long=23.321667 | directions=Opposite the Banya Bashi mosque.
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q190675
| content=Has many stalls selling all kinds of food, drink and cosmetics. The second floor has various fast-food cafés. ''As of early 2023 closed for renovations.''.
}}
* {{buy
| name=TZUM | alt= | url=https://www.tzum.bg/ | email=tzum@tzum.bg
| address=2, Knyaginya Maria Luiza Blvd | lat=42.698333 | long=23.323056 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 926 07 00 | tollfree=
| hours=10:00 to 21:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q136504
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Mall of Sofia | alt= | url=http://www.mallofsofia.com/ | email=
| address=101, Aleksander Stamboliyski Blvd | lat=42.698056 | long=23.308611 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 929 33 77 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 929 33 00
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q12287294
| content=Contains a Piccadilly store and a Cinema City multiplex.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Park Center | alt= | url=http://www.parkcenter.bg | email=
| address=2 Arsenalski Blvd., floor 3 | lat=42.678611 | long=23.320556 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 865 72 85 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 865 71 37
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3656933
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=SkyCity Mall | alt= | url=http://www.skycitycenter.com/ | email=office@skycitycenter.com
| address=52 Kosta Lulchev Str. | lat=42.6798 | long=23.3676 | directions=You can get there by tram No 20, bus No 9, and Route Taxi No 1, 19 and 21.
| phone=+359 2 971 02 13 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 971 01 89
| hours=10:00 to 22:00 | price=
| content=Also has an entertainment center.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Serdika Center Sofia | alt= | url=http://serdikacenter.bg/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.692 | long=23.354 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2272273
| content=Contains a Piccadilly store.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Sofia Outlet Center | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.645244 | long=23.392617 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q7553661
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Bulgaria Mall | alt= | url=https://www.bulgariamall.bg/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.6641 | long=23.2885 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1252090
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Paradise Center | alt= | url=http://paradise-center.com/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.657778 | long=23.314444 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q7134254
| content=Largest shopping mall in Bulgaria; contains also a Carrefour store, large Arena cinema, a lot of cafes and restaurants, etc.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Sofia Ring Mall | alt= | url=http://www.sofiaring.bg/ | email=
| address= | lat=42.6246 | long=23.3519 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q12294461
| lastedit=2016-07-31
| content=Contains a karting track and a Cinema City multiplex.
}}

==Eat==
[[File:Banitsa borzo.jpg|thumb|Banitsa, a favourite breakfast cheese pastry]]
Sofia is full of trendy cafes with outdoor seating in the summer and good-quality restaurants.
===Fast food===
You can easily find take away food in Sofia. For less than 2 лв you can get a slice of pizza, a hot-dog or a sandwich. You can get more traditional Bulgarian food in bakeries, offering banitsa and other kinds of pastry. This food is often consumed with ayran or boza. Another possibility is to get a katma, which is a big pancake filled with cheese, ham, jam or chocolate.

===Budget===
Pizzeria-type restaurants and snack bars can be found all over Sofia. Although many are very uninteresting for the traveler looking for a meal with a local flavor, some include excellent Bulgarian dishes.

All these are in the city center:
* {{eat
| name=Trafa Beerhouse | alt= | url= | email=
| address=ul. "William Gladstone" 27 | lat=42.6917320 | long=23.3189438 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Pleasant, unpretentious, delicious. They have all the good Bulgarian dishes. The balcony has a lovely view.}}
* {{eat
| name=Veselata Gozba Restaurant | alt= | url= | email=
| address=ул. П.Парчевич 29 | lat=42.6910612 | long=23.3181592 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Good variety of main courses, soups, salads and desserts. The food is delicious. Family-operated restaurant}}
* {{eat
| name=Gastrobar 6 | alt= | url= | email=
| address=ul. "Han Krum" 6 | lat=42.6908742 | long= 23.3243059 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Favorite place for delicious food in a great pleasant atmosphere. You feel at home}}
* {{eat
| name=Ali Baba | alt= | url= | email=
| address=ул. „Алабин И. Вл.“ 52 | lat=42.6947793 | long=23.3216411 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Good place for a quick bit of kebabs and falafel.}}
* {{eat
| name=Dream House | alt= | url= | email=
| address=улица „Алабин И. Вл 50 | lat=42.6948210 | long= 23.3213987 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Very good vegetarian restaurant. Quick service, simple and good food, good value for money.}}
* {{eat
| name=Мекица и Кафе (Mekitsa and Coffee) | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=42.6908996 | long= 23.3255927 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Here you can have brunch and the typical Bulgarian breakfast. One of them gems of Sofia. Great, hot, fresh, on the spot mekitsa. With very friendly staff. You can go to the second floor, sit at the table against the window, munch mekitsa and sip your beverage. Good times!}}
* {{eat
| name=DARO | alt= | url= | email=
| address=ul. "Angel Kanchev" 20 | lat=42.6914779 | long=23.3220743 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=A breakfast restaurant}}

===Mid-range===
* {{eat
| name=Pizza Victoria | alt=Ресторант VICTORIA Цар Освободител | url=http://www.victoria.bg/ | email=
| address=bul. "Tsar Osvoboditel" 7 | lat=42.6951406 | long=23.3298342 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=One of the best Bulgarian pizzas.
}}
*{{eat
| name= Godzila | url=http://godzila.bg/welcome | email=office@godzila.bg
| address=ul. Gen. Y. V. Gurko 52 2 | lat= 42.6903468| long=23.3309960 | directions=Under the Sofia's sport palace with entrance from Gen. Gurko street.
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=Godzila's first restaurant opened in 1999 in the sea capital of Bulgaria, Varna . There you can try some fresh salads, juicy barbecue, delicious pizza and various other dishes. The menus are also written in English and the staff speaks English as well. There are traditional Bulgarian cuisine and Western cuisine as well.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Pod Lipite | url=http://www.podlipitebg.com/ | email=
| address=ul. "Elin Pelin" 1 | lat= 42.6818057| long=23.3354685 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=Very good traditional food. Reservation is required.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Motto | url=http://www.motto-bg.com/ | email=
| address=18 Aksakov str. | lat=42.6936970 | long=23.3301993 | directions=Motto is on the street right behind the Radisson hotel, and then two blocks East (turn to the right on the first small street behind the Radisson if you are walking from the big horse statue) - it's kind of hard to find as the sign is a small black sign with white lettering.
| phone=+359 2 987 27 23 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=5–15 лв per dish.
 | lastedit=
| content=This place is always fairly busy with a trendy crowd. The decor is modern and cool, and the people typically good looking. The service here is usually pretty nice, and many of the wait-staff speak English. The food is consistent and enjoyable.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Hadjidraganovite kashti | alt=Traditional Bulgarian Cuisine | url=http://www.kashtite.com/index_en.html | email=
| address=75 Kozloduy | lat=42.7066004 | long=23.3225812 | directions=2 minutes walking distance from the Lion Bridge, around the corner from Ramses II Casino
| phone=+359 (2) 931 31 48 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=11:30 - 02:00 | price=€10-30 (April 2011)
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=Amazing restaurant just off one of Sofia's main streets. The decor is old-style Bulgarian and the food is traditional Bulgarian, plentiful and very, very tasty. Entertainment includes a Bulgarian walking band and guests are primarily locals. Staff is very friendly and most speak English. Reservations are necessary, even on weeknights.
}}

===Splurge===

* {{eat
| name=Cosmos Restaurant / Космос | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Lavele St 19 | lat=42.6947539  | long= 23.3189502 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=
}}

==Drink==
===Mineral springs===
[[File:Hot Springs - Горячие минеральные источники - panoramio.jpg|thumb|Sure, it tastes slightly of sulphur, but you can't beat the price.]]
Sofia was founded here because of the quality of its mineral waters. In the city, there are 7 independent '''mineral water springs'''. Top off your water bottles here!
* At the Sofia History Museum, there is a tap in a corner of the façade, and a larger cluster of mineral water drinking fountains just across the small street to the north (left when facing the building).

===Cafés===
* {{drink
| name=Onda Coffee Break | url=https://www.facebook.com/ONDA-COFFEE-BREAK-88775021385/ | email=onda@onda.bg
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 2 980 49 40 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 980 19 39
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Pchela Sweet Shop | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Nedelya Sweet Shop | url=http://www.nedelya.com/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 88 560 08 30 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Art Club since 1991 | url= | email=
| address=6 Tsar Ivan Asen II Str. | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* International chains '''[https://costacoffee.bg/ Costa Coffee]''' and '''[https://www.starbucks.bg/en Starbucks]''' have several locations across the city

===Bars===
* {{drink
| name=JJ Murphys Irish pub | alt= | url=https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100051778763880 | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-23
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=The Cocktail Bar | alt= | url=https://thecocktailbar.bg/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-23
| content=Tasty cocktails, crowded in the evenings, has a summer garden (it is actually in a small park, which becomes occupied by the customers)
}}
* {{drink
| name=Bar 5L | alt= | url=https://www.facebook.com/5LSpeakeasyBar/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-23
| content=Speakeasy (5L is a transliteration of ''rooster'' in Bulgarian). Designer cocktails in cozy atmosphere. The key, corresponding to the day of the month, unlocks the door (not sure whether they change it at midnight).
}}

===Nightlife===
The Sofia nightlife is vibrant, concentrated mostly in two areas - the city center and around Studentski grad (Студентски град/Student's town), which is the neighborhood with the university dorms. There are frequent live performances in various venues, check the freely distributed guides in various shops and restaurants like Programata (Програмата/The Program). The primary distinction between the clubs is whether the music includes chalga (чалга/folk-Turkish-Greek-Serbian influenced local genre) or not. Expect that any local acquaintances will have strong feelings whether they attend or not the chalga clubs. There are hundreds of clubs and bars, with prices from 2 лв for beer and 5 for cocktail to luxurious places charging exorbitant sums. It is better to pay with cash, as POS terminals are not widely available, especially in the cheaper places. The people start to gather after working hours for a beer, cocktail or glass of wine, moving to dinner around 20:00 and clubs and discos after 23:00.

In the warm months, crowds overflow from the more popular places like [http://sofia.zavedenia.com/471/Bilkova/#! '''Bilkova'''] (Билкова/The Herbal) on the street. The centrally located parks and gardens like Crystal (Кристал) and Gradinkata na Narodniya (Градинката на народния/The garden of the national theater) and crowded during the summer, with drinks provided from nearby shops or cocktails in disposable cups.
* '''[https://www.carruselclub.com/index.html Carrusel]{{Dead link|date=January 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}'''. Upscale club, hosting DJ parties and special events.
* [http://culturebeatclub.com/ '''Culture Beat''']. Boutique cafe, bar, and nightclub, in NDK (National Palace of Culture). Great view from the terrace in the summer.
* '''Gramophone''' - contemporary music
* '''RocknRolla''' - large underground venue with rock music, on Garibaldi square
* '''[https://www.yaltaclub.com/ Yalta]{{Dead link|date=March 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}''' - the biggest, oldest and most famous disco in Sofia, existing since the communist times, resident and guest DJ parties and events. EDM, house.
* '''[http://www.bedroom.bg/sofia/ Bedroom Premium Club]{{Dead link|date=July 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}''' - R&amp;B, hip-hop, house
* '''Stroezha''' - rock and contemporary music
* '''Onyx''' - contemporary music
* '''Sugar''' - hip-hop
* '''Bar Dak''' and '''Bar Dak 2''' - bars
* '''Once Upon a Time Библиотека''' - housed in the building of the National Library, rock.
* '''Club Alcohol''' - rock
* '''Mixtape 5''' - huge club, next to NDK (National Palace of Culture), various events.
* '''Sofia Live Club''' - live events, in NDK
* '''Club Terminal 1''' - big venue, mostly rock
* '''Club Mascara''' - in the building of the National Opera, contemporary music, house.
* '''Megami''' - in the Marinela hotel, chalga, upscale.
* '''BIAD''' - Rakovski streer, next to Memento, chalga.
* '''Club Revue''' - opposite of the National Assembly, chalga.
* '''Dada Cultural Bar''' - tango, salsa, live performances
* {{drink
| name=Apartment | url=http://a-part-mental.org/?lang=en {{dead link|December 2020}} | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
|lastedit=2023-10-18| content=Popular among locals as well as foreigners is the "apartamenta", some sort of private club in the second floor of a turn of the 19th century mansion where you find a series of rooms, all in different styles and wall-drawings, colourful tapestries, etc. Go to the right, get a drink in the kitchen (everything non-alcoholic is 4 лв), and just pick and choose a room which looks cozy enough (shouldn't be too hard to find one with all the couches lying around). If you love the music, there are Mac computers in most of the rooms where you can pick something out of the playlist. Have a game of chess. There is also a Cinema room, if there is nothing running just go in, pick a movie out of the list and start the projection. There is also home-made chocolate and cream and all different kinds of organic drinks like Himalayan tea or Kiwi nectar.
}}
* The largest discos in Sofia are concentrated in Student's town (Studentski grad) in the southern part of the city and can be reached by buses #94 (from Sofia university and Culture palace), #280 (from Sofia University, Orlov most) and #102. The last bus to Studentski grad departs from the city center at about 23:30 (from Sofia University and Culture Palace). The entrance fee for most discos is between 1 and 5 лв. Discos that can be visited there include: Avenue, Tantra, Orient 33, Jim Beam, Maskata, Stroezha.
* {{drink
| name=4km | url=https://www.facebook.com/PartyCenter | email=
| address=boulevard Tsarigradsko shose 111 | lat=42.66933 | long=23.36965 | directions=Take metro line 1 to G.M.Dimitrov Metro Station and walk ~15 min. through Dimitrov boulevard to the big roundabout
| hours= | price=Entrance is ~€10, but slightly cheaper if you arrive before midnight
| content=This place plays mostly drum&amp;bass and dubstep music.
}}

==Sleep==

===Budget===
* {{sleep
| name=Peter Pan Hostel | alt= | url=https://www.peterpan-hostel.com/ | email=
| address= bul. Knyaz Aleksandar Dondukov| lat=42.69835 | long=23.33297 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Private €12-14
| lastedit=2021-03-19
| content=Owner-run, small hostel on the first floor of apartment building. Newly renovated. Small but clean rooms with single beds or bunk beds. Rooms come with TV, small balcony, fridge. Wifi available. No communal space or kitchen (only microwave). 
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Levitt Hostel | alt= | url=http://levitthostel.com | email=alekzander.levitt@gmail.com
| address=&lt;s&gt;55 Vitosha Blvd&lt;/s&gt; shifted | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 885640012 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin=12:00 | checkout=11:00 | price=€10
| content= Offers free unlimited high speed Internet (1000 Mbit/s) and Wi-Fi connection through the entire hostel, free coffee and tea any time of the day, free use of fully equipped kitchen, free blankets, pillows and sheets, free towels on request, free laundry (with 3 nights stay), free use of iron/ironing board, free hair dryer, free city maps, travel desk, security system + 24 hours video surveillance, designated smoking area, no curfew or lockout.
}}
*{{sleep
| name=Crosspoint Sofia Hostel | alt=КросПойнт София Хостел | url=http://www.crosspointhostel.com {{dead link|December 2020}} | email=office@crosspointhostel.com
| address=#6, Parensov St | lat=42.689865 | long=23.328756 | directions=just a block away from Patriarh Evtimiy Square, and some 500 m away from the Parliament
| phone=+359 896511179, +359 888455699 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€9-18
| checkin=12:00 | checkout=11:45
| content=A hostel with a friendly atmosphere. Free Wi-Fi; 1m-wide spacious and very comfortable beds; metal lockers. Offers mixed and female dorms as well as private rooms. Great young staff with an attitude working there.
}}
*{{sleep
| name=Hostel Mostel | alt= | url=http://www.hostelmostel.com/sofia/facilities-services | email=
| address=2A, Makedonia Blvd | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 889223296 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=From €9
| content=Beautiful wooden flooring. Has a huge lounge to chill out, you can browse the net on modern computers. Some dorm rooms are en-suite, trips to Rila Monastery are run daily. 5 Euros for breakfast.
}}
*{{sleep
| name=Nightingale Hostel | url=http://www.facebook.com/NIGHTINGALEHOSTEL | email=booking@nightingalehostel.com
| address=&lt;s&gt;2A, Petko R. Slaveykov Square&lt;/s&gt; shifted | lat=42.692268 | long=23.323806 | directions=Close to the corner of Solunska Str. and Graf Ignatiev Str.
| phone=+359 877214888, +359 29801583 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€7-12
| checkin=14:00 | checkout=12:00
| content=At Famous Slaveykov Square (center of the downtown), a non-smoking eco hostel provides beds and rooms and it is a social place with air-conditioning, common/TV room and lobby area. Free of charge- breakfast, kitchen, PC and WiFi internet, lockers, maps, call a taxi, book a club, check timetables service, hot showers in renovated and sexes separated toilets and 24hr reception desk. Laundry, pick up, meals and drinks are available. Friendly and talkative staff. A lot of info for local life.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Orient Express Hostel - Sofia | alt= | url=http://www.orientexpresshostel.com {{dead link|June 2020|December 2020}} | email=
| address=8A Hristo Belchev Str. | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=This small hostel offers a variety of room options. 
}}
*{{sleep
| name=Interhost / Hello Sofia | alt= | url= | email=interhostel@yahoo.co.uk
| address=50A Allabin Str | lat=42.69477 | long=23.3213 | directions=On the corner with Vitosha Blvd and Allabin Str
| phone=+359 889138298 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Private from €11
| lastedit=2021-03-17
| content=Formerly known as "Internet Hostel". Small place but very central. 3 (dorm) rooms, 1 apartment available in this location. Communal space: Small kitchen/dining area. No reception or staff on site, so announce your arrival upfront. Heating in the rooms is remote-controlled and only switched on at night times. The company operates several venues in Sofia. If you book in advance they might move you to a different location, based on availability.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Alegra Hostel | alt= | url=http://alegrahostel.eu/ {{dead link|December 2020}} | email=alegrahostel@abv.bg
| address=Sofroniy Vrachanski street № 145 | lat=42.71024 | long=23.31713 | directions=near central railway and central bus station
| phone=+359 889446364 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin=11:00 | checkout=12:00 | price=€30 private room /€15 per person
| lastedit=2015-04-14
| content=skype: alegra.hostel VIBER: 00359889446364 Location:in the center, at a quiet street, on the first floor of a three-storey residential building, with fully independent separate entrance and a tiny courtyard. The living area occupies 80 m². 4 separate rooms, individual locks, a fully equipped kitchen (kitchen stove, dishwasher, pots, saucepans, refrigerator, porcelain food sets, coffee machine, tea, microwave oven), two bathrooms with toilet, small vestibule. Bedding: Three rooms with three single beds, three individual locking wardrobes. The fourth room is furnished with two single beds and wardrobe. Window with PVC framed windows, convector radiators for heating in each room. All doors are locked with separate keys. In each room there are table, chairs, television, free WiFi, Internet, fax and two towels for each guest. Washing machine, clothes dryer, hair dryer, ironing board, mirror, bedside lamp, non-stop hot water. The Guest House is set up to accommodate up to 11 people. Included in the price: breakfast, tea, coffee.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=10 Coins Hostel | alt= | url=http://www.10coins-hostel.eu/ | email=10coins.hostel@gmail.com
| address=Dechko Uzunov 24, Nadezhda | lat= | long= | directions=Take blue line to "Han Kubrat", nuicance to find without GPS
| phone=+359 889303592 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin=14:00 | checkout=11:00 | price=Dorm €7, private room €18
| lastedit=2017-08-25
| content=Average but friendly hostel outside of the centre, Small kitchen, quiet neighborhood.
}}

===Mid-range===

*{{sleep
| name=Holiday Inn Sofia | alt= | url=http://www.hisofiahotel.com | email=
| address=111 Aleksandar Malinov Blvd | lat=42.62547 | long=23.37593 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 8070707 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Rooms from €68
| wikidata=Q111400985
| content=Modern five-star hotel offering conference facilities and spa centre.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Holiday Village Diplomat | alt= | url=http://www.gloriapalace.net | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=Is near Vitosha mountain and 20 min away from the city centre. Spacious rooms, large park area and friendly staff.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Maxim Hotel | alt= | url= | email=hotel_maxim@abv.bg
| address= | lat=42.70582 | long=23.3241 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| wikidata=Q111858624
| content=A hotel 5 min walking distance from the train/bus station and 5 min away in the opposite direction from downtown Sofia. It is a cute hotel with a nice bedroom and also a living/TV room, large private bathroom and includes breakfast buffet in the morning. Only negative is they do not have an elevator. Cost in slow season was €60 for 2 people, €50 for one person.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Metropolitan Hotel Sofia | alt= | url=http://metropolitanhotelsofia.com/ | email=Reservations@metropolitanhotelsofia.com
| address=64, Tsarigradsko shose Blvd | lat=42.65685 | long=23.38294 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 419 19 00 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 419 19 09
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| wikidata=Q111400984
| content=Business 4-star hotel near airport, ideal for business and leisure.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Red House B&amp;B | alt= | url=http://www.redbandb.com/home.aspx | email=
| address=15, Lyuben Karavelov St | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price=From €30 | checkin= | checkout=
| content=A charming B&amp;B in the Red House cultural centre.
}}
*{{sleep
| name=Hello Sofia Guesthouse | url=http://www.hellosofia.hostel.com/ | email=sofiaguest@yahoo.com
| address=12 Stefan Stambolov Bul | lat= | long= | directions=Close to the corner with Todor Aleksandrov &amp; Hristo Botev Blvd
| phone=+359 889138298 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=From €20
| checkin= | checkout=
| content= Just opened small and cozy guesthouse in the very center of Downtown, eco-friendly, offers individually designed en-suite rooms, also deluxe dormitories and studios, furnished and supplied with all natural materials and fabrics/linens, pillows by choice, free parking during the weekends, free WiFi, 40" LED HDTVs and individual PCs in some of the rooms!
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Lozenetz | alt= | url=http://www.lozenetzhotel.com | email=info@lozenetzhotel.com
| address=23, Sveti Naum Bul | lat=42.67826 | long=23.32614 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 9654444 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| wikidata=Q111858627
| content=
}}

===Splurge===

* '''Maria Luiza Hotel''' occupies an exquisite building dating back to the turn of 20th century and listed as one of Bulgaria's cultural monuments of national significance. Maria Luisa Hotel offers a combination of the standards and services found in a luxury hotel plus the privacy and independence of one's own home.
*{{sleep
| name=Sofia Hotel Balkan, a Marriott Luxury Collection Hotel | alt=previously branded as Sheraton | url=https://www.marriott.de/hotels/travel/soflc-sofia-hotel-balkan-a-luxury-collection-hotel-sofia/ | email=
| address=5, Sveta Nedelya Sq | lat=42.69712 | long=23.32204 | directions=opposite the statue of Sofia and Sveta Nedelya Church
| phone=+359 2 9816541 | tollfree=
| checkin=14:00 | checkout=12:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q111400989
| content=Impressive 5-storey hotel, in classical design, houses 184 rooms, including 19 suites. All rooms are soundproof, with air condition control, direct dial phone, message alert, TV with satellite program, radio, mini bar.
}}
*{{sleep
| name=Park Inn by Radisson Sofia Hotel | alt= | url=https://www.radissonhotels.com/en-us/destination | email=info.sofia@rezidorparkinn.com
| address=Atanas Dukov Str. 36 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+359 2 861 5700 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Set in a building that resembles a baroque castle, this hotel offers 77 rooms and 36 one- or two-bedroom apartments.
}}

==Stay safe==
Generally, Sofia is a safe and walkable city, even at night. Nevertheless, avoid poorly lit areas and use your common sense. One problem area is around the central bus and rail station, continuing south down Maria Luiza Blvd and the Lions' Bridge (Lavov Most). Dark areas of the city parks should also be avoided — Borisova Garden in particular can be unsafe after dark. These areas are known for drug use, opportunistic theft, and approaches from touts selling contraband. Single women should take particular care.

Pedestrians should be careful since many Bulgarian drivers do not yield right of way to those on foot.

Do not get into conflict with football fan groups if they seem drunk and aggressive. Avoid wearing football shirts or scarves of the Sofia-based football teams, especially on match days.

Be wary of petty thieves and poorer neighborhoods, as pick pocketing and thefts are common. If you are approached by locals trying to sell stolen goods, give you directions or bother you exercise caution.

If you get in legal trouble, the Bulgarian police and judiciary may not protect you adequately because of corruption and nepotism.

==Cope==
===Embassies===

* {{flag|Armenia}} {{listing
| name=Armenia | alt= | url=http://bulgaria.mfa.am | email=armbulgariaembassy@mfa.am
| address=ul. "Zagorichane" 3 | lat=42.688716 | long=23.353705 | directions=
| phone=+359-2 9461272, +359 2 9461273 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 09:00-18:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q31194238
| content=
}}
* {{flag|China}} {{listing
| name=China | alt= | url=http://bg.china-embassy.gov.cn/ | email=chnemb_bg@live.cn
| address=bul. "James Bourchier" 58 | lat=42.673389 | long=23.324028 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 973 3873 | tollfree= | fax=+359 2 971 1081
| hours=M-F 10:00-12:00, 14:00-16:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q114520637
| lastedit=2024-02-08
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Germany}} {{listing
| name=Germany | alt= | url=https://sofia.diplo.de | email=
| address=ul. "Frederic-Joliot-Curie" 25 | lat=42.67 | long=23.3493 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 91 83 80 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q58491509
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Greece}} {{listing
| name=Greece | alt= | url=https://www.mfa.gr/bulgaria | email=
| address=ul. "San Stefano" 33 | lat=42.6913 | long=23.33808 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 8433085, +359 2 8433086 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q109040251
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Finland}} {{listing
| name=Finland | alt= | url=https://finlandabroad.fi/web/bgr/ | email=sanomat.sof@formin.fi
| address=ul. "Bacho Kiro" 26-28 | lat=42.700556 | long=23.326667 | directions=5th floor
| phone=+359-2-810 2110 | tollfree=
| hours=M-Th 08:15-16:15, F 08:15-15:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q41589049
| content=
}}
* {{flag|France}} {{listing
| name=France | alt= | url=https://bg.ambafrance.org/ | email=
| address=ul. "Oborishte" 27-29 | lat=42.694923 | long=23.341036 | directions=
| phone=+359-2-965 1100 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2841733
| lastedit=2016-10-30
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Japan}} {{listing
| name=Japan | alt= | url=https://www.bg.emb-japan.go.jp | email=emb-jp-bg@sf.mofa.go.jp
| address=ul. "Lyulyakova Gradina" 14 | lat=42.670833 | long=23.355556 | directions=
| phone=+359 80046070 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q41589184
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Italy}} {{listing
| name=Italy | alt= | url=https://ambsofia.esteri.it/ | email=consolare.sofia@esteri.it
| address=ul. "Shipka" 2 | lat=42.6951 | long=23.3312 | directions=
| phone=+359 29217300 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3891389
| content=
}}
* {{flag|North Macedonia}} {{listing
| name=North Macedonia | alt= | url=https://sofia.mfa.gov.mk/mk | email=sofia@mfa.gov.mk
| address= ul. "Frederic Joliot-Curie" 17, block 2, floor 3, Suite 5| lat=42.671944 | long=23.352778 | directions=
| phone=+ 359 2 870 15 60 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q41588616
| content=
}}

* {{flag|Poland}} {{listing
| name=Poland | alt= | url=https://www.gov.pl/web/bulgaria | email=sofia.amb.sekretariat@msz.gov.pl
| address=ul. "Han Krum" 46 | lat=42.68575 | long=23.32645 | directions=
| phone= +359 2 902 34 00 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q30906047
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Romania}} {{listing
| name=Romania | alt= | url=http://sofia.mae.ro/ | email=sofia@mae.ro
| address=bul. "Mihai Eminescu" 4 | lat=42.685556 | long=23.351389 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 9733510 | tollfree=
| hours=M and F 09:00-12:00; W 09:00-12:00, 14:00-16:00; | price=
| wikidata=Q41588466
| lastedit=2021-12-03
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Russia}} {{listing
| name=Russia | alt= | url=https://bulgaria.mid.ru | email=
| address=bul. "Dragan Tsankov" 28 | lat=42.671944 | long=23.345833 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 963 4458 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q16687389
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Switzerland}} {{listing
| name=Switzerland | alt= | url=https://www.eda.admin.ch/sofia | email= sofia@eda.admin.ch
| address=ul. "Shipka" 33 | lat=42.6932 | long=23.3428 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 942 01 00 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q101095889
| content=
}}
* {{flag|UK}} {{listing
| name=Great Britain | alt=UK | url=https://www.gov.uk/world/organisations/british-embassy-sofia | email=BritishEmbassySofia@fcdo.gov.uk
| address=ul. "Moskovska" 9 | lat=42.69716 | long=23.32735 | directions=
| phone=+359 2 933 92 22, +44 20 7008 5000 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q59290116
| content=
}}

== Connect ==
5G internet is available from all three major mobile networks ([https://www.a1.bg/en A1], [https://www.vivacom.bg/en/ Vivacom], Yettel). WiFi is widely available in public places.

==Go next==
* In the region:
** To the north, among the [[Balkan Mountains]]: the Iskar Gorge, picturesque [[Etropole]], and [[Pravets]] with its golf resort and the museum of Bulgaria's last Communist dictator
** To the west: [[Bankya]], a mineral springs resort {{km|15}} from central Sofia, almost absorbed as a suburb (e.g. accessible by public transport)
** To the south-west: industrial [[Pernik]] on the other side of Vitosha; further away is [[Kyustendil]], "Bulgaria's orchard" under the Osogovo Mountain on the border
** To the south, under the slopes of Rila: [[Dupnitsa]] and [[Blagoevgrad]], with the [[Rila Monastery]], the most famous in Bulgaria and a {{unesco}} (suitable for a day trip from Sofia)
** To the south-east, closer: [[Samokov]] and the mountain/ski resorts of [[Borovets]] and Malyovitsa
* Elsewhere in Bulgaria:
** '''[[Plovdiv]]''' – Bulgaria's second most populous city, with good highway and rail connections to Sofia. Its Old Town, Roman ruins, and relaxed atmosphere make it a great day-trip.
** '''[[Veliko Tarnovo]]''' – A beautiful city along a winding river, the former capital of Bulgaria in the Middle Ages.
* Other countries:
** [[North Macedonia]], via the Gyueshevo/Deve Bair crossing by Kyustendil, {{km|130}} to the south-west, towards [[Kriva Palanka]] and [[Kumanovo]]
** [[Romania]], by international trains starting in Sofia - either [[Craiova]] via [[Vidin]], or the capital [[Bucharest]] via [[Ruse]]
** [[Serbia]] is less than {{km|60}} to the west, via the Kalotina/Gradine crossing - [[Dimitrovgrad (Serbia)|Dimitrovgrad]], [[Pirot]] and [[Niš]]
** [[Turkey]], by international train to [[Istanbul]]

{{routebox
| image1=Tabliczka E80.svg
| imagesize1=30
| directionl1=W
| majorl1=[[File:Aiga immigration.svg|18px]] Kalotina/Gradinje
| minorl1=[[Dragoman Marsh]]
| directionr1=E
| majorr1=[[Plovdiv]]
| minorr1=[[Pazardzhik]]
}}

{{usablecity}}
{{geo|42.7000|23.3333}}
{{isPartOf|Bulgarian Shopluk}}</text>
      <sha1>30653b6z1h5celfcez7g8kh20y4rr3j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
