<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikivoyage</sitename>
    <dbname>enwikivoyage</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.46.0-wmf.24</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="1728" case="first-letter">Event</namespace>
      <namespace key="1729" case="first-letter">Event talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Athens</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1808</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5264354</id>
      <parentid>5264353</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-20T18:20:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>~2026-24379-31</username>
        <id>2396013</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>5264354</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="144065" sha1="n173m5wgnu3oqqac26k5ysdfqah5cyv" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Athens Banner.jpg|disambig=yes|unesco_whs=yes}}
'''Athens''' ([[Greek phrasebook|Greek]]: {{Lang|el|Αθήνα}}, ''Athína'') is the capital city of [[Greece]] with a metropolitan population of 3.6 million inhabitants (2025) based on ELSTAT Census but with undocumented population it reaches 5.2 million. It was a major cultural, political and religious centre of [[Classical Greece]], a place that deeply influenced the course of Western civilization. Don't come expecting a philosopher's theme park; contemporary Athens is the graffiti-coated, fast-beating urban heart of the country, where modern Greek culture, business and social life flourish amidst ancient monuments.

== Districts ==
Athens is the largest city in Greece, and sprawls across the majority of the Attica region. Most areas of interest to visitors will be found within the central Athens municipality. The following are the five main regions. 

* [[Central Athens]] - The active heart of the city. Most ancient sites as well as museums can be found here. 
* [[North Athens]] - A mainly residential area. Contains some museums, high end restaurants and malls, and activities.
* [[West Athens]] - Residential with some malls. 
* [[Piraeus (Area)]] - Athens' main port. Location of National Library as well as some activities.
* [[South Athens]] - The location of most beaches accessible by public transport.

==Understand==
===Ancient Athens===
[[File:The Stoa of Attalus in Athens (50823740763).jpg|thumb|The reconstructed Stoa of Attalos, in the Ancient Agora]]
{{seealso|Ancient Greece|Greek mythology}}
According to mythology, the Greek Gods Poseidon and Athena wanted to claim the city for their own. To persuade the people to accept them, they granted gifts. Poseidon struck his spear into the ground and produced running water. Athena gave the city olive trees, which provide food and economic prosperity through trade. The people were then asked to vote for the Gods, and Athena won by a single vote, resulting in the city bearing her name.

The first pre-historic settlements were constructed in 3000 BCE around the hill of Acropolis. According to legend the King of Athens, Theseus, unified the ten tribes of early Athens into one kingdom in around 1230 BCE. This process of ''synoikismos'' ({{Lang|el|συνοικισμός}}) – bringing together in one home – created the largest and wealthiest state on the Greek mainland, but it also created a larger class of people excluded from political life by the nobility.

By the 7th century BCE, social unrest had become widespread, and the Areopagus appointed Draco to draft a strict new law code (hence "draconian"). Still, the Draconian laws were a big advancement, as they codified crime and punishment unlike the previous arbitrary judgments of the rulers. When Draco's system failed, they appointed Solon, with a mandate to create a new constitution (594 BCE). This was the great beginning of a new social revolution, which was the result of the democracy under Cleisthenes (508 BCE). When Roman historians wrote the history of their own republic, they fudged the date so that their republic would be older than Athenian democracy, but today's scholarly consensus is that Rome "got inspiration" from the Greeks.
[[File:Evzones marching, Athens, Greece.jpg|thumb|Evzones marching, Tomb of the Unknown Soldier]]
In the 5th century BCE, Athens reached the peak of its fame. It was the most powerful Greek city-state, and the center of Greek cultural life, claiming many important cultural advances within European history. Fields of study like science, philosophy, history, and medicine were advanced by Athenian scholars in the timeframe between 480 (the battle of Salamis) and 343 (when Aristotle went to Macedonia to assume teaching duties to Alexander the royal heir), known as Athens' "golden age" - although political dominance came to an end after the Peloponnesian War (431-404 BCE), most famous because of its ''History'' written by the Athenian general and scholar Thucydides, the "Father of Scientific History".

Later on, Athens became part of the [[Alexander the Great|Macedonian empire under Alexander]], and still later part of the [[Roman Empire]]. While it was decreasingly politically significant, its intellectual reputation gave it a special status, until, in the year 529 CE, Emperor Justinian issued an edict imposing a perpetual silence on all its schools, and the empire's intellectual center moved to [[Istanbul|Constantinople]].

Athens was thriving and prosperous during the Crusades, actually benefiting from the Italian trade during this period. However, this fruitful period was short-lived, as Greece suffered badly under the [[Ottoman Empire]], only to recover in the 19th century as the capital of independent Greece.

===Modern Athens===
[[File:Plaka1.JPG|thumb|250px|Old Athens]]
Athens was just a small provincial city when it was chosen in the 1830s to serve as the national capital of the modern Greek State. Although it had a prestigious past, the city's political, economic and cultural importance had declined over the centuries, leaving behind only its classical ruins as a reminder of better times. With the decision to move the national capital from Nafplio to Athens, architects and city planners were hired to build a new city next to the classical ruins, with grand neoclassical homes and public buildings, large city squares, green spaces, and wide avenues, making a conscious, decisive turn from the city's Ottoman past. The city regained its importance in Greek civilization, and by 1900 had evolved into a very attractive cosmopolitan city, with abundant neoclassical architecture harking to the nation's past.

[[File:National observatory Athens Greece.jpg|thumb|The National Observatory as seen from the Acropolis]]
The 20th century however, marked the rapid development of Athens. The city suffered minor damage during World War II, and suffered extensive urban planning in the decades that followed, as the nation rapidly industrialized and urbanized. In the 1960s and 1970s, many 19th century neoclassical buildings, often small and private, were demolished to make way for office buildings, often designed by great Greek architects. The city also expanded outward through rash development, particularly towards the west, as its population grew by absorbing job-seekers from the provinces. With the onset of the automobile, public officials reduced the city's public transportation services without foreseeing the traffic gridlock and smog that would menace the city by the 1980s.

By the late 1980s and early 1990s, the city's reality led to a rude awakening among local and national officials and, coupled with the country's new found remarkable prosperity, large scale projects began to slowly regenerate the city and undo some of the damage of previous decades. Over the course of the next 15 years, money was poured into new transportation infrastructure projects, the restoration of surviving neoclassical buildings, the gentrification of the city's historical center and the renovation of many former industrial areas and the city's coastline. The restoration of charming neoclassical buildings in the city's historical center has been accompanied by the construction of attractive post-modern buildings in newer districts; both of which have begun to improve the aesthetic essence of the city. The Athens urban area has grown to house 3.15 million people, nearly half the population of the entire country.

===2004 Olympic Games===
[[File:Panathenaic Stadium, Athens, 20240601 1026 0064.jpg|thumb|Panathenaic Stadium, hosting sporting events for over 2000 years.]]
Athens hosted the 2004 Summer [[Olympic Games]]. The entire urban area underwent major lasting changes that have improved the quality of life for visitors and residents alike. Aside from the new freeways and rail systems that were completed in time for the 2004 Olympics, the city's historic center underwent serious renovation. Most notable among the city's facelift projects are the ''Unification of Archaeological Sites'' (which connects the city's classical-era ruins and monuments to each other through a network of pleasant pedestrianized streets) and the restoration of the picturesque neoclassical ''Thissio'' and ''Pláka'' districts.

The men's and women's shot put competition was held at the restored stadium of [[Olympia (Greece)|Olympia]], where the ancient Olympic Games took place from 776 BCE to 394 CE. This was the first time in history that women athletes competed in this venue. Olympia is a lengthy but interesting day trip from Athens.

===Climate===
{{climate chart
|Athens
|8.6 |14.1 |52.1
|9.4 |15.2 |47.0
|11.1 |17.6 |31.9
|14.3 |21.6 |19.0
|18.4 |25.8 |17.0
|23.4 |31.1 |21.0
|26.6 |34.1 |5.9
|26.4 |33.6 |6.0
|22.6 |29.6 |21.2
|17.6 |24.1 |40.6
|14.0 |19.8 |60.0
|10.4 |15.6 |69.6

|float=right
|clear=right
|source=[[:w:Athens]]
|description=
}}
Spring and late autumn are the best times to visit Athens. Summer can be extremely hot and dry during heatwaves, but this rarely happens. Winter is definitely low season, with the occasional rainy or snowy day, but also an ideal time to save money while enjoying the city without countless other tourists.

Whilst peak traffic hour can be a bit smoggy on the main roads, on most sunny days the skies are azure blue. The main reason attributed for the pollution of Athens is because the city is enclosed by mountains in a basin which does not allow the smog to leave. The government's ban on diesel vehicles within Athens and the early 1990s initiatives to improve car emissions have greatly contributed to better atmospheric conditions in the basin.

===Orientation===
[[File:Hellenic Parliament from high above.jpg|thumb|right|Hellenic Parliament by sunset]]
The sprawling city is bounded on three sides by Mt. Ymettos, Mt. Parnitha and Mt. Pendeli; whilst inside Athens are twelve hills [the seven historical are: Acropolis, Areopagus, Hill of Philopappus, Observatory Hill (Muses Hill), Pnyx, Lycabettus, Tourkovounia (Anchesmus)], the Acropolis and Lykavittos being the most prominent. These hills provide a refuge from the noise and commotion of the crowded city streets, offering amazing views down to Saronic Gulf, Athens' boundary with the Aegean Sea on its southern side. The streets of Athens (signposted in Greek and English) now melt imperceptibly into [[Piraeus]], the city's ancient, and still bustling, port.

Many places of interest can be found within walking distance of the city centre at '''Syntagma Square''' (''Plateia Syntagmatos''), named after the Greek constitution (''syntagma'') proclaimed from the balcony of the royal palace that overlooks the square on 3 September 1843. It has been beautified, and the manic Athenian traffic has been re-routed. It contains a major metro stop flanked by cafes, restaurants, fast food, and airline offices. The square occasionally serves as a rallying place for demonstrations and public celebrations. It is bordered by the districts of Plaka to the south, Monastiraki to the west, Kolonaki to the east and Omonia to the north.

The '''Acropolis''' is the ancient high city of Athens, a prominent plateaued rock perched high above the modern city with commanding views and an amazing array of ancient architecture, mostly from the Classical period of Ancient Greece, the most famous of which is the Parthenon. A visit to Athens is not complete without visiting the Acropolis; hundreds of tourists each day accordingly make the pilgrimage.

Gentrified during the 1990s and now very popular with tourists, '''Plaka''' is a charming historic district at the foot of the Acropolis, with its restored 19th-century neoclassical homes, pedestrianized streets, shops and restaurants, and picturesque ruins from the city's Roman era. '''Thissio''', to the west side of the Acropolis, is very similar and now houses many restaurants and cafes. Between the two is '''Monastiraki''', a very bohemian district increasingly popular with tourists, with stores selling a variety of items including antiques, cookware, souvenirs, arts and crafts, movie posters, punk culture, funky clothing, and pretty much anything you can think of. Another part of Plaka is '''Anafiotika''' and is on the northernmost place. There you will find the first university of Athens before it was relocated in central Athens. It's an oasis of calm and quietness, and there are many green spaces which are part of the green space of Acropolis.

Plaka's boundaries are not precisely defined. Clear borders are the Ancient Agora and Plateia Monastiraki on the west, the Acropolis and Dhionysiou Areopayitou street on the south, the Temple of Olympian Zeus and Leoforos Amalias on the south-east, and the west part of Mitropoleos street, up to the cathedral on the north (but Mitropoleos street and Leoforos Amalias, though boundaries, shouldn't be considered part of Plaka, since they have a modern and fairly non-descript atmosphere). The north-eastern and eastern boundaries are a bit less well defined, but if you're south of Apollonos street and west of Nikis street you'll probably feel like you're still in Plaka.

'''Omonia Square''' ({{Lang|el|Πλατεία Ομονοίας}}) is the centre of Athens, and is composed of the actual square together with the surrounding streets, open areas and assemblage of grand buildings that include banks and offices. The neighbouring area of '''Exarcheia''' ({{Lang|el|Εξάρχεια}}) to the north, dominated by the Athens Polytechnic and its famous band of anarchists, is a bohemian district with lots of bars and clubs visited by students, intellectuals and people who are into alternative culture.

'''Kolonaki''' is near Lykavittos Hill. The district's borders are not very sharply defined; it covers the south and southeast slopes of Lykavettos Hill north of Vassilisis Sofias Avenue. Kolonaki is the posh area of central Athens. Traditionally the home of the in-town rich, it's the location of a number of embassies and several prominent archaeological schools, including The '''[https://www.ascsa.edu.gr/ American School]''' and The '''[https://www.bsa.ac.uk/ British School]'''.  It also has the city's greatest concentration of trendy fashion boutiques, and many, mostly upscale, cafes, bars and restaurants.

==Get in==
===By plane===
Athens airport is a major hub in the Aegean, Balkan and East Mediterranean regions. American, Air Canada, Air Transat, Delta, Emirates, Norwegian Air Shuttle and United maintain non-stop flights from North America (some are only seasonal), while a large number of European carriers fly direct into Athens. 

{{listing
   | type = go
   | name = Athens Eleftherios Venizelos International Airport
   | alt = {{IATA|ATH}}
   | url = https://www.aia.gr/traveler/
   | email = 
   | address = 
   | lat = 37.93607
   | long = 23.94463
   | directions = {{km|27}} east of the city centre near the suburb of [[Spáta]] ({{lang|el|Σπάτα}})
   | phone = 
   | tollfree = 
   | hours = 
   | wikipedia = Athens International Airport
   | wikidata = Q211734
   | lastedit = 2025-12-28
   | content = ATH opened in 2001 as part of the infrastructure improvements in preparation for the Olympics.  It is now one of the more attractive and efficient major European airports, though some old Athenian hands say they miss the messy atmosphere of the old Hellenikon. The airport has the usual array of fast food restaurants, duty-free shops, lounges, and other airport services. Free Wi-Fi used to be time-limited, but now is free to use for unlimited time.  There is a landside convenience store open 24 hours opposite the car rental counters.  Luggage storage, run by [https://www.care4bag.gr/ Care4bag], can be found at the south end of the airport, landside, on the arrivals level. Storage time varies from 6 to 36 hours, no automatic lockers.  Like many midsize airports, ATH is using remote hard stands and shuttle buses as an interim measure to expand capacity until it can justify building more permanent gates and jetways.  However, the shuttle bus rides can lead to significant delays if your plane is parked at a remote hard stand and not at a jetway next to the terminal. 
}}

There is a '''tourist information office''' on the arrivals level which can provide information about Greek ferries.

There is also a small '''museum''' on the top floor with interesting history information about Athens, and a space for temporary exhibits.

* {{Listing
   | type = go
   | name = flight by Eurowings
   | lat = NA
   | long = NA
   | url = https://www.eurowings.com/en/booking/offers/flights-to/-GR/ATH.html
   | content = flight from Cologne/Bonn Airport to ATH
   | price = from €29
   | lastedit = 2025-09-01
}}
* {{Listing
   | type = go
   | name = flight by Sky Express
   | lat = NA
   | long = NA
   | url = https://www.skyexpress.gr/en/flights-from-dusseldorf-to-athens
   | email = commercial@skyexpress.com
   | content = flight from [[Düsseldorf Airport]] to ATH
   | price = from €58
   | lastedit = 2025-09-01
}}

===By bus===
'''[https://ktelbus.com/en/ KTEL regional coaches]''' connect Athens to other cities in Greece. The fleet of buses has been upgraded, which makes the journey pleasant and safe. For some destinations one can also use the buses of the railroad company (OSE, see next section) that might be international, but can also be used for in-country transport. At times there are collaborations with companies from adjacent countries such as Turkey, Bulgaria, Serbia, North Macedonia and Albania, so it's advisable to ask on both the bus and the train companies about the available options.

There are two KTEL coach stations:
* {{go
| name=Liosion KTEL Station | alt=Σταθμός Λιοσίων | url= | email=
| address=Liosion Avenue | lat=38.010347 | long=23.7230531 | directions=near Aghios Nikolaos station on the Green line
| phone=+30 2108317186 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q18457006
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=
}}
* {{go
| name=Kifissos KTEL Station | alt=Σταθμός Κηφισού | url= | email=
| address=Kifissos Avenue | lat=37.9979 | long=23.6991 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q15238422
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=Bus routes X93 (Athens International Airport), 051 (Athens center), 052 (Elaionas Metro station), 420 (Piraeus port).
}}

Construction on a single consolidated terminal is underway in  Eleonas, expected to open in 2026.

====From Albania====
Several travel agencies offer bus service between Tirana and Athens, also stopping at several other cities in Albania.
Cost is usually €30 between Albania and Athens (same cost regardless of the city in Albania).
* {{go
| name=Albatrans | alt= | url=https://albtrans.com.al/en/ | email=info@albatrans.com.al
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+355 42 259 204 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=€30
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=
}}
* {{go
| name=Top Lines | alt= | url=https://top-lines.al | email= | address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2105203350-1 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=
}}
* {{go
| name=Papadakis Bros S.A. | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 52 02 551-3 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=
}}
* {{go
| name=Osumi Travel | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 52 49 268 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=€30, or €25 between Gjirokaster and Athens
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=
}}
* {{go
| name=Alvavel | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 5222436 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=€30
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=
}}

====From Bulgaria====
{{go
   | name = Flixbus
   | url = https://global.flixbus.com/bus-routes/bus-sofia-athens
   | content = from Sofia to Athens
   | lastedit = 2025-09-01
}}

===By road===

The main approaches to Athens by road are by the A1 motorway (European route E75) from the north and the A8 motorway (European route E94) from the west.

===By train===
[[File:Athens Metro 02 - 2008-09-15.JPG|thumb|You have to run the rail lines to Athens somewhere.]]
'''[https://www.hellenictrain.gr/ Hellenic Train]''', the national rail service, connects Athens to other cities in Greece. However, the national railroad system is limited compared to other European countries, in effect having only two lines. One goes south to the [[Peloponnese]]. The other goes to the north, connecting Athens with the second major city in Greece, [[Thessaloniki]] and [[Larissa]], the capital city of [[Thessaly]] region. From there the line continues further to the north and all the way to the east, passing through many other cities of northern Greece and eventually reaching [[Istanbul]].
* {{go
| name=Athens Central Railway Station | alt=Larissa Station | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.9919558 | long=23.7208624 | directions=Larissa Station of the red line (line 2)
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3560693
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=
}}

There are two types of train; normal, slow, type of train equipped with beds, and the so-called new 'Intercity' type which is more expensive because of a 'quality supplement fee' that grows with distance. For example, travelling from Athens to [[Thessaloniki]] by the 'Intercity' type will save one hour at most, but the ticket will be almost twice the price. 'Intercity' tends to be more reliable, yet more 'bumpy' than the normal train.

As of 2024, the international trains which used to connect Athens with [[Belgrade]] and [[Sofia]] via [[Thessaloniki]] have been suspended.

===By boat===
{{marker | type=go | name=[[Piraeus]] | lat=37.9351377 | long=23.6224843}} is the chief sea port of Athens. It is served by many ferries. Cruise ships also regularly visit, especially during warm months. Generally, pedestrian ferry users will be closer than cruise passengers to the Metro station providing access to central Athens; walking distances can vary considerably. Cruise passengers on larger ships usually reach the main cruise terminal by port shuttle bus; otherwise, it can be a non-trivial walk. Smaller ships (e.g., 1200 or fewer passengers) may dock near the terminal, an easy walk. From the terminal, pedestrians face a safe, level walk of over a mile to the Piraeus Metro station; taxis are readily available to go there, but are not cheap.

{{marker | type=go | name=[[Lavrio]]| lat=37.7085779 | long=24.0563638}} {{km|60}} south of city centre and {{marker | type=go| name=[[Rafina]]| lat=38.0229913 | long=24.0108963}} {{km|25}} east of city centre act as alternative ports of Athens. They are served by KTEL regional buses.

==Get around==

{{mapshapes|Q336488}} &lt;!-- Metro --&gt;
{{mapshapes|Q252135}} &lt;!-- Tram --&gt;

'''[https://www.oasa.gr/en/ Transport for Athens (OASA)]''' operates public transportation in Athens. Its subdivisions include STASY and OSY. A single ticket allows you to travel on any types of transport, metro, trams, buses, with unlimited transfers anywhere time within Athens for 90 minutes.

If you do not read Greek, signs on Athens transit always have a transliteration into Roman letters. Transliteration can vary; for example, ''Ellinko'' and ''Helliniko'' are both spellings for {{Lang|el|Ελληνικό}}. English information is abundant and most staff can communicate in English.

=== Fares ===
The base ticket price is {{EUR|1.20}}. This covers all OASA routes except for Airport Express lines (Line {{rint|athens|m3}} and Route X80). There are also Daily, 3-Day + Airport, 5-Day and bulk ticket packs. See details on the [https://www.oasa.gr/en/tickets/prices-of-products/ OASA fare table.]
{| class="wikitable"
|+
!price
!time
!Includes X80?
|-
|€1.20
|90min
|No
|-
|€4.10
|1 day
|Yes
|-
|€8.20
|5 days
|No
|-
|€20
|3 days
|Yes
|}
''(As of Dec 2025)''

'''The standard fare to or from the airport is {{Currency|EUR|9}} each way'''. This includes the full journey between any point in the Athens public transport system and the airport.

The contactless payment system "tap2ride" is available on all means of transport. Just tap your contactless Visa or Mastercard card or mobile phone (GPay, Apple Pay) on the reader! This will pay for a {{EUR|1.20}} simple ticket (or the airport fare). The cost is billed at the end of the day and capped at {{EUR|4.10}}.

Discounted fares (students, seniors) are only available through a personalised ATH.ENA card, though the hassle and one-time cost of {{Currency|EUR|4.50}} will probably not be worth it for a short stay. Please note that the '''ATH.ENA card and [https://www.oasa.gr/en/tickets/products/ath-ena-ticket/ ticket] are different''': they have different regulation. For example, the '''ticket''' is the better choice for tourists (easier and temporary) and does not allow to use for Athens Airport.  

===By metro===
[[File:Public transport map of Athens.png|thumb|Public transport map of Athens|350px]]
[[File:20140622-Anthoupoli-62D304_(7872).jpg|thumb|A Line 2 train in Anthoupoli station|300px]]
There are three lines:
* Line {{rint|athens|m1}}: '''Piraeus – Kifissia''', the oldest line, connects the port of Piraeus and the northern suburbs of Athens (Kifissia station) via the city centre. Be sure that you keep an eye on your personal stuff when using this line, and be prepared for people getting in the train and asking for money.
* Line {{rint|athens|m2}}: '''Anthoupoli – Elliniko''' connects western and southern Athens via Athens centre.
* Line {{rint|athens|m3}}: '''Dimotiko Theatro– Doukissis Plakentias – Airport''' connects Piraeus and the western suburbs with the eastern suburbs (Halandri and Doukissis Plakentias stations) and the International Airport.

Syntagma (constitution; {{Lang|el|Σύνταγμα}}), Larissa ({{Lang|el|Σταθμός Λαρίσης}}) station and Acropolis (Akropoli; {{Lang|el|Ακρόπολη}}) station are the major three stations in this system. 

Usually you need to pass a ticket validator before entering, but it is not needed at all exits. The stations run from 5:30 to 12:30.

Many metro stations (e.g. Syntagma) exhibit artifacts excavated during construction. During rush hour, it can become very crowded. In the summer, the air conditioning is not very efficient.

===By suburban railway===
The '''[https://www.hellenictrain.gr/ Athens Suburban Railway]''' (Proastiakos/{{Lang|el|Προαστιακός}}) is operated by Hellenic Train. There are 3 Proastiakos lines:
* From Piraeus to Airport
* From Piraeus to Aigio
* From Athens Central Station (Larissa station) to Chalkida.

===By tram===
[[File:Straßenbahnnetz Athen.png|thumb|[[File:Tram-Logo.svg|20px]] (2019)]]
The '''[http://www.stasy.gr/index.php?id=1&amp;no_cache=1&amp;L=1 Athens Tram]''' connects the city centre with the southern suburbs and has connections with the metro lines. There are three tram lines:
* Line {{rint|athens|t3}}: '''Peace and Friendship Stadium – Asklipeio Voulas Hospital''' connects Faliro with the southern suburbs and runs along the coastal zone.
* Line {{rint|athens|t4}}: '''Syntagma– Neos Kosmos – Peace and Friendship Stadium''' connects the city centre with Faliro.
* Line {{rint|athens|t5}}: '''Syntagma  – Neos Kosmos – Asklipeio Voulas Hospital''' connects the city centre with the coastal zone and the southern suburbs.

===By bus===
The [https://www.oasa.gr/ Athens Urban Transport Organisation] runs a network of diesel buses, natural gas buses and electric trolleybuses.  The price of express (X) bus lines like X93 (Airport - Kifissos Station) is {{Currency|EUR|5.50}} ({{Currency|EUR|2.70}} for children, teenagers, over 65). 

Most central bus stops have smart displays that show bus arrival times and transport announcements. 

===By taxi===
Canary yellow taxis are a common sight in Athens and are a reasonably priced way of getting around (if you can avoid the traffic jams). The starting fee is {{Currency|EUR|1.19}}, after which the meter ticks up at €0.34/km ("rate 1") or €0.64/km ("rate 2"), with a minimum fare of €3.20. Rate 1 applies through Athens city limits, including the airport, while rate 2 applies outside the city and from midnight to 05:00. Legal surcharges apply for calling a taxi by radio (€1.60), trips to or from the airport (€3.20) and heavy bags (€0.32). Tipping is not necessary, although it's common to round up to the nearest full euro.

Taxi fare fraud is not as widespread as it used to be, but it still happens, so insist on the meter and make sure the rate is correct. At busy tourist locations, drivers try to con with a set rate that is ridiculously high (e.g. €20 for a short trip). In these cases, it is best to find another and again insist on the charge shown on the meter. If you feel you have been overcharged, ask for a receipt (they are obliged to give one) and take the plate number, then phone the tourist police to report the driver on 171.

Taxi drivers rarely obey the rules of the road. Expect that if you are leaving Athens on an early flight the driver will drive aggressively to get you there as quickly as possible.

Taxis are considered to be fairly cheap in Athens. Therefore, you can expect to share the ride during rush hours if you can find one, and at night after the Metro has shut down. If you hail a taxi which is already occupied (occupied taxis have a brightly lit TAXI sign on top of the car) the driver will ask where you want to go to before letting you in to join the other customers.

Strikes by cabbies and public transit are common, so be prepared and watch the local news. If this puts you in a bind, your lodging host may have some creative solutions for you.

===By car===
You can rent a car at the airport, where most major international car rental companies have a presence. There are also several large local companies which will deliver the car outside of the airport.  There are two rental car lots at the airport, Lots A and B.  Keep track of which one you picked up the car at, because that is where you must return it. Both are a long walk from the rental car counters.

Rental cars with automatic transmissions are expensive.  Collision damage waiver (CDW) with deductible and "super cover" to reduce CDW deductible to zero are both very expensive.  When you see the scratched-up appearance of many Greek cars, you will understand why.

Unless you plan to stay off toll expressways, you will probably need euro bills or coins to pay cash tolls on the Attiki Odos expressway going to and from Athens.  The Attiki Odos company does not have any system in place with Greek rental car companies to automatically pass through tolls from its e-PASS electronic toll system to individual renters' accounts. 

Driving in Athens is notoriously difficult. Streets are extremely narrow, corners are blind and often tight, curbside parking is virtually impossible to find, drivers are aggressive, and accidents are frequent.  Motorcyclists often split lanes and weave across all lanes in order to filter forward through heavy vehicular traffic.  Road signs are small and cryptic.  Road markings are often faded and confusing.  As with much of Europe, street names are usually posted on signs affixed to building walls (rather than standalone posts at street corners). Certain intersections are configured in ways unheard of elsewhere, such as having a one-way street oscillate back and forth between completely opposite directions with each traffic light cycle to accommodate traffic on a perpendicular one-way street that does not line up with its onward counterpart on the other side (e.g., Agiou Meletiou at Moschonision).  Do not attempt to drive in Athens unless you have already acquired extensive experience driving elsewhere in similar conditions in a variety of rental cars.  

Numerous Athens traffic lights come with a stop sign on top, to remind drivers to come to a complete stop if the traffic light is not working.  Obviously, if the traffic light is showing a green light, that overrides the stop sign.  

Athens does not have parking meters or ticket vending machines for curbside parking.  In the unlikely event you can actually find a curbside space in Athens, curbside parking requires you to acquire a scratch-off card from a kiosk, scratch off the date and time you started parking, and leave the card on your dashboard.  In the alternative, you can pay online through a parking app, which will require data roaming or arranging for a local eSIM for your cell phone. 

Most garages in the city centre offer only valet parking.  Your car and any objects left inside are at the mercy of the valet staff, and it may end up three or four cars deep inside a tiny garage.  If you leave the car for a while, expect a long wait for retrieval since the valet has to move other cars out of the way. 

Self-park garages exist in Athens, but are rare.  If you insist on driving in Athens and prefer self-park, research such garages thoroughly and mark their locations in your map app.  Most adhere to the common system of requiring you to take a ticket to lift the entrance gate. The notable exception is Klafthmonos Square, where a camera reads your license plate at both the entrance and exit gates, and you must pay by plate number to exit.

The most convenient self-park garage for visiting the Acropolis and the Acropolis Museum is at the Sygrou-Fix metro station. The Klafthmonos Square self-park garage is convenient for visiting Syntagma Square and Monastiraki Square.  The PolisPark self-park garage at Platia Egiptou is convenient for visiting the National Archaeological Museum. It is one of the few self-park garages which sits outside the Daktylios boundary which is also within walking distance of a metro station (Victoria).

Always discuss with the rental car company whether your assigned vehicle is eligible to enter the Daktylios pollution control area in the city centre whenever that restriction is in effect (usually from October to July).  For vehicles not exempt from Daktylios, whether your vehicle's license plate number ends in an even or odd number controls whether the vehicle can enter the Daktylios area on calendar days that are even or odd numbers. In other words, if your vehicle's number is an even number and the current calendar day is an odd number, you cannot enter the Daktylios, and vice versa.

===By bicycle===
Athens is not a friendly city for cyclists, as it does not have many bicycle lanes, and the car drivers tend to drive quite aggressively. Nevertheless (or maybe because of this) riding a bicycle in Athens has become lately some sort of a political (counter-)action, especially by young people with an alternative lifestyle. In general, tourists not familiar with the terrible Athenian traffic are not advised to use a bicycle as a principal means of transport. But within the network of pedestrian streets in the historical city centre, rides are safe and can be quite enjoyable. A bike hire scheme is at its fledgling stages; its bike station is in Technopolis.

===On foot===
Several central streets have been pedestrianized. A mostly car-free archaeological walk starts at Vasilisis Amalias Street, passes in front of the Acropolis Museum, Acropolis, Herodion Theatre, Thiseio (Apostolou Pavlou Str), Ermou Street and ends at the popular area of Kerameikos (Gkazi) where there are many bars and clubs. Pleasant walking can also be had in '''Plaka''', especially its upper reaches, and in much of '''Kolonaki'''. The National Garden can provide a welcome respite from the heat and noise of the city centre.

Away from the touristy streets, walking in Athens is more challenging. Athens traffic can make crossing the street in some areas difficult, and walking down some very urban streets is an unpleasant experience due to noise pollution. The humidity of summer is exhausting, and there are parks to provide an escape from it. Fortunately, much of the traffic-plagued area of the city can be avoided by the use of the Metro, which goes most places a visitor would want to see or walk around in.

Wear comfortable shoes with good traction, and make sure that you leave home any high heels or similar shoes. Some sensitive archaeological sites have banned heels because the pointed heels damage the soft, slippery marble that you're walking on.

=== Airport transfers===

==== Metro and suburban train ====
At the airport both metro trains and suburban trains pass from the '''same platform'''. If you are travelling to some small stations, you should take the metro trains, because there are more stations for stop.

The airport trains run every 36 minutes. Not all Metro trains from central Athens go to the airport; trains in the intervals turn around at Doukissis Plakentias. Airport trains are indicated on the schedule and by an airplane logo on the front of the train, they are also announced by the signs on the metro platform.

The airport metro station has a desk staffed most hours by someone who speaks English. They hang the time table of airport train on the window at the shelter (at Syntagma station). It's useful to go to the Metro station the day before, explain to the agent (mostly English can be spoken) when you need to be at the airport, and ask what time you should catch the airport train from that station.

You can buy the ticket from a vending machine with credit card or cash, or tap your contactless credit card at the fare gate.

[https://www.hellenictrain.gr/ '''Suburban Railway'''] (line A1/A2) from Airport station to Athens Central station (Larissa/Larissis)  leaves at xx:07 every hour, passing through Central Athens before heading to Piraeus. Trains to Northern Greece and the Peloponnese depart from Athens central station. From Airport station to Monastiraki station via change at Nerantziotissa. A change at Neratziotissa suburban station (connection to Metro Line 1 "Neratziotissa station") can take you to The Monastiraki station. Or change at Doukissis Plakentias to Line 3 (blue) of the metro to get to Monastiraki and Syntagma stations. Suburban trains run more sparsely than the metro.

==== By express bus ====
It takes 45 minutes to 1½ hours depending on traffic. Buses, unlike Metro, operate 24 hours a day. When leaving to the airport early from Syntagma (before the metro opens), tickets can be bought at a kiosk next to the bus stop.

==== By bus ====
'''[http://ktelattikis.gr/en/lavrion KTEL Attikis Buses]''', the sole transport provider for all long-distance bus lines of Attica, depart from a stop in front of the Sofitel Hotel to Koropi metro station (€1.60, 15 min, as of Mar 2025). Their frequency varies throughout the day, from every half an hour to more than three; see linked schedule (the workers at the express bus stop have no information about KTEL buses). From Koropi Station you can take the metro to the city centre paying the normal ticket price of €1.20, and so avoid the additional fare of €5.50 charged to Koropi from the airport and vice versa. You can also take local bus 308 from Koropi metro for the same price. For getting to the airport, KTEL buses pass Koropi Station 20-30 minutes before the departure times from the airport listed on the above linked schedule.

==== By taxi ====
If you take a taxi, you should know that there is a special rule. Taxi rides to the centre cost €40 during the day and €60 during the night. Prices are fixed and includes toll costs.

==Talk==
: ''Please see this [[Greece#Talk|section at the country level]] for a full discussion''

While Greek is the official language in Greece, many Athenians speak English and those in the tourist industry are likely to also speak French and/or German. Almost all signs are written in Greek and English.

==See==
{{Mapframe|37.9792|23.7324|zoom=14|width=520|height=560|layer=W|lang=en}}At first glance, Athens seems entirely to be composed of unremarkable, four- to six-story concrete buildings, lacking character and badly in need of a paint job. But if you look beyond that, you will find little gems tucked in among the grey. The areas at the foot of the Acropolis, Anafiotika, Plaka, Monastiraki and Thissio are home to many wonderful Neoclassical buildings, trendy and traditional cafes and shops, narrow winding streets, and incredible views of the Acropolis. Little Greek Orthodox churches are tucked in among the concrete, often in the most unexpected places. These are usually beautifully decorated with icons and brass fixtures inside, but make sure you're appropriately dressed (no short sleeves or bare legs is a good rule of thumb, as a mark of respect).

=== Acropolis ===
{{infobox|Greece Archaeological Site Pricing|In 2025, Greece introduced a new pricing system for most of the country's archaeological sites:
* {{EUR|30}} for the Acropolis
* {{EUR|20}} for archaeological sites and museums with over 200,000 visitors 
* {{EUR|15}} for archaeological sites and museums with over 75,000 visitors 
* {{EUR|10}} for archaeological sites and museums with over 15,000 visitors 
* {{EUR|5}} for other archaeological sites and museums

There are no longer any combo tickets, each site charges a separate entry fee.

Entrance fees are halved for EU citizens over 65 or teachers accompanying students. Some sites also offer free entry to EU citizens under 25 and children of any nationality under 18. Additional discounts apply to certain Greek residents. Most other discounts offered to non-Greek residents before 2025 are no longer available.
}}
* {{see
| name=Acropolis of Athens | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.97145 | long=23.72377 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 3214172 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Acropolis of Athens | wikidata=Q131013
| lastedit=2025-12-04
| content=It was the ancient fortified town of Athens, dating back to the Late Bronze Age. It is now a UNESCO World Heritage Site for its historic role and the many iconic buildings of the Greek Classical age, among them the Parthenon, the Erectheion, and the Temple of Athena Nike. The key landmark of Athens, visible from afar, the Acropolis dominates the Athenian sky and symbolizes the foundation of modern culture and civilization. The Acropolis is considered to be an enduring symbol of Western civilisation.
}}

Atop the Acropolis are several dramatic ruins, in various states of restoration:
* {{see
| name=Propylaea | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3407649
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=The monumental gate at the western end of the Acropolis with Doric columns of Pentelic marble. In a prominent position on a steep bastion to the right of the entrance is the ''Temple of Athena Nike''
}}
[[File:View of the Acropolis Athens (pixinn.net).jpg|thumb|The Acropolis, the birthplace of Western civilization]]
* {{see
| name=Parthenon | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q10288
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=This massive temple was built in the 5th century BC in thanksgiving for the Greek victory over Persian invaders. It was later converted into a Christian church, then an Ottoman mosque. It was mostly intact until 1687, when a Venetian bomb landed on the Parthenon, which the Ottomans had used as a munitions dump. From 1800 to 1803, the 7th Earl of Elgin removed many of the surviving sculptures and shipped them to England. Since 1975, numerous large-scale restoration projects have been undertaken to preserve remaining artefacts and ensure its structural integrity.
}}
* {{see
| name=Erectheion | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q242741
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=This elegant temple was primarily dedicated to the goddess Athena. The uneven ground led to a complex plan, with an east-facing entrance lined with six Ionic columns. Unusually, the temple has two porches, one borne by Ionic columns, the other supported by huge female ''caryatids''.
}}

The full ticket is €30, reduced ticket is €15 (see sidebar). Hours are 08:00-20:00 during summer (Apr-Aug). During the winter, closing time tracks sunset, down to 17:00 in Dec. ''Last entry is 30 min before closing time''.

Many portions of the site are undergoing significant but badly needed renovations. You will encounter the construction office along the south side of the Parthenon.  Some views will be marred by scaffolding, cranes, tracks, and other modern equipment.

The Acropolis has two entrances, from the west and the south.
* The main entrance is at the west end of the Acropolis. From the Akropoli metro stop and New Acropolis Museum, walk west along Dionysiou Areopagitou Street and take the first right on to Theorias; from the Thissio metro stop west of Monastiraki, walk west to Apostolou Pavlou Street, turn left on it, and walk south to turn left on Theorias. From Plaka, you can walk south up steep Mnisikleous Street as far as you can go and turn right on Theorias. 
* The entrance from the south is near the Theater of Dionysos. 

To comply with European regulations, disabled access to the Acropolis is allowed by means of special paths and a purpose-built lift on the north face of the hill.  The lift is ''only'' for the use of those in wheelchairs.  All other visitors are expected to be able to climb and descend the Acropolis on their own, including the very old and very young. 

Since 1 April 2024, timed-entry tickets are mandatory.  Buying online in advance is strongly recommended.  Make sure you are buying from the '''[https://hhticket.gr/tap_b2c_new/english/tap.exe?PM=P1P&amp;place=000000002 HHTicket official web site]'''.  The on-site ticket offices can sell timed-entry tickets, but then you have to stand in a long line to buy a ticket, and in peak season, the ticket offices may not have time slots available for that same day.  As for accessing the actual entrance gates, Acropolis staff will not let you into the line to have your ticket scanned until less than 15 minutes before the scheduled entry time on your ticket.  

Guides can nearly always be found near the entrance gates offering you a private tour of the Acropolis, at a price. As an alternative, ask for the free leaflet published by the Archaeological Resources Fund, which includes a ground plan of the site and valuable information on the various monuments.

Additional historic sites and artifacts at the foot of the Acropolis are also included with the admission ticket. Most notably:
* {{see
| name=Theatre of Dionysus | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.97067 | long=23.72764 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= |wikipedia=Theatre of Dionysus
| content=Classical Athens' main theatre, the first theatre ever built. Many of the great Greek plays were performed here for the first time. According to Plato's ''Symposium'', it could hold an audience of 19,000 spectators. Aristophanes' ''The Clouds'', mocking Socrates, was first performed here, and Plato considered this play to be a contributing factor in Socrates' trial and execution.
| wikidata=Q1227044}}
* {{see
| name=Odeon of Herodes Atticus | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.97090 | long=23.72457 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Odeon of Herodes Atticus
| content=This theatre, built in 161 CE, is still used for concerts and plays. The stone backdrop is still preserved to a remarkable height of 3 stories, because it was incorporated into a later fortification on the site.
| wikidata=Q1328165}}

The Acropolis Museum is outside the Acropolis security perimeter, you will need to buy a separate timed-entry ticket for that attraction.  Therefore, to see both on the same day, you must estimate how much time you will need for both attractions. Most people need a minimum of one hour to tour the Acropolis. Anyone with a passion for history, classics, or scenic photography will need at least two hours. Opinions vary on which to see first, but most people agree that you should see both. If it's a sunny summer day, you may want to be inside the air-conditioned museum instead of atop the shadeless Acropolis during the peak heat.

{{see
| name=Acropolis Museum | alt= | url=https://www.theacropolismuseum.gr/en | email=info@theacropolismuseum.gr
| address=Dionysiou Areopagitou 15, 11742 | lat= | long= | directions=Acropolis metro station
| phone=+30 210 900 0900 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=€20, reduced €10
| wikidata=Q421084
| lastedit=2025-12-14
| content=You will need to purchase a timed-entry ticket for this museum, separate from the Acropolis. Buying online in advance from the official website is strongly recommended. This museum replaces an older museum on the Acropolis, which was far too small to hold and display all the artifacts recovered by archaeologists. Its design looks very "modern" from the outside, but on the inside it's very intuitive. The main floor is filled with a seemingly-endless collection of classical sculptures excavated from each stage of pre-Roman Athens. The top floor has an excellent view of the Acropolis and lavish placeholder exhibits for the Parthenon Marbles, to refute the United Kingdom's arrogant excuse that Greece did not have an appropriate place to display them. Most people will need at least one hour; anyone who loves classical art will need two hours or more. Exhibits have detailed descriptions, and the museum offers a free app-based audioguide. Archaeologists uncovered Roman ruins at the site before construction began; the final compromise was to elevate the museum above them.  After you visit the museum, go down the path to the left of the main entrance plaza and use your museum ticket to access the Roman ruins.
}}

===Archaeological sites===
The Acropolis is the only major attraction where extreme overtourism requires extensive advance planning. Other ancient sites can be seen at your leisure. Nearly all are within 2 km of the Acropolis.

* {{see
| name=Pnyx | alt=Ancient Greek: Πνύξ; [[Greek]]: Πνύκα, ''Pnyka'' | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.971667 | long=23.719444 | directions={{m|500}} west of the Acropolis
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Free
| wikipedia=Pnyx | wikidata=Q1125096
| lastedit=2019-03-07
| content=If Athens is the birthplace of democracy, then Pnyx is its cradle. Around 507 BCE this rocky hill, overlooking the Akropolis, became the meeting place for the ''ekklesia'', Athens' early democratic assembly. This site thus witnessed addresses by Pericles, Aristides and Alcibiades during the "Golden Age" of Athens, and had a capacity for 6000 to 13,000 hearers. The site was redesigned several times, creating three distinct phases in its history, until the ''ekklesia'' moved to the Theatre of Dionysos some time during the first century BCE. During the Roman era Pnyx was instead used as a sanctuary of Zeus.
}}
* {{see
| name=Ancient Agora | alt= | url=http://odysseus.culture.gr/h/3/eh351.jsp?obj_id=2485 | email=
| address= | lat=37.9751 | long=23.7224 | directions= accessible only from the western entrance at Plateia Jacqueline de Romilly; the historic Panathenaic Way is undergoing a major construction project, blocking the main north entrance until 2026
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-Su 08:30 - 15:30, M 10:00-15:30 | price=€20, reduced €10, ticket valid for both the archaeological site and the museum
| wikidata=Q395367
| lastedit=2025-12-04
| content=The site of the ancient city centre is a green space with a beautiful view of the Acropolis.  It was built as a multipurpose area, then evolved into a religious area over time.  The Ancient Agora was eventually abandoned and then large parts of it were later built over for a thousand years. The open space you see today was excavated starting in the 1850s.
}}
:Contains the following sites:
:* {{see
| name=Temple of Hephaestus | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.9757 | long=23.7215 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q756824
| lastedit=2019-03-07
| content=The best preserved ancient Greek temple, 5th century BCE.
}}
:* {{see
| name=Stoa of Attalus | alt=Museum of the Ancient Agora | url=http://odysseus.culture.gr/h/1/eh151.jsp?obj_id=3290 | email=
| address= | lat=37.9752 | long=23.7242 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1263335
| lastedit=2019-03-07
| content=This building was reconstructed in the 1950s from its original foundations, incorporating as much of the original structure and materials as possible, with limestone quarried from Piraeus and roof tiles made of clay from Attica. It is used as a museum to house relics found in the Agora.  
}}
:* {{see
| name=Church of the Holy Apostles | alt=Agias Apostoli | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.974 | long=23.7239 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2615369
| content=From the 11th century, one of the oldest churches in Athens.
}}
[[File:Ac.agora3.jpg|thumb|right|The Tower of the Winds and the ruins of the Roman Forum]]
* {{see
| name=Roman Agora | alt=Roman Forum | url=http://odysseus.culture.gr/h/3/eh352.jsp?obj_id=2402 | email=
| address= | lat=37.9743 | long=23.7265 | directions=at the western end of Plaka
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=08:30 - 16:00 | price=€10, reduced €5
| wikidata=Q1435551
| lastedit=2025-12-04
| content=This area became the main marketplace of the city after the Ancient Agora to the west became primarily a religious facility under Roman rule.  It houses the Tower of the Winds, an eight-sided tower with a different wind deity on each side, the remains of ancient shops, and a fountain.  Although the official entrance faces the end of Pikilis, you cannot buy tickets at the entrance. The ticket office is just around the corner and across the street to the north, on Epaminonda. 
}}
* {{see|name=Kerameikos
|lat=37.97859 | long=23.71811
| hours=08:30 - 16:00 | price=€10, reduced €5
| wikidata=Q630974
| lastedit=2019-03-07
|content=The site of the ancient cemetery of Athens. It also houses the Dipylon Gate, where the Panathenaic procession would begin. Its museum showcasing many of the grave stele and other archaeological items found on the grounds. The site has more than 20 tortoises, so be sure to watch your step and not trample on them.}}
[[File:AteneOlympieionDaAcropoli.jpg|thumb|The Temple of Olympian Zeus and Hadrian's Gate, seen from the Acropolis]]
* {{see
| name=Temple of Olympian Zeus | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.9695 | long=23.7331 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€10, reduced €5
| wikidata=Q1123019
| lastedit=2025-12-15
| content=Only the ruins remain today. The column that has fallen and can still be seen in pieces was brought down during a thunderstorm about a century ago.
}}
* {{see
| name=Arch of Hadrian | alt=Hadrian's Gate | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=next to Temple of Olympian Zeus
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=Free
| wikidata=Q1567576
| lastedit=2025-12-15
| content=A monumental gateway resembling a Roman triumphal arch. It was built around 131 AD to honor the Roman emperor Hadrian, an admirer of Greek culture, for his many benefactions to the city.
}}
* {{see
| name=The Lyceum | alt=Λύκειο, Lýkeio | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.974075 | long=23.743503 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€10, reduced €5
| wikidata=Q1160664
| lastedit=2019-03-07
| content=An ancient temple here hosted lectures by Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle, and early meetings of the Athenian Assembly. Aristotle made the temple the home of his school, the Lyceum. It hosted the world's first zoo and botanical garden, as well as a library which preserved classical Greek works for centuries afterwards. Rediscovered in 1996, the site can now be viewed outdoors. Entrance is from the north, from the same entrance as for the Byzantine and Christian museum.
}}
* {{see
| name=Plato's Academy | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.992359 | long=23.708059 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q193093
|lastedit=2026-02-09| content=This house of study was founded by the famous philosopher Plato. His equally famous follower Aristotle studied here for 20 years before leaving to found a school of his own. The site is an outdoor free park where you can see the excavated ruins. The ruins are not well explained or particularly impressive, but they do form a very nice park in a charming family oriented neighborhood. The exact coordinates given here are for a sign which best explains the various ruins in the park. The site is a long walk from all other historic sites, or a single bus route which runs slower than walking on the busy streets.
}}
* {{see
| name=Hadrian's Reservoir | alt= | url=https://www.atlasobscura.com/places/hadrians-reservoir | email=
| address= | lat=37.979044111132616 | long=23.741593526570966 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=Free
| content=Now the base of a summertime outdoor cinema, you can view the remains of the reservoir that was the terminus of an aqueduct that transported water for Roman-era Athenians from Parnitha to the base of Mount Lycabettus. You can only peer through windows and are not able to descend into the reservoir.
}}

===Modern sites===
* {{see
| name=Panathinaiko Stadium | alt= | url=http://www.panathenaicstadium.gr/HomePage/tabid/84/language/en-US/Default.aspx | email=info@panathenaicstadium.gr
| address=Leof. Vasileos Konstantinou | lat=37.96835 | long=23.74111 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 75 22 984-6 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=€12 entry / €6 concession
| wikipedia=Panathenaic Stadium | wikidata=Q208811
| lastedit=2022-10-18
| content=The stadium that housed the first modern day Olympic Games of 1896. Earlier versions of the stadium date as far back as 330 BCE. It's an enormous, white, marble stadium, with a horseshoe configuration.
}}
* {{see
| name=Lycabettus Hill | alt= | url=https://www.lycabettushill.com/ | email=
| address= | lat=37.982 | long=23.7434 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1357713
| lastedit=2025-10-10
| content=A 200m hill bordering the Kolonaki district. You can reach the top by walking (the path starts 15 minutes from Evangelismos metro stop, and will take 30 minutes to walk up the winding, but paved and not steep, path) or by a funicular railway (€10 single/€13 return trip). From halfway up looking towards the sea there are astonishing views of the Parthenon with the blue of the sea glimpsed between its columns. And from the top you can see the whole city, the port of Piraeus and, on a clear day, the island of Aegina and the Peloponnese. Have a drink at the cafe there, and visit the chapel of St George.
}}
* {{see
| name=Olympic Stadium | alt= | url=http://www.oaka.com.gr | email=
| address= | lat=38.036129 | long=23.785403 | directions=Eirini Station (Metro Line 1)
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q189663
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=National Theatre | alt= | url=http://www.n-t.gr/ | email=
| address=Agiou Konstantinou 22 | lat=37.98479 | long=23.72532 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=National Theatre of Greece | wikidata=Q583039
| content=A low but imposing building erected between 1882 and 1890 by architect Ernst Ziller in the eclectic style of that age, commissioned by King George I.
}}
[[Image:Tomb_of_the_unknow.jpg|thumb|right|Tomb of the Unknown Soldier at the bottom of the Greek Parliament]]
* {{see
| name=Syntagma Square | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.97555 | long=23.73484 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1137997
| content=Check out the Parliament building and the newly restored Grande Bretagne Hotel. 
}}
:* {{see
| name=Hellenic Parliament Building
| address= | lat=37.97529 | long=23.73707
| content=This building is on the eastern side of the square. It was the former royal palace before Greece became a republic.  At its base, facing the square, is the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier.  
}}
:* {{see
| name=Tomb of the Unknown Soldier | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.97553 | long=23.73641 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q3531128
| content=Catch the changing of the guards in front of the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier in front of Parliament every hour on the hour.  The guards are a fascinating sight; they wear distinctive uniforms with pleated kilts and leather clogs with pom-poms.  The uniforms and the guards' unusual marching style are a tribute to the light infantry insurgents (evzones) who bravely fought the Greek War of Independence.  Make sure you don't get too close or stand on the wrong side of them if you want to take a picture. If that occurs, they will knock their gun and, as they are not allowed to speak, another guard in regular military uniform will kindly ask you to change position. A more elaborate version of the ceremony takes place at 11:00 every Sunday, when it is accompanied by a marching military band.
}}

===Further away===
[[File:Dafni Monastery.jpg|thumbnail|Dafni monastery]]
* {{see
| name=Daphni Monastery | alt= | url=http://odysseus.culture.gr/h/2/eh251.jsp?obj_id=1514 | email=1eba@culture.gr
| address=Athinon avenue | lat=38.01298 | long=23.63593 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 5811558 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Tu and F 08:00-15:00 | price=Free admission
| wikipedia=Daphni Monastery | wikidata=Q500444
| lastedit=2018-03-26
| content=An 11th-century Byzantine monastery and [[UNESCO World Heritage site]]. Damaged by an earthquake in 1999, but has now been fully restored.
}}
*{{see
| name=Kaisariani Monastery and Gardens | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Kaisariani Monastery | lat=37.960833 | long=23.798333 | directions=It's easiest to take a taxi
| phone=+30 210 723 6619 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Kaisariani Monastery | wikidata=Q1168003
|lastedit=2023-02-25| content=A nice escape from the city in the foothills of Mount Hymettus. Walking trails. There's a functional monastery one can walk in, and several ruined chapels or basilicas up on the walks.
}}

===Museums and galleries===

Because of its antiquity and influence, Athens is full of museums and galleries. The major ones are the National Archaeological Museum, the Acropolis Museum, the Benaki and Museum of Cycladic Art, the Agora Museum, and the Kanellopoulos and Folk Art Museums.

====Archaeology museums====
[[File:The Antikythera Mechanism (3209887483).jpg|thumb|The Antikythera Mechanism, an ancient computer.]]
* {{see
| name=National Archaeological Museum of Athens | alt= | url=https://www.namuseum.gr/en | email=eam@culture.gr
| address=44 Patission St | lat=37.98910 | long=23.73276 | directions=
| phone=+30 213 214 4800 | tollfree=
|fax=| hours=Winter: W-M 08:30–15:30, Tu 13:00–20:00 | price=€12, reduced €6
| wikidata=Q637187
|image=| lastedit=2025-12-15
| content=This is the largest and most popular of Athens' many museums, and is usually very crowded. Its vast collection includes treasures unearthed from Mycenae by Heinrich Schliemann; a staggering array of sculpture including the earliest known Greek figurines dating from around 2,000 BCE; frescoes from the volcanic island of Santorini; and remains of Antikythera mechanism, the oldest known mechanical computer. Plan to make several visits to absorb it all.
}}
* {{see
| name=Kanellopoulos Museum | alt= | url=https://pacf.gr/en/ | email=info@pacf.gr
| address=12 Theorias &amp; Panos Streets | lat=37.97300 | long=23.72596 | directions=Plaka
| phone=+30 21 0324 4447 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Tu-Su 08:00-15:00 | price=Apr-Oct: €4, €2 reduced; Nov-Mar: €2
| wikipedia=Museum of Pavlos and Alexandra Kanellopoulou | wikidata=Q4306141
| lastedit=2018-03-26
| content=A small but excellent museum displays artifacts from Mycenean Greece on, and includes some wonderful Persian artifacts.
}}

====Art museums====
The visual arts have a big role in the Athenian life. Next to big institutions such as the National Gallery and the Benaki Museum, many small private galleries are spread across the city centre and the surrounding areas, hosting the works of contemporary visual and media artists. Bar galleries have sprung up, where you can have a drink or a coffee while visiting an exhibition.

* {{see
| name=Benaki Museum of Greek Culture | alt= | url=https://www.benaki.gr/index.php?lang=en | email=
| address=1 Koumbari St. &amp; Vas. Sofias Ave | lat=37.97602 | long=23.74038 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=W F 10:00-18:00; Th Sa 10:00-00:00; Su 10:00-16:00 | price=€9, students, seniors, people with disabilities and teachers €7; temporary exhibitions €7/€5; €25 Benaki Museum Experience ticket entitles the visitor to one entrance per exhibition in all the Benaki Museum buildings, valid for 3 months
| wikidata=Q816669
| lastedit=2019-03-07
| content=Visit the beautiful Neoclassical main building which houses collections of Greek art, from ancient times through the Byzantine period and the modern state. Open late and for free on Thursday evenings. The museum shop is a good place to buy souvenirs. There is a small selection at high prices but the quality is excellent.
}}
[[File:Stathatos Mansion.JPG|thumb|The Museum of Cycladic Art]]
* {{see
| name=Museum of Cycladic Art | alt= | url=http://www.cycladic.gr/en | email=
| address= | lat=37.9757 | long=23.74227 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=M W-Su 10:00 to 17:00, open till 20:00 on Th | price=€7, on Mondays and students - €3.50
| wikidata=Q1230253
| lastedit=2019-03-07
| content=Holds the second largest collection of Cypriot antiquities in the world outside Cyprus, after the Metropolitan Museum in New York. Some of the most popular exhibits include the Cycladic figurines, the idols from Early Bronze Age Cyclades, whose style greatly influenced modernist work in the 20th century, and Cypriot pottery and Ancient Greek artifacts, especially the ‘Scenes of Daily Life in Ancient Greece’ display, which is popular with families. They also sell great souvenirs, and lunch is available at the elegant Aethrion Café. If you are lucky, there may be a quirky temporary exhibition too (with no extra entry fee), as they hold archaeological, modern and contemporary art exhibitions.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Gallery | alt= | url=http://www.nationalgallery.gr/en | email=
| address=Michalakopoulou 1 | lat=37.97563 | long=23.74938 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=National Gallery (Athens) | wikidata=Q1167467
| lastedit=2019-03-19
| content=It's one of Greece's main art institutions and features paintings and works of art from some of Greece's and Europe's best from the 19th and 20th centuries. Emphasis is given to popular Greek contemporary artists including Giannis Tsarouchis, Domenikos Theotokopoulos (a.k.a. El Greco), Theodors Vrizakis, Nikolaos Kounelakis, Nikiforos Litras, Konstantinos Parthenis, Maleas, Giannis Moralis and others.
}}
* {{see
| name=Benaki Museum of Islamic Art | alt= | url=http://www.benaki.gr | email=
| address=22 Ag. Asomaton &amp; 12 Dipilou Streets – Kerameikos | lat=37.97924 | long=23.72023 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| lastedit=2019-02-09
| hours=Th F Sa Su 10:00-18:00 | price=€9; students, seniors and teachers €7
| content= An excellent collection which anyone interested in Islamic art will want to see. The museum was opened in 2004 as a branch of the Benaki, but is in a different part of town in two connected buildings.
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Greek Folk Art | alt= | url=http://www.melt.gr/en | email=
| address=22 Panos str., Plaka | lat=37.972533 | long=23.732308 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=M W-Su 08:00-15:00 | price=€2; students from non–EU countries, senior citizens from EU €1; under 19, students from EU (with ID), and people with disabilities free
| wikidata=Q4306259
| lastedit=2017-12-12
| content=An excellent museum of its type. Too often neglected by visitors to Athens, even though it is in the heavily touristed Plaka neighbourhood. Displays include artefacts, tools, primitive painting, folk pottery and interior decor. It is particularly strong on costume and embroidery.
}}
* {{see
| name=Athens Municipal Art Gallery | alt=Pinakothiki | url=http://www.elculture.gr/blog/venues/dimotiki-pinakothiki-athinwn/#prettyPhoto | email=
| address=Pireos, 51 | lat=37.98088 | long=23.72144 | directions=near Koumoundourou square
| phone=+30 210 3231841 | tollfree=
| hours=M-F 09:00-13:00 and 17:00-21:00 | price=
| wikidata=Q1576793
| content=Paintings of Greek painters of the first half of the 20th century are displayed.
}}
* {{see
| name=Vorres Museum | alt= | url=http://www.vorresmuseum.gr/ | email=
| address=1 Parodos Diadochou Constantinou St., Paiania, Attiki | lat=37.95264 | long=23.8476 | directions=Public transport: Metro Line 3 to Nomismatokopio, then bus 125 or 308 to 1st Agias Triado stop. Alternatively: Metro Line 3 to Koropi, then bus 307 to 2nd Agias Triados stop
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Sa Su 10:00-14:00, weekdays by appointment only and for groups of at least 20 people | price=€5, students €3
| wikidata=Q7941879
| lastedit=2015-05-29
| content=A museum of folk and contemporary art. Its grounds cover 320,000 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (80 acres) including several buildings, gardens and courtyards. Its collection includes over 6,000 pieces covering 4,000 years of Greek history and art. The museum was donated by the Vorres family to the Greek state.
}}
[[File:Old Greek Parliament Athens.jpg|thumb|250px|National Historical Museum (Old Parliament)]]
[[File:Averof_Today2.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Averof ship museum]]

====Other museums====
[[File:Kotsanas Museum at Katakolon port.jpg|thumb|Museum of Ancient Greek Technology]]
* {{see
| name=Museum of Ancient Greek Technology Kotsanas | alt= | url=https://kotsanas.com/en/home-en/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 693 183 1530 | tollfree=
| hours=10.00-15.00 | price=
| wikidata=Q15260365
|lastedit=2026-02-09| content=A very interesting museum that should not be missed. Excellent demonstration of some fantastic inventions of the ancient Greeks. Most models are functional and can be interacted with. Some can only be interacted with when a docent is leading a tour, so join one as soon as you can. Upstairs is a display of ancient Greek musical instruments—some of them playable, and downstairs is a display of reproductions of ancient Greek armor. It's a relatively small museum, but if you take the time to read everything, it will take several hours.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Historical Museum | alt=Old Parliament | url=http://www.nhmuseum.gr/en | email=info@nhmuseum.gr
| address=Stadiou Street | lat=37.9775 | long=23.732778 | directions=NW of Syntagma Square
| phone=+30 210 3237617 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-Su 08:30-14:30 | price=€3
| wikidata=Q822101
| content=In the old parliament building, this museum contains a large collection of historic documents such as the first constitution of Greece, furniture, equipment from the revolution. If you are lucky you may see the old session room.
}}
* {{see
| name=Numismatic Museum | alt= | url=http://www.nummus.gr/ | email=
| address= | lat=37.9778 | long=23.7354 | directions=north of Syntagma Square
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q658339
| lastedit=2018-12-30
| content=The building of the museum is one of the most beautiful in Athens, and was built by Ernst Ziller and was used as the residence in Athens of Schliemann. The collection contains thousands of ancient coins and ancient Greek, Roman, Byzantine, Medieval figurines.
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Greek Popular Musical Instruments | alt= | url=http://odysseus.culture.gr/h/1/eh151.jsp?obj_id=3403 | email=
| address=1-3 Dioyenous, Plaka | lat=37.97447 | long=23.72751 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q4306254
| lastedit=2020-08-24
| content=Includes exhibits of traditional Greek musical instruments, with recordings of most of them.
}}
*{{see
| name=National War Museum | alt= | url=http://www.warmuseum.gr/en | email=
| address=2 Rizari | lat=37.97539 | long=23.74534 | directions=Not in Kolonaki, but just across the street
| phone=+30 210 729-0543, +30 210-7252974 | tollfree=
| hours=Nov-Mar: 09:00-17:00, Apr-Oct: 09:00-19:00 | price=€4
| wikidata=Q1788831
| lastedit=2016-09-21
| content=The National War Museum is the only significant surviving public project of the military dictatorship which ruled Greece 1967 - 1974. The museum's displays are old fashioned and biased towards the more successful periods of Greek military history. The tanks, artillery guns and aircraft on display outside the museum form the most interesting part of its collection, and can be visited for free. Perhaps the only internationally famous object in the collection is the portrait of Lord Byron in hellenic dress.
}}
* {{see
| name=Park of Maritime Tradition | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Palaio Faliro | lat=37.93369 | long=23.6849 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2015-05-23
| content=Including the historical warships Georgios Averof, Velos and a replica of an ancient trireme.
}}
* {{see
| name=Hellenic Air Force Museum | alt= | url=https://www.haf.gr/en/history/museum/ | email=
| address=Palaio Faliro | lat=38.104917 | long=23.778444 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Hellenic Air Force Museum
| lastedit=2015-05-23
| content=A number of old planes from as far back as the 1930s can be seen here.
| wikidata=Q692428}}
* {{see
| name=City of Athens Technopolis | alt= | url=http://www.technopolis-athens.com/web/guest/home | email=
| address= | lat=37.978139 | long=23.714111 | directions=At Peiraios Avenue &amp; Persefonis Street, next to Kerameikos metro station
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q174552
| lastedit=2017-04-04
| content=An industrial museum of incomparable architecture. The centre has assisted in the upgrading of a historic Athens district.
}}
*{{see
| name=Spathario Museum | alt=Karagiozis Museum | url=http://www.karagiozismuseum.gr/ | email=
| address=Mesogeion &amp; Voriou Ipirou 27 | lat=38.053176 | long=23.812165 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 80 22 360, +30 210 61 27 245 | tollfree=
| hours=M Tu Th F 09:00 - 14:00 | price=Free
| wikidata=Q7574011
| lastedit=2019-04-02
| content=The first and unique museum of shadow theatre in the world, dedicated to the famous Greek shadow theatre character "Karagiozis".
}}
* {{see
| name=Cultural Centre Hellenic Cosmos | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.9626148 | long=23.6887172 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Hellenic Motor Museum | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.991435 | long=23.729910 | directions=near Pedion tou Areos and Victoria Metro Station (Line 1)
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1163632
| lastedit=2019-04-05
| content=
}}
*{{see
| name=OTE Telecommunications Museum | alt= | url=https://www.cosmote.gr/cr2010/cr2010_en/ote-telecommunications-museum.html | email=
| address= | lat=38.088265 | long=23.808076 | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0620 1899, +30 21 0620 1999 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=Free
| lastedit=2019-05-05
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Michael Cacoyannis Foundation cultural center| alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.967475 | long=23.696648 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 3418550 | tollfree=
|fax=| hours= | price=
|wikipedia=|wikidata=|image=|lastedit=2019-05-05| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Planetary Evgenidio Foundation| alt= | url= | email=
| address= 387 Syggrou Ave. (entrance 11 Pentelis st Palaio Faliro, Athens 175 64) | lat=37.9398247 | long=23.6963433 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 9469600
|fax=| hours= | price=
|wikipedia=|wikidata=|image=|lastedit=2019-05-05| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Onassis Cultural centre| alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.9579477 | long=23.7193069 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 9005800
|fax=| hours= | price=
|wikipedia=|wikidata=|image=|lastedit=2019-05-05| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Epigraphical Museum | alt= | url=http://odysseus.culture.gr/h/1/eh151.jsp?obj_id=3348 | email=
| address=1 Tositsa Str | lat=37.988303 | long=23.731321 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 8232950 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q2732854
| lastedit=2019-05-05
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum of Contemporary Art | alt= | url= | email=
| address=| lat=37.9630089 | long=23.7253329 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2019-05-05
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Digital Museum Plato | alt= | url= | email=
| address=| lat=37.9944535 | long=23.7073032 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2019-09-13
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Mineralogy and Petrology | alt= | url= | email=
| address=| lat=37.9666472 | long=23.7843246 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2019-09-13
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Gounaropoulos Museum | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.975 | long=23.761528 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q5588347
| lastedit=2019-09-13
| content=
}}

==Do==
* If you're lucky enough to be in Athens for the '''Easter Weekend''', you'll see the spectacular sight of hundreds of people making their candlelit way down the hill on Holy Saturday night as part of the Easter Vigil procession.
* If the weather is good, head to the '''beaches in south Athens'''. Take buses A2, B2 or E22 from metro station Sygrou, or the tram from Syntagma. Just get off wherever the sea takes your fancy. Beach-side cafes can hit you hard with prices of food and drinks. If you are the only person getting on the bus, you must flag the bus down to get it to stop or it will just fly on by. See the articles on [[Piraeus]], [[Palaio Faliro]] and [[Vari-Voula-Vouliagmeni]] for more details.

===Parks and nature===
[[File:National Gardens.jpg|thumb|250px|National Gardens]]

Several of Athens' hills - '''Lycabettus''' and '''Pnyx''' (see above), {{marker|type=do | name=Philopappos hill | lat=37.9675643 | long=23.7221248 }}, {{marker|type=do | name=Ardettos hill | lat=37.96791 | long=23.73928 }} - are planted with pines and other trees, and are more like small forests than typical urban parks.

*{{do
| name=National Gardens | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.97351 | long=23.7378 | directions=Between the Parliament and Zappeion buildings
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Dawn-Dusk | price=
| wikidata=Q646284
| content=A Peaceful and beautiful park in the centre of Athens, easily the coolest place to hide from the summer sun. Wander around, check out the quirky art that seems to sprout up every now and again, look on in disbelief at the "zoo", sit on one of the benches, enjoy the luxuriant flowers and vegetation, marvel at the turtle and duck ponds, have a frappe in the cafe, and spot one of the resident tortoises exploring... it's a fun place to hang out.
}}
* {{do
| name=Pedion tou Areos | alt=Field of Mars | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.992836 | long=23.736514 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-12-08 |wikipedia=Pedion tou Areos
| content=Covers 27.7 hectares, near the National Archaeological Museum.
| wikidata=Q932606}}
* {{do
| name=Dionysiou Aeropagitou Street | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=37.9698 | long=23.72633 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q15214100
| content=This landmark street starts from the Temple of Olympian Zeus at Vasilissis Olgas Avenue, continues under the southern slopes of the Acropolis near Plaka, and finishes just beyond the Temple of Hephaestus in Thiseio. The street has been pedestrianised, forming a scenic route. The entire route provides visitors with views of the Parthenon and the Agora (the meeting point of ancient Athenians), away from the busy city centre.
}}
* {{do
| name=Parnitha National Park | alt= | url=http://www.parnitha-np.gr/welcome.htm | email=
| address= | lat=38.173333 | long=23.7175 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q25510750
| content=Well-marked paths, gorges, springs, torrents and caves do the protected area. Hiking and mountain-biking in all four mountains remain popular outdoor activities for many residents of the city.
}}
* '''[[Spata#Do|Attica Zoological Park]]''' in nearby [[Spata]].

===Sport===
[[File:Faliro Sport Pavillion.jpg | thumb | 300px | Faliro Sports Pavilion Arena]]
* '''Football:''' The Greek men's national team play home games at Agia Sophia Stadium (capacity 32,500 all seated), aka Opop Arena. Completed in 2022, it's in Nea Filadelpheia 10 km northwest of city centre. The UEFA Europa Conference League final was played there on 29 May 2024.
: Athens has four soccer clubs playing in Super League (Σούπερ Λιγκ), the top tier:
:: '''[https://www.aekfc.gr/ AEK Athens]''' play at Agia Sophia Stadium. 
:: '''[https://www.atromitosfc.gr/ Atromitos]''' play at the 9000-seater Peristeri Stadium 3 km northwest of Syntagma.
:: '''[https://www.olympiacos.org/ Olimpiacos]''' play at the 33,300-seater Karaiskakis Stadium in Neo Faliro, 1 km east of [[Pireaus]] ferry port.
:: '''[https://www.pao.gr/ Panathinaikos]''' play at the 16,000-seater Apostolos Nikolaidis Stadium, 1 km northeast of Syntagma.
: Lower placed clubs are Apollon Smyrnis at Georgios Kamaras Stadium 5 km north of Syntagma, and Ionikos at Neapolis Stadium 10 km west.

* '''Basketball:''' Athens teams playing in the Greek Basketball League, the top tier, are Olympiakos at Peace and Friendship Stadium in Neo Faliro, Panionios and Ionikos at Sofia Befon Palaio Faliro Indoor Hall, Peristeri at Peristeri indoor hall (next to Atromitos) and AEK and Panathinaikos both at Nikos Galis Hall.

===Theatre and performing arts===
Athens is home to 148 theatrical stages, more than any other city in the world.

* {{do
| name=Athens Festival | alt=Athens-Epidaurus Festival | url=http://aefestival.gr/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Athens Festival
| lastedit=2023-01-01
| content=Runs from May to October each year. Offers a wide spectrum of events covering almost every taste. Outside Athens, try to attend a performance at the ancient theater of [[Epidaurus]] – a truly unforgettable experience.
| wikidata=Q3557159}}

In addition to a large number of multiplexes, Athens plays host to a variety of romantic, open air garden cinemas.

The city also supports a vast number of music venues, most notably:
* {{do
| name=Athens Concert Hall | alt=Megaro Mousikis | url=https://www.megaron.gr | email=
| address= | lat=37.98111 | long=23.754164 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q582203
| lastedit=2017-12-08
| content=This venue attracts world-famous artists all year round.
}}

===Cultural activities===
[[File:View towards Acropolis from Stavros Niarchos Cultural Foundation.jpg|thumb|View towards Acropolis from Stavros Niarchos Cultural Foundation]]
* {{do
| name=Stavros Niarchos Cultural Centre | alt=Politismou Idrima Stavros Niarchos | url=https://www.snfcc.org/ | email=
| address= | lat=37.94064 | long=23.69131 | directions=Leof. Andrea Siggrou 364, Kallithea 176 74
| phone=+30 216 8091000 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=06:00-20:00 (gardens open till 22:00 in summer; National Library open 06:00-00:00) | price=Free
| wikipedia=Stavros Niarchos Foundation Cultural Center
| lastedit=2018-01-07
| content=This complex in the seaside suburb of Kallithea has stunning views from its terrace all the way to the Acropolis on one side and of the coast on the other. Evening concerts and other cultural events take place here. The building, gardens and complex alone are worth a visit, and a free shuttle bus is provided from Syntagma Square. Check the web site for the free (optional) tours in English. The collection of the National Library of Greece is being transferred here, and one wing of the building contains an opera house (this part can only be visited as part of a free tour, if you are not attending an event in the auditorium).
| wikidata=Q17511186}}

==Buy==
[[File:Souvenir shop.jpg|thumb|Souvenir shop in Plaka]]
[[File:Plaka District.jpg|thumb|Plaka District]]

Although a huge city, Athens has relatively few shopping malls or large department stores; the small, family run shop still conquers all. Souvenirs are of course available everywhere that tourists go. Other shopping opportunities are antiques, museum reproductions, embroideries and other folk art goods, and Greek food and drink products.

'''Plaka''' is lined with souvenir shops, most of them selling cheap souvenir knick-knacks, though there are a few higher-quality shops. Prices can be high for good quality items.
* '''Flea Market''' could refer to two places. The sign next to Monastiraki station at the beginning of Ifaistou Street claims that you are entering "the Flea Market of Athens." The street is lined with second-hand and surplus shops of every description. Few are of much interest to the visitor, though towards the west end of the street there are some interesting shops selling old books, posters, and Greek and other music recordings. The real Flea Market is held on Sunday mornings in Plateia Avissinia at the western end of Ifaistou Street. There is incredible assortment of used objects, antiques, and junk.
* Among all the souvenir and second-hand stores in the area, '''Martinos''' at 50 Pandrossou ({{phone|+30 210 321-3110}}) stands out as a genuine antique shop, offering top quality items from Greece and the Eastern Mediterranean. Prices are also top of the line, so this is a shop for knowledgeable antique buyers in the market to do some serious spending. Remember that taking antiques out of Greece and into your own country may be subject to the laws of both countries and be sure you're familiar with them before taking anything old home.

'''Kolonaki''' is the upscale, hip, and artistic shopping area. Kolonaki offers the usual range of shops for an upscale neighbourhood; art galleries, hip clothing boutiques, and antique stores are common. The area is small and along with the small streets north of it, including Skoufa, Anagnostopoulou and the pedestrianized Tsakaloff, are ideal for simply wandering around. {{marker|type=buy|name=Plateia Kolonaki|lat=37.97698 | long=23.74084}}(Kolonaki Square) There are also plenty of shops along Patriarchou Ioakim and Haritos streets and their cross streets.

For a more reasonable price tag, try '''Ermou Street''', beside Syntagma Square. Turn right off Ermou at the MAC makeup shop and you'll find yourself on Aghiou Markou and other small streets which have a wide range incredibly cheap shoes, bags, jewellery, gifts and homewares.

'''Street vendors,''' with their wares laid out on blankets on the pavement, can be found in many places where tourists congregate, especially in Plaka and Monastiraki. Their goods are mostly forgeries, cheap knock-offs, and illegal CDs. A surprising number of them sell large collections of coins, most of them fairly modern, which may be of interest to the numismatically inclined, though anything especially antique is likely a reproduction. These vendors are unlicensed, which is in violation of Greek law, and you may notice them vanishing as soon as a policeman is in sight, to reappear the instant the police have gone. They are best ignored. (This warning doesn't apply to vendors of fruit, nuts, etc., from street carts, who are usually legitimate.)

The main supermarket chains are Sklavenitis and Masoutis.  Most Greek supermarkets are closed on Sundays.  If you need to buy groceries on Sunday, you must find one of the rare exceptions which opens for business on Sunday, find a well-equipped convenience store, or simply do without groceries until Monday. 
*{{buy
| name=Laiki | alt=People's market | url= | email=
| address=Divaki Pindou and Ioanni Theologou, and in several other places in Athens neighbourhoods | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
|lastedit=2018-11-14| content=A fruit, vegetable and fish market. Good fun.
}}

===Shopping malls===
* {{buy
| name=The Mall Athens | alt= | url=http://themallathens.gr/ | email=
| address= | lat=38.04453 | long=23.79027 | directions=Neratziotissa station (Metro Line 1 and suburban rail)
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-12-08
| content=The biggest shopping mall in Athens with a large variety of shops, cafés and restaurants and one of the most "hi tech" cinemas in the city.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Golden Hall | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=38.03417 | long=23.79276 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-12-08
| content=A shopping mall at Kifissias avenue in Maroussi. It has shops with luxury brands, luxury cafés, bars, and restaurants.
}}
* {{buy
| name=Athens Metro Mall | alt= | url=https://www.athensmetromall.gr/ | email=
| address=Par. Leof. Vouliagmenis 276, Ag. Dimitrios 173 43 | lat=37.939392 | long=23.739979 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2019-04-03
| content=A shopping mall in Vouliagmenis avenue close to Agios Dimitrios station (Metro Line 2). The food court on the top level offers a nice view of the city and the sea.
}}
* '''Designer Outlet Athens''' and '''Smart Park''' in nearby [[Spata]].

==Eat==
[[File:Plaka Restaurants.JPG|thumb|right|Traditional restaurants (sing.: taverna, pl.: tavernes) in the side streets of the Plaka district]]
The districts ''Kolonaki'' and ''Plaka'' are especially good areas for dining out.

===Fast food===
For a quick, decent and low-budget meal, try a '''souvlaki''' (σουβλάκι, ''soo-VLAH-kee''), meat (usually pork or chicken) grilled on a skewer. They are typically served with tomato, onion and '''tzatziki''' (τζατζίκι, ''tzah-TZEE-khee''), yogurt enriched with garlic and cucumber, wrapped inside a '''pita''' (πίτα, ''PEE-tah''), a thin pan bread. Prices of souvlaki vary according to the confidence and/or nerve of the cornershop owner, but usually cost from €1.70 to €3, and another €5 for drink, salad and French fries for a total no more than €7. Take away is cheaper than if you sit at a table. You can get souvlaki just about everywhere, especially in tourist areas.
* At the end of Mitropoleos, just around the corner from the Monastiraki Metro station, is a trio of famous souvlaki shops &amp;mdash; '''Thanasis''', '''Savvas''' and '''Bairaktaris''' (Μπαϊρακτάρης) &amp;mdash; which are, depending on who you ask, the Zeus or the Hades of souvlaki lovers. At any of the three, if you take a seat and ask for a souvlaki, you'll be served a plate with meat, pita and chips for around €9. But, if you ask cashier for a ''pita-souvlaki'', you'll get the same stuff in a sandwich to take away for around €1.70.
*{{eat
| name=Σουβλάκι Κώστας 1950 συνταγμα (Kostas) | alt= | url= | email=
| address=5 Pentelis | lat=37.9749191 | long=23.7319332 | directions=take Metropolis from Syntagma Square, turn left on Pentelis
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=It's authentic, friendly and fast.
}}
*{{eat
| name=The 2 Brothers | alt=Τα δύο αδέλφια | url= | email=
| address=Leof. Stratarchou Alexandrou Papagou 81 | lat=37.9780537 | long=23.7697173 | directions=around Alexandri Square (Gardenia)
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=A giro will cost around €2
 | lastedit=
| content=The best souvlaki in this part of Athens.
}}

If you're interested in a sandwich, cheese pie, spinach pie or the equivalent of a fast snack, try '''Grigoris (Γρηγόρης)''' or '''Everest''', two chains of fast food in most districts of Athens and the rest of Greece. '''Goody's''' is the Greek equivalent of McDonald's and offers a fair variety of tasty meals, including pasta, different salads, burgers etc. McDonald's is the same like everywhere, but here it has a slight Greek slant.

===Budget===

Adrianou, which runs along the north side of the Acropolis from Thissio in the west to Plaka in the east, is packed with tavernas. Many are touristy and a little on the pricy side, so try to pick one that also has locals as customers. Expect to pay a little extra at any place that has views of the Acropolis.

There are several budget-friendly restaurants in the centre.
* {{eat
| name=Vegan Beat Athens | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Perikleous 56 | lat=37.9767757  | long=23.7297995 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=Vegan street food restaurant. Tasty food and nice people that work there. A good place for all vegans and even non-vegans. The true Parthenon of the vegan scene of Athens. Excellent vegan souvlaki.
}}
* {{eat
| name=The Traditional | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Kolokotroni 59 | lat=37.9777446 | long=23.7288011 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Traditional Greek food. If you want to eat in a quality village tavern in the center of Athens, you will come here. Great roasted food, salads and appetizers! The food is handmade.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Krasopoulio tou Kokkora | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Esopou 4 | lat= 37.9776907| long=23.7241521 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Among the best traditional Greek restaurants in Athens downtown. The owner is smiling, polite and very keen to assist. A wonderful casual lunch or dinner spot. Fresh ingredients and substantial portions.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Aspro Alogo | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Apollonos | lat=37.9747521 | long=23.7312560 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=An excellent little Greek restaurant well worth finding. Everything is fresh and delicious and the service is great. The owner is a helpful and generous guy. Attentive and familiar treatment.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Atlantikos | alt= | url= | email=
| address= Greece, Avliton 7| lat=37.9774240 | long=23.7229415 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Nice little place with great seafood selection. The meals look simple and are delicious. The portions are quite large and the quality price ratio is very well balanced. One should go in time and expect quite some waiting time to get a table on a small alley. Best local fish tavern with crunchy anchovies and perfect frying without being oily.
}}
* {{eat
| name= Kafeneio Ivis | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Ivis 10 | lat=37.9775546 | long=23.7226786 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Very authentic Greek tavern, frequented by locals. Great value for money. Warm welcome, nice terrace and fast service.
}}

===Mid-range===

*{{eat
| name=Lefka | url=https://www.facebook.com/pages/category/Greek-Restaurant/%CE%A4%CE%B1%CE%B2%CE%AD%CF%81%CE%BD%CE%B1-%CE%97-%CE%9B%CE%B5%CF%8D%CE%BA%CE%B1-1708448126101278/ | email=
| address=Mavromiháli 121 | lat=37.9868921 | long=23.7421405 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 36 14 038 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=A long-established traditional taverna with spacious outdoor seating. Closed Sundays.
}}
* {{eat
| name=K Filippou | alt= | url=https://www.filippou.gr/en/ | email=
| address=19 Xenokratous | lat=37.9791029 | long=23.7444796 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 72 16 390 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=A long-established taverna serving some of the best and most authentic food in Athens. Seating is indoors and outdoors, though it's hard to find a seat in the latter during pleasant weather.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Karamanlidika | alt= | url=https://www.karamanlidika.gr/ | email=
| address=Ermou 119 | lat=37.9770462 | long=23.7228509 | directions=near Greek Agora
| phone=+30 210 32 19 119 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2024-08-29
| content=A very remarkable, slightly upscale restaurant specializing in dishes native to the [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karamanlides Karamanli people]. Owing to their history, the food served here is a (very well-executed) mix between Greek and Turkish cuisine. A hidden gem (that is rather crowded, though)! Expect to pay 11€ per person for main courses and water.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Karavitis | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Pafsaniou 4 | lat=37.9714946 | long=23.7436133 | directions=near Pafsaníou
| phone=+30 210 75 15 155 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=a severely traditional taverna where the speciality is stamnaki, or beef, potatoes and cheese cooked in tomato sauce in an individual clay pot. The fried zucchini here are also always good. Mostly patronized by Greeks, but there is an English-language menu.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Το Κιούπι (To Kioupi) | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Acharnon 255 | lat=38.0076697 | long=23.7295943 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 36 14 033 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=Known among some expatriates as "the hole in the ground," this is a basement taverna serving authentic, inexpensive traditional Greek fare.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Platanos Taverna | alt= | url=http://eleinitsa.wixsite.com/platanos | email=
| address=4 Dioyenous | lat=37.9743207 | long=23.7276950 | directions=Plaka
| phone=+30 210 322 1065 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia= | wikidata=
| lastedit=2022-09-01
| content=One of the oldest tavernas in Plaka with a pleasant outdoor terrace under a huge plane tree, though some old Athens hands have complained that the food has become lacklustre.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Zeus Xenios | alt=pronounced and sometimes spelled ''Zefs'' in modern Greek | url=http://xenioszeus.business.site/ | email=
| address=Mnisikleous 37 | lat=37.9729390 | long=23.7277745 | directions=at the very top of Mnesikleous Street
| phone=+30 21 0324 9514 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia= | wikidata=
| lastedit=2022-09-01
| content=literally in the shadow of the Acropolis, offers quieter and less expensive dining than the many touristy tavernas lining Mnesikleous whose touts will try to snare you as you walk up the hill. The view isn't as spectacular as you might expect, but the outdoor seating is very pleasant and the traditional Greek dishes include some unusual ones, like grilled peppers in yogurt sauce. The price includes a bottle of water, an appetizer plate and garlic bread.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Pame Psirri | alt=Πάμε Ψυρρή | url=https://www.pamepsirri.gr/portal/ | email=
| address=Katsikogianni 5 | lat=37.9791381 | long= 23.7243386 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 3246098 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2022-09-01
| content=On Agii Anargiri square -- Psiri. A "mezedopolio" where local singers sing rempetika music.
}}
*{{eat
| name=O Morias | alt=Ταβέρνα Ο ΜΩΡΙΑΣ | url= | email=
| address=Eirinis 56, Ag. Paraskevi 153 41 | lat=38.0084138 | long=23.8193609 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=Greek restaurant
}}
*{{eat
| name=Voskopoula (The Shepherdess) | alt=Βοσκοπούλα | url=https://www.voskopoula.com/ | email=
| address=sivoron 87, 111 42 | lat=38.0260094 | long=23.7481295 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=Greek restaurant
}}
*{{eat
| name=Τaverna Μanolis. | url=http://www.taverna-manolis.gr/#/ | email=
| address=Samou 1 Chalandri | lat=38.0305556 | long=23.8063889 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 6824342 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=Greek restaurant taverna.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Rosalia | alt= | url=http://www.rozalia.gr/?language=en | email=
| address=Valtetsiou 58 | lat= | long= | directions=Exarxeia
| phone=+30 210 3302933 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=A tavern that serves simple, traditional Greek meals.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Giántes | alt= | url=https://www.facebook.com/yiantes/ | email=
| address=Valtetsiou 44 | lat= | long= | directions=Exarxeia
| phone=+30 210 3301369 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=A tavern with a garden serving organic dishes.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Kostarelos Cheese and Dairy | alt= | url=https://www.kostarelos.gr/en/home/ | email=
| address=46 Pentelis Avenue | lat=38.0377372 | long=23.8253713| directions=
| phone=+30 210 8104470 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price= 
 | lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Orea Penteli | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=On Psiri square
| phone=+30 2103218627 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Another "mezedopolio" with live music in an old restored building.
}}

===Splurge===
* {{eat
| name=Cafe Avissinia | alt= | url=https://cafeavissinia.net | email=cafeavisinia@gmail.com
| address=Kinetou 7 | lat=37.9766922  | long=23.7236566 | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0321 7047 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
|lastedit=2023-01-25| content=A remarkable restaurant, serving refined and creative innovations on traditional Greek dishes in a chic setting. It is on the square of the same name which is the venue of the main Athens flea market. This is an interesting place to come for lunch, where you can sit enjoying the upscale food and ambiance while looking out on the gritty bazaar of the Flea Market. Moderately expensive, and unfortunately no open wine, though they do have a short but well-chosen list of Greek bottled wines. Open for lunch and dinner. Those considering walking there for dinner from Plaka or the Monastiraki Metro should be aware that the intervening area, while fine by day and not known to be particularly dangerous even at night, it does take on an uncomfortable "Bladerunner" atmosphere after dark.
}}

===Kosher dining===
Athens has only one kosher restaurant, Gostijo, a Sephardi restaurant in Psiri.

==Drink==
[[File:Dacapo Athens.jpg|thumb|Cafe in Kolonaki district]]
Greeks love to socialize, and Athens buzzes long after its other European counterparts have laid their heads down to sleep. 20:00 is the earliest most Greeks will consider going to eat out, and clubbers start to get ready at about midnight. Many Athens clubs relocate to the beach during the summer months. Cafes spill onto the streets and the sound of lively conversation is everywhere in the evenings.

Go to the '''Psyrrí''' area (Monastiraki or Thissio station, Lines 1 and 3 and Line 1 respectively) for a number of smart bars and small clubs. It is the area immediately north of Ermou street between these two metro stops.

There are more and better bars in the area north of Ermou street between Monastiraki and Syntagma than there used to be. Aiolou and Kolokotroni streets offer a fair variety of cafés and bars. '''Magazé''', '''six dogs''', '''Booze''' and all the bars on Karytsi square (a small square at the end of Christou Lada street, behind Klafthmonos square on Stadiou avenue) can get very busy on Fridays and Saturdays, with visitors having their drinks even on the streets outside from spring through autumn, when the weather is nice.

The area around the Kerameikos station, called '''Gazi''' (Γκάζι, ''gas'') has been the gay village of Athens for quite a few years. Since the opening of the metro station, in 2007, the neighbourhood has attracted all kinds of crowds. This is a home to dozens of bars, cafés and clubs, gay or not, and to small theatrical scenes, the latter one especially to the northeast of the area, towards Metaxourgeio.
* {{drink
| name=Balux | url=http://www.baluxcafe.com/ | email=
| address=Vassileos Georgiou B No. 58 Asteria, Glyfada | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=One of the best bars in Athens for the specific style, to call it a bar is an understatement. Balux is large complex set right on the water in Glyfada, one of the trendiest areas of the city. It is open during the summer for swimming in the ocean or pool all day and turns into a lounge and full club at night. Where Athens' wealthy go to party.
}}
The '''Plateia Exarcheia''' square and nearby streets like '''Solomou''' have lots of clubs and bars.
*{{drink
| name=Taximi | url= | email=
| address=Cnr. Harilaou Trikoupi and Isavron | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210-363-9919 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
*{{drink
| name=Rebetiki Istoria | alt= | url= | email=
| address=181 Ippokratous | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 2587455 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| content=One of the best rebetica clubs, often open in summer when most others are closed.
}}
'''Kolonaki Square''' (''Plateia Kolonaki;'' its official name is ''Plateia Filikis Etaireias,'' but no one ever uses it) is bordered with cafes whose customers tend to be mature Athenian movers and shakers for whom the area is the traditional in-town home. Most of these cafes serve desserts, light meals and drinks, and most of them are expensive. They tend to be liveliest late at night. One of the best established, and most prestigious, is '''Lykovrisi.''' Not many foreigners visit these cafes, but the visitor may find they make for interesting people-watching.
*{{drink
| name=Showroom | url=http://www.showroom.gr | email=
| address=Milioni 2 &amp; Irakleitou | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€5 for a beer
| content=Nice cafe/restaurant.
}}
* '''Oréa Ellás''' ("Beautiful Greece") with two entrances 59 Mitropóleos and 36 Pandhróssou, Monastiráki (but just a minute's walk from Plaka; the cafe is upstairs) is a combination cafe and gift shop. The cafe, open all day but not after 18:00, offers coffees and alcoholic drinks and a limited range of snacks and sweets, in a wonderful old fashioned setting with stunning views of the Acropolis out the windows. The shop, called Kendro Ellinikis Paradosis (Centre of Greek Tradition) is an excellent place to buy souvenirs, which are more expensive but vastly better than the knick-knacks offered by the cheek-by-jowl tourist shops lining the street outside.
* {{drink
| name=Ydria | url=http://www.ydria.gr | email=
| address=68 Adhrianoú | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30-210-3251619 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content= This sprawling cafe-restaurant that takes up a large part of Platía Paliás Agorás along Adhrianoú St. at the western end of Plaka, is a good place for daytime coffee or a before or after dinner drink. They also serve food, though if you're there for a meal you'll be directed to a different seating area, so tell the waiter when you arrive if you just want a drink. This is the most pleasant cafe in a square packed with them; despite the Plaka location it's relatively quiet, with snatches of views of antiquity from the mostly outdoor seating. Particularly popular with younger Greeks, though all ages and nationalities will feel comfortable. Prices average or slightly below for Plaka, which still means not cheap, though the ouzo comes in hefty shots, and if you order the giant "ouzo platter" (€25) of appetizers with them, it will easily suffice for three people.
}}
* '''Vrettos''' at 41 Kydathineon, Plaka is a very atmospheric 100 year old distillery which makes its own ouzo, brandy and liqueurs, and sets up a bar at night where you can order them by the glass. They also offer wine tastings selected from 100s of Greek wines between 10:00-16:00.
*{{drink
| name=Costa | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€3-€4 for a coffee
| content=Standard stuff, but has a nice air conditioned and quiet upstairs seating area overlooking the square.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Metamatic_taf | alt=Taf | url=http://www.theartfoundation.gr | email=home@metamatictaf.gr
| address=Normanou 5, Monastiraki | lat=37.97657 | long=23.72442 | directions=close to Monastiraki Square and metro station in Normanou street
| phone=+30 21 0323 8757 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=10:00-04:00 | price=
| wikipedia=el:Metamatic:taf#
| lastedit=2017-04-11
| content=Independent space organising and hosting cultural events related to all forms of artistic production, and a point of social gathering. Great cocktails and a variety of jazz/soul music.
}}

===Cafes===
Have a '''frappé''', the delicious Greek version of cold coffee. It is nothing like the frappé you find in other countries. Served sweet, medium, or without sugar, with or without milk. Delicious with Bailey's too.

*{{drink
| name=Playce | url=http://www.playce.gr | email=
| address=Str. Papagou 128 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=A really nice cafe where you can play board games whilst drinking your coffee. Very popular.
}}
*{{drink
| name=Filion Cafe | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Start the day with a double shot of dark espresso at this cafe in the Kolonaki neighbourhood, just north of Syntagma Square.
}}

===Clubbing and nightlife===
Athens is famous for its vibrant nightlife. The Athenians like to party and will do so almost every night of the week. The choices are plenty and they appeal to all tastes and lifestyles. In general, things get started pretty late: after midnight for bars and clubbing and after 22:00 for dinner at the city's tavernas, Athens Restaurants and bar-restaurants.

Hip areas include '''Gazi, Psirri, Metaxourgio, Exarcheia, Monastiraki, Theseion and Kolonaki'''. Traditional Greek evenings can be spent in '''Plaka'''.

Many of Athens' hottest clubs and bars are in '''Psirri'''. '''Gazi''' has changed tremendously. Most of the galleries, mainstream bars, restaurants, clubs and Greek nightclubs here (featuring live Greek pop singers) are trademarked by their industrial design, as many of them are housed in remodelled—and once abandoned—factories. Gazi is one of the trendiest areas of Athens nightlife. You can get there by metro line 3 at Kerameikos station.

'''Plaka - Monastiraki''' are two ancient, historic and all-time classic Athenian neighbourhoods popular with visitors, they do not have many big dance clubs and bars, but offer lively, traditional places to enjoy Greek culture year-round, and several rock and jazz clubs.

You will find plenty nightclubs with live Greek music along '''Syggrou Avenue''' and at the industrial strips of '''Iera Odos''' and '''Pireos Street''' in Gazi. In the summer months, the action moves to '''Poseidon Avenue''' and the coastal towns of '''Glyfada''', '''Voula and Vouliagmeni'''. '''Kolonaki''' is a staple dining and entertainment destination, catering to the city's urban working professionals who enjoy an after work cocktail at many of its bars that are open - and busy - until after midnight, even on weekdays. The clubs here are also very chic. '''Exarchia''' is where to go for smaller more bohemian style haunts that cater to artists and college students. At the foot of Strefi Hill is where you will find most of the bars and clubs, many of which play rock music. An alternative option of Athens nightlife.

A 'club zone' is in the coastal district, running to the east- if you go there and you are lucky, you can actually get to listen to non-Greek music. There are also many clubs and pubs in the center of Athens.

==Sleep==
Athens has a wide variety of accommodation options, from camping and hostels, right up to 5 star luxury hotels.

For most tourists, the primary question is Plaka or not Plaka.  For the latter, the next question is whether to stay just outside of Plaka, or along one of the main routes going to the coast (e.g., Leoforos Andrea Siggrou is home to the Grand Hyatt, Marriott, and InterContinental hotels), or in one of the coastal suburbs like Glyfada or Piraeus.  These latter options may allow for staying in more modern hotels or with a scenic coastal view, but then one has to travel to Plaka and back for sightseeing.

For hotels near the airport, see listings in [[Spata]] and [[Rafina]].

===Camping===
* {{sleep
| name=Dionissotis Camping | alt= | url=http://www.campingdionissotis.gr | email=dionissiotis@hol.gr
| address= | lat=38.1051 | long=23.8134 | directions=on the road that leads to Varibobi/Tatoi (Parnitha)
| phone=+30 210 8001496, +30 6977-261615 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 8001512
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€6 per person, €4 per small tent, €6 per large tent/caravan
| lastedit=2015-06-01
| content=It has a hall for breakfast, a minimarket, a swimming pool and a playground for the children. 115 places for tents.
}}

===Budget===
* {{sleep
| name=Athens Backpackers | alt= | url=http://www.backpackers.gr/ | email=info@backpackers.gr
| address=12 Makri Street - Makryanni, Athens | lat=37.96861 | long=23.73051 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 32 25 891 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Standard backpacking hostel offering clean and comfortable beds, 24 hr reception access, and discounted wifi access. Great spot to meet other travellers.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Athens Psiri Hotel|alt= | url=https://www.athenspsirihotel.com/en/| email=info@athenspsirihotel.com
| address=32 Sofokleous street | lat=37.981290|long=23.726320 | directions=next to Monastiraki metro and Plaka
| phone=+30 2105234329 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin=13:30 | checkout= | price=€35
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2021-04-17
| content=Fully renovated in 2020. All rooms include private bathrooms, free wifi, air conditioning and heating.
}}
*{{sleep
| name=Safestay Athens Monastiraki |alt=formerly Athenstyle| url=https://www.safestay.com/venue/safestay-athens-monastiraki/ | email=safestayathens@safestay.com
| address=Ag. Theklas 10 Monastiraki | lat= | long= | directions=2 mins from Monastiraki metro station
| phone=+30 2103225010 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€15-50
| checkin= | checkout=
|lastedit=2026-02-28| content=Studios and hostel beds within walking distance of the metro. Each dorm has lockers. Artists have painted murals in the reception and some of the rooms, and there's a basement lounge with art exhibitions, pool table, home cimena and internet corner. The small rooftop bar is ideal for evening drinks. It produces a weekly art and culture guide. Yellow and green building.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Dioskouros Athens | alt= | url=https://www.dioskouroshostel.com/ | email=hoteldioskouros@gmail.com
| address=6 Pittakou Street, Plaka, Athens | lat=37.97128 | long=23.73237 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 3248 165 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 3233359
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€15-20 per person in high season
| content=Offers simple clean accommodation in a central location.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Tony Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.hoteltony.gr | email=tony@hoteltony.gr
| address=26 Zaharitsa Str., Koukaki | lat=37.9653650 | long=23.7233088 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 9235761 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hostel Aprodite | alt=Aphrodite | url=http://www.hostelaphrodite.com | email=info@hostelaphrodite.com
| address=12 Einardou and Michail Voda corner 65, Athena 10440, Greece | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210-8810589 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=€12 for a 6 bed dorm, €14 for a 4 bed dorm, and more. Air conditioning €3 extra per person
| checkin= | checkout=
| content=Low-budget backpackers' hangout not too far from Larissa train station and Victoria Square, a bit north of the Omonia district.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Orion | alt= | url=http://www.orion-dryades.com/ | email=
| address=105 Emm. Benaki &amp; Anexsartisias str | lat=37.98736 | long=23.73802 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 33 02 387-8 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 38 28 575
| checkin= | checkout= | price=from €28 double
| content=This small hotel is next to Strefi hill, offers nice view from its terrace and is in a calm area. Freshly renovated rooms and breakfast in communal kitchen. Internet included and sister hotel offers nice breakfast at the terrace, too.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Elite Athens | alt= | url= | email=
| address=23 Pireos str Athens | lat=37.98271 | long=23.72528 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 32 25 891 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=10 minutes walk from Monastiraki; simple, decorated rooms with air conditioning and TV. There is also a bar and coffee shop on the ground floor.
}}

=== Mid-range===
* {{sleep
| name=Acropolis View Hotel Athens | alt= | url=https://www.acropolisviewhotel.gr/en/home | email=
| address=Webster street 10, Athens | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 32 25 891 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Attention to detail is catered for in this hotel, with most rooms having a fresh lick of paint on them every year. Rooms have central heating and A/C, private baths and mini fridges, and some have balconies. Price from €88 for a single room in high season.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Acropolis House | alt= | url=http://www.acropolishouse.gr | email=htlacrhs@otenet.gr
| address=6-8 Kodrou, Plaka | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 3226241, +30 210 3222344-45 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 3244143
| price=bathroom ensuite is €87 (includes breakfast) | checkin= | checkout=
| content=The staff are very friendly and the hotel will hold your luggage if you are departing later in the day. Some of the older, more expensive rooms are very atmospheric; others are rather drab.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Athos | alt= | url=http://www.athoshotel.gr/english/profile.htm | email=
| address= | lat=37.97489 | long=23.73073 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 3221977-9 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Patrou 3. Nice hotel in Plaka with roof-garden with a view of the Acropolis.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Central Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.centralhotel.gr/ | email=
| address=Apollonas St 21 | lat=37.97462 | long=23.73103 | directions=Plaka
| phone=+30 210 32 25 891 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Designed by architect Stelios Demos, this hotel fuses modern art design with a classical Greek touch. Restaurant, daily buffet breakfast. Priced from €128 for a standard room in the high season.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=O&amp;B Athens Boutique Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.oandbhotel.com | email=
| address= | lat=37.97756 | long=23.72194 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=A small boutique hotel in the center of Athens, close to sightseeing, shopping, and entertainment.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Omiros Athens | alt= | url=http://www.omiros-hotel.com/ | email=
| address=15 Apollonos Str, Athens | lat=37.97466 | long=23.73171 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 32 25 891 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Each of the 40 rooms features air conditioning, a television and a mini fridge.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Fresh Hotel | alt= | url=https://freshhotel.gr/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=A superb designer hotel within easy walking distance of the Acropolis in the centre of Athens. The rooftop bar and swimming pool has breathtaking views of the Acropolis - the perfect way to end the day's sightseeing or business.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Periscope Hotel | alt= | url=http://periscope.athenshotels.it/ | email=
| address=22 Charitos Street | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=An upscale (with prices to match) hip boutique hotel in Kolonaki with glossy, minimalist decor. This hotel used to be the Athenian Inn, and that name may still be found in some Athens hotel listings in guidebooks, but the former hotel has been so completely refurbished that it is now a totally different establishment.
}}
* {{Sleep|name=Mirabello|url=https://www.athens-mirabello.gr/|email=info@athens-mirabello.gr|address=Geraniou 49|phone=+30 210 52 23 657|lastedit=2022-07-26}}

===Splurge===
* {{sleep
| name=Radisson Blu Park Hotel | alt= | url=https://www.radissonblu.com/en/hotel-athens?facilitatorId=CSOSEO&amp;csref=org_gmb_sk_en_sn_ho_ATHZH | email=
| address=10 Alexandras Ave, Athens 10682 | lat=37.99126 | long=23.73330 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 8894500 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=5 star hotel offering high speed internet access and express mail, late check out and foreign currency exchange.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=The St George Lycabettus Hotel Athens | alt= | url=http://www.sglycabettus.gr/ | email=info@sglycabettus.gr
| address=2 Kleomenous Street, 106 75 | lat=37.97942 | long=23.74248 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 7290711 19 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 7290439
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Located in Kolonaki. This boutique hotel offers great views of the Acropolis.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Conrad Athens the Ilisian | alt=Hilton Athens | url=https://www.hilton.com/en/hotels/athgrci-conrad-athens-the-ilisian/ | email=info@conradathens.com
| address=Leoforos Vasilissis Sofias 46 | lat=37.97609 | long=23.75058 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 728 1000 | tollfree=
| checkin=16:00 | checkout=12:00 | price=
| wikipedia=Hilton Athens | wikidata=Q18918653
| lastedit=2021-01-27
| content=Just south of the Kolonaki district, this is the biggest hotel with the biggest pool in Athens. Fifteen floors and wonderful views everywhere you look. Also the "Milos Restaurant" is on site.
}}
*{{sleep
| name=President Hotel Athens | alt= | url=http://www.president.gr | email=
| address=43 Kifissias Avenue, 11523, Athens | lat=37.98928 | long=23.76369 | directions=Nearest metro station is Ambelokipoi, which is on Alexandras avenue. 5 min walk from Alexandras avenue is Kifissias avenue, and the hotel is 5 min walk from that junction.
| phone=+30 2106989000 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin=12:00 | checkout=12:00 | price=~€80 per night for a double bed room
| content=A 4-star hotel renovated in 2004 with a lovely terrace bar and pool, 3 restaurants with view of the Lycabetus hill, and very accommodating personnel. The hotel is in an ideal location for catching the bus or the metro for the north suburbs of Athens (Kifisia, Marousi, Chalandri etc). Acropolis, Lycabetus hill, Syntagma square are all within 5 to 15 min taxi drive.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Royal Olympic Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.royalolympic.com/ | email=
| address=28-34 Diakou Athanasiou | lat=37.96783 | long=23.73233 | directions=
| phone=+30 210-928-8400 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=In front of the Temple of Zeus. Outdoor swimming pool, rooftop garden restaurant. Free wi fi and conference room available.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Electra Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.electrahotels.gr | email=
| address=5, Ermou str. Syntagma Square | lat=37.97561 | long=23.73303 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 33-78-000 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=A 4-star property in the heart of Athens. Within walking distance from all major historical sites and the business and commercial districts.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Grande Bretagne Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.grandebretagne.gr/ | email=
| address=1 Vasileos Georgiou A' str | lat=37.97651 | long=23.73549 | directions=North edge of Syntagma square
| phone=+30 210 3330000 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=Prices from €300
| wikidata=Q1630906
| content=Traditionally the "best hotel in town," this historic luxury hotel with gilded woods, fine fabrics and chandeliers in the public areas has long been the accommodation of choice for visiting diplomats and power players.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=King George Palace | alt= | url=http://www.classicalhotels.com/?siteid=2 | email=
| address=3 Vassileos Georgiou A' St, Syntagma Square | lat=37.97643 | long=23.73496 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 32-22-210 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Some rooms have a view of the Acropolis, and the Royal Presidential Suite has a private outdoor pool. The Tudor restaurant on the 7th floor has views of the Acropolis.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hellenic Vibes | alt= | url=https://www.hellenicvibes.gr | email=info@hellenicvibes.gr
| address=Agias Irinis 7, Athens 105 51| lat=37.9770090323007 | long=23.727248284533765 | directions=straight down the road
| phone=+30 210 32 40 504 | tollfree= | fax=
| price= €150 | checkin= | checkout=
| content=Hellenic Vibes Smart Hotel is a brand new 5-star hotel right in the heart of rebranded Athens, with a capacity of 35 rooms and exclusive suites, is located behind the doors of an impressive neoclassical facade of the 19th century.
|lastedit=2022-11-04}}

== Connect ==
As of February 2026, Athens has 5G from Cosmote, Vodafone and Nova. Wi-fi is widely available in public places.

==Stay safe==
{{cautionbox|
'''Visitors should always carry their passport or identity documents, especially if they may be perceived as an African, Middle Eastern or another darker-complexion ethnicity.''' Such persons should be especially wary when encountering police and, if detained, demand to speak to their consulate immediately (a right all persons have under international law).|lastedit=2025-09-02}}
Athens is '''generally a safe city'''. There are many police officers and security guards around the city. Many places have CCTV. Street crime is rare. Violent crime against tourists is rare.

There are '''pickpockets''' on the Metro (especially at the interchanges with the line from the Airport), buses and in other crowded areas, including Plaka. You will notice that natives travel with their hands on their bags and pockets, and keep their bag in front rather than on their side or back, which unfortunately is not without reason.  If any pocket, purse, or backpack is visible as you travel on the Metro, assume it will be targeted by pickpockets.  Assume that any stranger on the Metro (no matter how well-dressed) is a potential pickpocket and take appropriate precautions.  Beware of dense crowds at Metro vehicle doors, especially when a door seems to be broken or jammed. 

The '''friendly stranger''' [[Greece#Scams|bar scam]] has been reported from areas of central Athens frequented by tourists, including Omonia, Syntagma, and Plaka. There have been some reports of fraud. Usually, someone will stop you and ask for directions. A couple of other men then arrive claiming to be police, showing a badge (obviously a fake one). They ask if you were getting drugs from the other man and then ask for your passport and wallet for verification. While you are busy trying to convince them that your passport is valid, one of them sneaks out some money from your wallet.

[[File:Patission Avenue.JPG|thumb|Patission Avenue, one of the busiest streets in Athens]]

'''Demonstrations and riots''' are common and accepted as part of everyday life and democracy by most Athenians. (You shouldn't expect any less from the cradle of democracy!) Keep abreast of [https://www.ekathimerini.com/tag/protest/ news of demonstrations], and avoid them if you don't want to risk being arrested or tear-gassed, which often happens near Syntagma. Anarchist groups often clash with police, or target government buildings or perceived representations of capitalism during the night, mainly in Exarcheia ({{Lang|el|Εξάρχεια}}). It is unlikely that tourists would be harmed, as the anarchists usually take care to attack only property and police as opposed to civilians. However, parking in Exarcheia overnight could result in damage to your car. Anti-Israel pro-Palestine activities (such as graffiti) are common seen on the streets.

The '''football rivalry''' between local club Panathinaikos and Piraeus-based Olympiacos is notoriously intense, and has on occasion resulted in violent confrontations between opposing fans. To be safe, avoid wearing Olympiacos shirts while you are in Athens, especially during matchday, or it could result in you being harassed or even singled out for violence by opposing fans.

In the summer, the weather is very '''hot'''. [[Hot weather|Remember to drink enough water and apply sunscreen to your skin.]]

Athens has '''poor urban planning''', especially poor road planning.  When walking around, the greatest danger is on streets where sidewalks/pavements are nonexistent or too narrow for pedestrians to pass each other.  If a car or motorcycle comes around the corner too fast at that very second, someone may get run over. 

'''In case of emergency, dial 112'''. This is the pan-European emergency number that connects to police, ambulance, and fire services free of charge. 

===Rough areas===
Athenians hold negative perceptions of the areas around '''Omonia Square'''.  Locals advise you to avoid these areas late at night. The area is notorious for pickpockets and prostitutes, and there are many people who use drugs in the open, even during the day. Other places to avoid are Vathi square and the area between Agiou Konstantinou and Karolou/Marni. 

The Philopappou Hill area should be avoided at night. The back streets of [[Piraeus]] are probably also places where it's unwise to wander around late at night.

==Cope==
===Embassies and representative offices===
* {{flag|Armenia}} {{listing
| name=Armenia | url=http://greece.mfa.am/en/ | email=embassy.athens@mfa.am
| address=95 Konstantinou Paleologou Ave, Khalandri | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2106831130 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2106831183
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Australia}} {{listing
| name=Australia |alt=| url=https://greece.embassy.gov.au/athn/home.html | email=ae.athens@dfat.gov.au
| address=Level 6, Thon Building, Kifissias &amp; Alexandras Ave | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2108704000 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2108704111
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|Austria}} {{listing
| name=Austria | url= | email=athen-ob@bmei.gv.at
| address=Vass. Sofias Avenue 4 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107257270 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107257292
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Brazil}} {{listing
| name=Brazil | alt= | url=http://atenas.itamaraty.gov.br/en-us/ | email=embragre@embratenas.gr
| address=Platia Filikis Eterias 14 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107213039, +30 2107234450 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107244731
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Bulgaria}} {{listing
| name=Bulgaria | url= | email=embassbg@otenet.gr
| address=Stratigou Kallari 33A, Psychiko | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2106748106, +30 2106748107, +30 2106748108 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2106748130
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Canada}} {{listing
| name=Canada |alt=| url=https://www.international.gc.ca/country-pays/greece-grece/athens-athenes.aspx?lang=eng | email=athns@international.gc.ca
| address=Ioannou Gennadiou 4 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107273400 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107273480
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|China}} {{listing
| name=China | url=http://gr.china-embassy.org/eng/ | email=chinaemb_gr@mfa.gov.cn
| address=Dimokratias 10-12, Psychiko | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2106783840 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2106723819
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Colombia}} {{listing
| name=Colombia | url=https://colombianconsulate.gr/ | email=info@colombianconsulate.gr
| address=Kyprou 40 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 623 1453 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 623 1877
| hours= | price=
| content=(Consulate).
|alt=|wikidata=|wikipedia=|image=|lastedit=2017-04-22}}
* {{flag|Croatia}} {{listing
| name=Croatia | url= | email=croemb.athens@mvpei.hr
| address=Tzavela 4, Psychiko | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2106777033, +30 2106777037, +30 2106777049 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2106711208
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Cyprus}} {{listing
| name=Cyprus | url=http://www.mfa.gov.cy/mfa/Embassies/Embassy_Athens.nsf/DMLhouse_gr/DMLhouse_gr?OpenDocument | email=cyempkl@hol.gr
| address=2A Xenofontos Avenue | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2103734800 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107258886
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Denmark}} {{listing
| name=Denmark | url=http://graekenland.um.dk/ | email=athamb@um.dk
| address=Mourouzi 10 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107256440 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107256473
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Egypt}} {{listing
| name=Egypt |alt=| url=https://www.egyptembassy.org/location/greece/egypt-embassy-athens/ | email=embassyegypt@yahoo.com
| address=3, Vassilli Sophias Avenue | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2103618612 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2103603538
| hours=08:30-16:00 | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|Estonia}} {{listing
| name=Estonia | alt= | url=https://athens.mfa.ee/ | email=embassy.athens@mfa.ee
| address=Messoghion Ave, Athens Tower Bldg 2-4 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107475660 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107475661
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Finland}} {{listing
| name=Finland |alt=| url=https://finlandabroad.fi/web/grc/frontpage | email=sanomat.ate@formin.fi
| address=Hatziyianni Mexi 5 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107255860 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107255864
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|France}} {{listing
| name=France |alt=| url=https://gr.ambafrance.org/ | email=ambafran@first.gr
| address=Vass.Sofias Ave 7 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2103391000 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2103391009
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|Germany}} {{listing
| name=Germany | url=http://athen.diplo.de/ | email=info@athen.diplo.de
| address=Karaoli &amp; Dimitriou 3 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107285111 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107285335
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Hungary}} {{listing
| name=Hungary | alt= | url=https://athen.mfa.gov.hu/ | email=mission.ath@kum.hu
| address=Karneadou 25-29 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107256800 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107256840
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|India}} {{listing
| name=India |alt=| email=indembassy@ath.forthnet.gr
| address=Kleanthous 3 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107216481, +30 2107216227 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107211252
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2020-11-21| content=
}}
* {{flag|Indonesia}}{{listing
| name=Indonesia | alt= | url=https://kemlu.go.id/athens | email=athena.kbri@kemlu.go.id
| address=99, Marathonodromon Street, 15452 Paleo Psychico, PO.BOX : 65181 | lat=38.011588 | long=23.781152 | directions=
| phone=+30 210 677-7692, +30 210 674-2345 | tollfree=+30 694 646 0015
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q75401840
| lastedit=2018-01-15
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Ireland}} {{listing
| name=Ireland |alt=| url=https://www.dfa.ie/irish-embassy/greece/ | email=athensembassy@dfa.ie
| address=Vass.Constantinou Ave 7 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107232771, +30 2107238645, +30 2107232405 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107293383
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|Israel}} {{listing
| name=Israel | alt= | url=http://embassies.gov.il/athens/ | email=ambass-sec@athens.mfa.gov.il
| address=Marathonodromon 1, Psychiko | lat=37.99856 | long=23.76909 | directions=
| phone=+30 2106705500 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2106705555
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q5369738
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Italy}} {{listing
| name=Italy | alt= | url=https://ambatene.esteri.it/ambasciata_atene/it/ | email=ambasciata.atene@esteri.it
| address=Sekeri 2 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2103617260, +30 2103617261, +30 2103617262 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2103617330
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Japan}} {{listing
| name=Japan | alt= | url=http://www.gr.emb-japan.go.jp/itprtop_el/index.html | email=embjapan@otenet.gr
| address=Ethnikis Andistaseos 46, Chalandri | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2106709900 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2106709980
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Malta}} {{listing
| name=Malta Embassy | url= | email=maltaembassy.athens@gov.mt
| address=Vass.Sofias Avenue 96 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107785138 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107785242
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Netherlands}} {{listing
| name=Netherlands | url=http://mfa.nl/ath | email=ath@minbuza.nl
| address=Vass.Konstantinou Avenue 5-7 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 2107254900 | tollfree= | fax=+30 2107254907
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|North Macedonia}} {{listing
| name=Republic of North Macedonia | alt= | url=http://www.mfa.gov.mk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=300&amp;Itemid=646&amp;lang=en | email=athens@mfa.gov.mk
| address=Papadiamanti 4, P. Psychico | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 674 9585 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 674 9572
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Norway}} {{listing
| name=Norway |alt=| url=https://www.norway.no/en/Greece/ | email=emb.athens@mfa.no
| address=Vass.Sofias Ave 23 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0724 6173 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0724 4989
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|Portugal}} {{listing
| name=Portugal | url= | email=embportg@otenet.gr
| address=Vass.Sofias Ave 23 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0723 6784, +30 21 0729 0096, +30 21 0725 7505 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0729 0955
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Romania}} {{listing
| name=Romania | alt= | url=https://atena.mae.ro/en | email=atena@mae.ro
| address=Emmanouil Benaki 7 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0672 8875, +30 21 0672 8876 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0672 8883
| hours=M and Th 9:00-15:00; Tu-W 12:00-18:00; F 9:00-13:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-12-03
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Russia}} {{listing
| name=Russia |alt=| url=https://www.russianembassy.net/iservice.nsf/Cons/EmbassyOfRussiaInAthens | email=embraf@otenet.gr
| address=Nikiforou Litra 28, Psychiko | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0672 5235, +30 21 0672 6130 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0674 9708
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|Saudi Arabia}} {{listing
| name=Saudi Arabia | url= | email=gremb@mofa.gov.sa
| address=Marathonodromon 71, Psychiko | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0671 6911, +30 21 0671 6912, +30 21 0671 6913 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0674 9833
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Serbia}} {{listing
| name=Serbia |alt=| url=http://www.athens.mfa.gov.rs/ | email=beograd@hol.gr
| address=106, Vassilissis Sophias Ave, Consulate 25, Evrou St | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 210 777-43-44, +30 210 777-43-55 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0674 9833
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|South Africa}} {{listing
| name=South Africa | url=http://southafrica.gr/ | email=embassy@southafrica.gr
| address=Kifissias Ave 60, Maroussi | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0610 6645 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0610 6640
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Spain}} {{listing
| name=Spain |alt=| url=http://www.exteriores.gob.es/embajadas/atenas/es/Paginas/inicio.aspx | email=emb-esp@otenet.gr
| address=Dionissiou Areopagitou, 21 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0921 3123, +30 21 0921 3237, +30 21 0921 3238 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0921 3090
| hours= | price=
|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-02| content=
}}
* {{flag|Sweden}} {{listing
| name=Sweden | url=http://www.swedenabroad.com/en-GB/Embassies/Athens/About-us/The-Embassy/ | email=ambassaden.athen@foreign.ministry.se
| address=Vass.Konstantinou Ave 7 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0726 6100 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0726 6150
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Switzerland}} {{listing
| name=Switzerland | url=http://eda.admin.ch/athens | email=vertretung@ath.rep.admin.ch
| address=Iassiou 2 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0723 0364, +30 21 0723 0366, +30 21 0729 9471 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0724 9209
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Taiwan}} {{Listing|name=Taiwan|alt=|url=https://www.roc-taiwan.org/gr_en/index.html|email=grc@mofa.gov.tw|address=Leof. Marathonodromon 57, Psichiko 154 52|lat=|long=|directions=|phone=+30 21 0677 6750|tollfree=|fax=|hours=|price=|wikidata=|lastedit=2021-01-15|content=}}
* {{flag|Turkey}} {{listing
| name=Turkey | url= | email=info@turkishembasy.ondsl.gr
| address=Vass.Georgiou II 8 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0726 3000 | tollfree= | fax=+30 210 7229597
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|United Kingdom}} {{listing
| name=United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland | alt= | url=http://ukingreece.fco.gov.uk/en/ | email=info@fco.gov.uk
| address=Ploutarchou 1 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0727 2600 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0727 2723
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|United States}} {{listing
| name=United States of America | alt= | url=https://gr.usembassy.gov/ | email=usembassy@usembassy.gr
| address=Vass.Sofias Ave 91 | lat=37.9822 | long=23.7552 | directions=
| phone=+30 21 0721 2951, +30 21 0729 4301 | tollfree= | fax=+30 21 0645 6282
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q5369951
| content=
}}

==Go next==

=== Islands ===
[[Piraeus]] - the harbour of Athens, and [[Rafina]] (on the east coast of Attica) are the departure points for a large number of ferry services to the Greek Islands and other destinations in the eastern Mediterranean, including ports in [[Italy]], [[Egypt]], [[Turkey]], [[Israel]] and [[Cyprus]].

The closest islands, suitable for a day trip from '''Piraeus''', are  in the Argosaronic (or Saronic) gulf:
* [[Hydra]]
* [[Aegina]]
* [[Poros]]
* [[Spetses]]
* [[Kea]] (also pronounced ''Tzia'') is a very nearby destination, too, less than two hours from the port of Lavrio.
*[[Evvia|Evia]], or Euboea, is the second-largest Greek island in area and population, after Crete, and in close proximity to Athens. In less than 1.5 hours by bus, train, or car, you can reach [[Chalcis|Chalkis]], or Halkida, the island's capital city and enjoy the local beaches, Ottoman castle on the hill, the promenade with bars &amp; restaurants. From here you can continue to [[Kymi]] and take the ferry to [[Skyros]] island or choose to explore the islands hidden gems.

If what you are thinking is an island further away, like [[Paros]], [[Naxos]], [[Ios]], [[Santorini]] or any of the Dodecanese or Northern Aegean isles, consider extra days off Athens because of their distance from the mainland. Flying is also an option to the more distant islands.

=== Nearby ===
*[[Sounio]], Ktel bus starts from central Athens and also stop in some areas in south Athens. 1 hour from central Athens by car.
* Day trips to the [[Corinth]] Canal, the ancient theatre at [[Epidaurus]] and to the ancient sites of [[Olympia (Greece)|Olympia]], [[Delphi]] and [[Mycenae]] are easy with a rental car.
* Towns along the [[Peloponnese]] such as [[Nafplion]] are charming and worthwhile.

=== North ===
* [[Thessaloniki]], second biggest city in Greece
* [[Larissa]]
* [[Karditsa]]
* [[Trikala]]
* [[Kalambaka]]

===By air===

Athens has ultra-low-cost flights to several European countries, to [[Jordan]], [[Israel]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] and the [[United Arab Emirates]].

{{routebox
| image5=Sign EV8.svg
| imagesize5=22
| directionl5=W
| majorl5=[[Igoumenitsa]]
| minorl5=[[Pireaus]]
| directionr5=E
| majorr5=[[Dikili]]
| minorr5=[[File:Noun Ocean 1639439 006699.svg|18px]] Aegean Sea
| link5=EuroVelo cycling routes
}}

{{geo|37.9667|23.7167|zoom=11}}
{{isPartOf|Attica}}
{{usablecity}}</text>
      <sha1>n173m5wgnu3oqqac26k5ysdfqah5cyv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
