<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikivoyage</sitename>
    <dbname>enwikivoyage</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.46.0-wmf.24</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="1728" case="first-letter">Event</namespace>
      <namespace key="1729" case="first-letter">Event talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bratislava</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4567</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5245787</id>
      <parentid>5245785</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-28T02:42:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ground Zero</username>
        <id>1423298</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Cultural events */</comment>
      <origin>5245787</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="102998" sha1="qyh765c1dvfnxh84zuynuzcc6qs10wq" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Bratislava Banner.jpg}}
'''Bratislava''' ([[Hungarian phrasebook|Hungarian]]: ''Pozsony'', [[German phrasebook|German]]: ''Pressburg'', known as ''Prešporok'' before 1919), is the capital and largest city of [[Slovakia]]. It has a population of more than 475,000 (2021), and is the administrative, cultural and economic centre of the country. For most visitors, it is the entry point into the rest of the country.

Located on the border tripoint of Slovakia, [[Austria]] and [[Hungary]], the city has sat in the very hearts of empires since its earliest mention in the 10th century. As such, the city is a place of contrasts; the city centre features the medieval and renaissance old town, as well as the skyscraper-heavy business and shopping district; the outskirts feature both hillside villas, and communist-era apartment blocks.

== Understand ==
{{climate chart
|Bratislava
|-2.8 |3.1 |37.4
|-1.7 |5.8 |32.9
|1.7 |11.1 |36.8
|5.7 |17.5 |35.9
|10.6 |21.7 |58.6
|14.2 |25.6 |59.2
|16.2 |28.0 |61.8
|15.9 |27.9 |60.5
|11.2 |21.9 |58.6
|6.3 |15.6 |43.6
|2.6 |9.3 |46.2
|-1.5 |3.7 |42.7

|float=right
|clear=right
|description=
|source = &lt;ref name = Pogodaiklimat.ru&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://pogodaiklimat.ru/climate2/11816.htm
|title = Pogodaiklimat.ru – Bratislava
|publisher = Pogodaiklimat.ru
|accessdate = 20 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name= Climatemps&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.bratislava.climatemps.com/ {{dead link|August 2020|December 2020}}
|title = Climate of Bratislava
|publisher = Climatemps
|accessdate = 20 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
[[File:Bratislava Panorama R01.jpg|thumb|300px|Panorama of Bratislava]]
[[File:Bratislava - 52119321317.jpg|thumb|300px|The old town from the castle]]
Bratislava has a very pleasant medieval inner city with narrow, winding streets, a hill-top castle next to the river Danube, and many historic churches and buildings to visit. The old town is centered on two squares, Hlavné námestie (main square) and Hviezdoslavovo námestie (Hviezdoslav square, named after a famous Slovak poet). Of a rather different architectural character are some of the communist-era buildings found in the modern parts of the city; a prime example is Petrzalka housing estate, the biggest Communist-era concrete block housing complex in [[Central Europe]], which stretches on endlessly just across the river. Move further east and there are plenty of rural places to explore. There are farms, vineyards, agricultural land, and tiny villages less than 50 km to the north and east of Bratislava.

Bratislava and its surroundings form the second-most prosperous region in Central and Eastern Europe, with a per capita GDP of around 167% of the EU-27 average. Bratislava is the sixth richest region of the European Union, and GDP per capita is about three times higher than in other Slovak regions.

=== History ===
[[File:Hviezdoslavovo námestie (10266936594).jpg|thumb|300px|Hviezdoslav Square]]
After the fall of the Great Moravian Empire, Slovakia became part of the Kingdom of [[Hungary]] from the 10th century (later included with the [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]]) until the end of the First World War. The city was the capital (1536-1784), the coronation city (1563-1830), and the seat of the Diet (1536-1848) of the Kingdom of Hungary for three centuries. In this period, eleven Hungarian kings and queens were crowned at St. Martin's Cathedral. At that time, the city was called Preßburg in German and Pozsony in Hungarian, and had a clear German (42%) and Hungarian (40%) ethnic majority (1910 census). In 1919, the Treaty of Trianon created Czechoslovakia, and Bratislava was attached to the newly founded state. In the same year, the name Bratislava was officially adopted for the first time.

Between 1939 and 1944, Slovakia was a Nazi puppet state. In 1941–1942 and 1944–1945, this government collaborated in deporting most of Bratislava's approximately 15,000 Jews to concentration camps, where most were murdered. Bratislava was occupied by German troops in 1944, and eventually taken by the Soviet Red Army on 4 April 1945, after a failed insurrection of Slovak partisans, now commemorated as ''Slovenské národné povstanie'', or "Slovak National Uprising".

After the Communist Party seized power in Czechoslovakia in February 1948, the city witnessed profound demographic and urban transformation. In 1969 it became the capital city of the Slovak Socialist Republic, one of the two component states of federal Czechoslovakia.

Bratislava's dissidents anticipated the fall of Communism with the Bratislava candle demonstration in 1988, and the city became one of the foremost centres of the anti-Communist "Velvet Revolution" in 1989. In 1993, the city became the capital of the newly formed Slovak Republic following the "Velvet Divorce".

Since the fall of the Iron Curtain and especially with the accession of Slovakia to the European Union (May 2004) and later the Schengen Area, Bratislava is often marketed together with Vienna as "twin cities" due to their closeness. They are the two European capitals with the shortest distance to one another and should you ever get bored with Bratislava, Vienna is certainly an interesting day trip. You can even cross the roughly 60 km of distance on a bike in a single day if you're moderately fit.

===Visitor information ===
* {{listing
| name=Visit Bratislava | alt= | url=https://www.visitbratislava.com | email=touristinfo@visitbratislava.com
| address=Klobučnícka 2 | lat=48.1441 | long=17.1101 | directions=Take tram to Centrum station and walk southwest for 150 metres
| phone=+421 2 16 186 | tollfree=
| hours=M-Sa 09:00-12:30, 13:00-17:00; Su 10:00-12:30, 13:00-16:00 | price=
| lastedit=2024-09-05
| content=Tourist information centre in Old Town (Centrum). You can also buy the physical [https://card.visitbratislava.com/ Bratislava Card] here.
}}

== Get in ==
[[File:16-05-03-Letisko Milana Rastislava Štefánika-RalfR-DSCF7939 40 41.jpg|thumb|Bratislava Airport]]
===By plane===

====Bratislava Milan Rastislav Štefánik Airport====

{{listing
 | type = go
 | name = Bratislava Airport
 | alt = {{IATA|BTS}}
 | url = http://www.letiskobratislava.sk/
 | email = 
 | address = 
 | lat = 48.17
 | long = 17.212778
 | directions = 
 | phone = 
 | tollfree = 
 | fax = 
 | hours = 
 | price = 
 | wikipedia = Bratislava Airport
 | image = Bratislava airport.jpg
 | wikidata = Q828379
 | lastedit = 2025-02-08
 | content = The largest airport in the Slovak Republic. Served mainly by low cost and charter airlines.
}}

If you are flying with Ryanair and have check-in luggage, do not let the small size of the airport fool you. Arrive at the airport well in advance of your flight, as the queue can get very long.

There are no dedicated airport shuttles, however the airport is served as part of the municipal bus network. Use bus [https://imhd.sk/ba/route-line/61 No 61] (or N61 at night) for a direct connection to the [http://bratislava-slovakia.eu/places/bratislava-airport Central Train Station (Hlavná stanica)]. Or change for a tram at Trnavské mýto to get to the city center (in order to get to the tram stop, use the underpass and the exit marked "Centrum" (city center) and take any tram in the direction towards center. You can't buy tickets from the bus driver (see "Get around" below) so you must buy tickets in advance. Use the vending machines at the bus stop, but you will need euro coins as the vending machines don't take notes (there are also two big red ticket machines in the terminal building close to arrivals, which do accept banknotes and credit cards). You can also buy tickets in the tourist and exchange offices in the terminal, but they have only limited working hours. Be aware that the airport shops and kiosks are not very helpful when it comes to changing bills into coins. A screen in the arrivals hall displays actual departure times of next public transport buses and buses to Vienna. [http://www.imhd.sk Public transport buses] are cheap &amp;ndash; a single ticket to/from the city centre (validate the ticket in the marking machine in the bus; valid for 60 minutes from the moment of validation; transfer to other public transport lines allowed) costs €1.60 including any number of interchanges. Overstaying your ticket will result in an expensive fine, but during night and low travel the 30-min (€1.09) ticket can be sufficient for travelling between the airport and the bus station (or vice versa). Travel to and from the train station at night (with no cars around) is 31 min so you are better off with a 60-minute ticket.

Taxis taken directly from the airport are expensive (more than €30 for a 15-minute journey to the city centre) and even worse, taxi drivers do not respect the price you agreed with them in advance. If you like a taxi, call one or use Uber, Bolt, Hopin or Liftago apps: these are reliably working in Bratislava.

Direct bus services operating in approximately hourly intervals connect the airport with [[Vienna International Airport]] ({{IATA|VIE}}) and the city of [[Vienna]] (travel time to Vienna is c. 80–90 minutes).

====Vienna International Airport====
[[File:Austria Vienna Airport 2011-09-15.jpg|thumb|Vienna International Airport]]
'''[[Vienna International Airport]]'''/Flughafen Wien ({{IATA|VIE}}) is about 45&amp;nbsp;km (28&amp;nbsp;mi) from Bratislava, near to the town of Schwechat in [[Austria]]. The airport is the home base of the flag-carrier '''[https://www.austrian.com Austrian]'''. Most European airlines and several international airlines have direct connections to Vienna from their respective hubs.

There are three companies providing bus services between Vienna and Vienna International Airport and Bratislava, each running hourly. In Bratislava, all buses stop at ''Einsteinova'' (Petržalka) and ''Most SNP'' (under UFO Bridge) and/or Coach Terminal (''Autobusová stanica (Mlynské Nivy)'', in timetables abbreviated as ''Bratislava AS''). All but RegioJet buses continue towards Bratislava Airport every two hours.

A quick summary of transport options (schedules and prices as of June 2018):
* {{listing
| name=Slovak Lines (bus) | url=http://www.postbus.at/en/International_lines/index.jsp | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Price €1 (online, well in advance), €5 (Bratislava centre), €9.50 (Bratislava airport), children under 15 years of age €1; reductions for return-tickets, youth under 26 and seniors from 63| content=In total, there are at least 20 services in either direction from 06:30–22:30 and 24:00. Buses run at least every hour between Vienna Central Train Station (''Wien Hauptbahnhof''; Bus Terminal is next door at [http://www.postbus.at/en/Internat._Bus_Terminal/index.jsp Südtiroler Platz / Wiedner Gürtel]) and Vienna Airport and Bratislava Coach Terminal (''Bratislava AS''). Every two hours they extend to Bratislava Airport. All buses also stop at Hainburg, Wolfsthal (Austria) and at Einsteinova (Petržalka). Please check the [http://www.viennaairport.com/jart/prj3/va/uploads/data-uploads/Passagier/Parken/VIE_Postbus_1195_de_en.pdf timetable] &lt;!-- [https://www.slovaklines.sk/fileadmin/user_upload/pdf/wien.pdf timetable] --&gt;. You are allowed to transport two pieces of baggage per person at €1 per piece. The baggage tags can be purchased from ticket window or from the driver.
}} ''You can book [https://online.slovaklines.sk/home.aspx?l=en&amp;type=eu&amp;aid=postbus&amp;dep=999000682&amp;arr=&amp;jtype=2 online here]{{Dead link|date=May 2025 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}.''

* {{listing
| name=Flixbus (bus) | url= | email= | address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Price from €4.99 (online in advance) up to €9.99; children €3.90–4.99
| content=In total, there are 21 services in either direction from 06:50–23:50 and 01:05 (departure times from airport). Buses run at least every hour between [https://www.vib-wien.at/en/vib-busterminal Vienna U3 Erdberg VIB (''Vienna International Busterminal'')] and Vienna Airport and Bratislava. Bus stops in Bratislava: Einsteinova (Petržalka), New Bridge (''Most SNP'') and Coach Terminal (''Bratislava AS''). Every two hours the buses continue to Bratislava Airport. The buses that are not destined to the airport continue to the Coach Terminal and ''do not stop'' at Most SNP.
}}''You can book [https://shop.global.flixbus.com/search?departureCity=2988&amp;arrivalCity=1745&amp;route=Vienna+Airport-Bratislava&amp;adult=1 online here].''

* {{listing
| name=RegioJet (bus) | url=https://www.regiojet.com/timetables-and-stops/timetables/index.html?timetableId=3817007001 |email= | address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Price €5, as low as €1 if booked very early; children €4.50
| content= In total, there are 16 services in either direction at 7:00 and from 09:00–23:00 (departure times from airport). Buses run every hour between Vienna Central Train Station (''Wien Hauptbahnhof'', Bus Terminal is adjacently situated at [http://www.postbus.at/en/Internat._Bus_Terminal/index.jsp Südtiroler Platz / Wiedner Gürtel]) and Vienna Airport and Bratislava Coach Terminal (''Bratislava AS''), with stops in Einsteinova (close to Incheba in Petržalka) and Most SNP (UFO bridge). RegioJet buses do not continue towards Bratislava Airport. Make sure to book online.
}} ''You can book [https://fahrkarten.regiojet.com/Booking/from/10204055/to/10202001/tarif/REGULAR/return/false online here].''

* {{listing
| name=Train | url=http://fahrplan.oebb.at/bin/query.exe/en | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=The trains from Vienna to Bratislava do not pass by Vienna Airport as they run on different lines. &lt;!-- There are 2 different routes that do not pass by (!!): see section Get in by Train --&gt;However, it would be possible to take the hourly train (S7 or REX7) from Vienna Airport to Wolfsthal near the Austrian/Slovak border (45 minutes, regular ticket costs €11.10) and change to Slovak-operated [https://imhd.sk/ba/schedule-timetable/linka/901/smer/Bratislava-Most-SNP/zastavka/Wolfsthal-Bhf-Hauptstrasse-40/943719027757 regional bus 901] that will take you to Bratislava city centre (€1.50, €0.75 for youth under 26 years of age, children under 6 travel free) in just 12 minutes. The buses leave at 55 minutes past the hour on most hours during the day, except on Sunday when it is a 2-hourly service, but be aware that the departures/arrivals of the bus are not always aligned with the trains, so you run into risk of up to two hours of waiting in a small village 5&amp;nbsp;km from the border. Walking to Bratislava from here will take an hour and is not recommended though there is a path near the Danube. All in all, this is not a preferable way to get to Bratislava, but could be useful if schedules have been checked or if you have a back-up plan to arrange a ride or taxi (which can be hard to explain if you don't speak Slovak or German) from Wolfsthal.}}
* {{listing
| name=Taxi | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Cab fare is not set, so agree before getting in.
}}
* {{listing
| name=Vienna–Bratislava Transfer | alt= | url=http://www.vienna-transfer.at/en/transfer_bratislava.html | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-17
| content=A flat rate of €140 for transfers between Vienna and Bratislava.
}}

====Alternatives====
[[Brno]] Airport has a very small selection of destination offerings. [[Budapest]] and Prague airports are about a 4-5 hour journey but can mean substantial savings on intercontinental trips, especially to [[New York City]] or [[Beijing]].

=== By train ===
Most international trains stop at {{go
| name=Bratislava Main Station | alt=Bratislava hlavná stanica (sometimes Bratislava hl. st.) | url=https://www.zsr.sk/pre-cestujucich/zoznam-stanic-zastavok/detail-stanice.html?sid=100 | email=
| address= | lat=48.158333 | long=17.106944 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Bratislava hlavná stanica | image=Bratislava Main Station Bratislava hlavná stanica.jpg | wikidata=Q899662
| lastedit=2018-06-27
| content=It has good connections to public transport. To get to the city centre, you can take tram number 1 and get off at "Nám. SNP" (short for "Námestie Slovenského národného povstania") ([https://imhd.sk/ba/maps map]), but it is an unchallenging walk of 20–25 minutes anyway – just ask for a free map and directions at the tourism information desk inside the station.}} 
:* '''[[Vienna]]:''' 1 hr. There are two regional express services from ''Wien Hauptbahnhof'' (Vienna Central Train Station) to two different stations in Bratislava: one to Bratislava Hlavná stanica (Bratislava Central Train Station) via Marchegg and the other to Bratislava Petržalka station via Kittsee – each operating in hourly intervals, with first daily service leaving around 05:00 and the last train leaving around 22:30, to Petržalka at 23:15. The prices of regular tickets for the different routes are not the same. But with the advantageous return-ticket called [https://www.oebb.at/en/regionale-angebote/ueberregionale-angebote/bratislava-ticket ''Euregio'' '''''Bratislava-Ticket'''''] which, purchased in Vienna, costs €18 (children under 15 years of age: €9), you can indiscriminately use any train on both routes. It is valid for 4 days, but the trip must be started on the first day of validity. And on the first day it also serves as a day-pass for all public transport in Bratislava allowing the free use of the urban public transport till 01:00. You even will benefit from this return-ticket if you go only one-way to Bratislava-Petržalka via Kittsee, because it's cheaper than the regular full-price one-way ticket! Also, transporting one bicycle on the train is free. You can obtain it from ticket counters as well as from all ÖBB ticket-vending machines, but not by entering the destination, rather by choosing, at the bottom, "More products" and then "Tickets for neighbouring countries".
{{cautionbox|Due to the timeline of the reconstruction of a railway bridge to Marchegg slipping, trains from Vienna only run to the [[#Bratislava-Petržalka|Petržalka station]], except the Railjet services. Take into account the additional transfer time.}}
:* '''[[Prague]]:''' 4 hr, EC trains every 2 hours operated by the Czech railway company ČD (České drahy). [https://www.cd.cz/en/spojeni-a-jizdenka/ Online tickets] are much cheaper than the tickets purchased at the station, but you should buy them at least 3 days in advance. It is possible to get on a through sleeper car on the Euronight train [https://czech-transport.com/index.php?train=28&amp;lang=en EN 477 "Metropol"]{{Dead link|date=March 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}, however, the journey only takes 6 hours meaning you won't get too much sleep.
:Also the Czech private low-cost carrier RegioJet provides three direct connections ([https://regiojet.com/where-we-go/time-tables timetable]) to Bratislava, which continue to Budapest. Travel time just under 4 hours. Although RegioJet has ticket counters in Prague, the best way is to book tickets online ([https://bustickets.regiojet.com/Booking/from/10202003/to/1841058000/tarif/REGULAR/return/false ''here'']) well in advance in order to obtain best-price tickets.
:* '''[[Budapest]]:''' 2½ hr, nine EC trains a day in daytime, departing from ''Budapest Nyugati station''. The trains shuttle every 2 hours in both directions. [https://www.bratislava-slovakia.eu/travel/budapest-bratislava/budapest-train From Budapest], the cyclic two-hour EC schedule is from 05:30–19:30. From Bratislava, then EC trains run on cyclic two-hour schedule from 06:05–20:05. As of September 2024, a Budapest–Bratislava ticket costs €17.80 regardless of purchasing from Slovak railway company ZSSK or Hungarian railway company MÁV-START.
:* '''[[Berlin]]:''' 8½ hr, five day-time EC train connections every two hours. Except for one direct train ([https://czech-transport.com/index.php?train=1432&amp;lang=en EC 173 "Hungaria"]), all other trains require to change in [[Prague]]. No direct sleeper service, but one with only one change in Prague at a reasonable time of day. Tickets bought directly before departure or on the train usually are a lot more expensive than advance purchase fares (not earlier than 90 days prior to departure), which may be very cheap when bought as early as possible (starting at €29). Note that there is a €2 surcharge for tickets bought at the counter, but you can get information at the counter and later buy at the machine anyway, at no surcharge. Tickets can also be bought online at Deutsche Bahn's [https://www.bahn.com/en/view/index.shtml excellent website].
:* '''[[Warsaw]]:''' 7 hr, daily one direct train ([https://czech-transport.com/index.php?train=2129&amp;lang=en IC 131 "Varsovia"]) and two connections with change at Břeclav; 10¾ h on night train [https://www.czech-transport.com/index.php?train=1484&amp;lang=en EN 407 "Chopin"]{{Dead link|date=March 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} with change at Břeclav. There is a limited offer (''SparDay'' for daytime trains, ''SparNight'' for sleepers) of discounted tickets to Budapest via Bratislava, they're much cheaper than normal tickets to Bratislava.
:* '''[[Belgrade]]:''' 12¾ hr in total, starting on [https://czech-transport.com/index.php?train=1122&amp;lang=en INT/D 344 "Avala"]{{Dead link|date=March 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} towards Budapest, there ''transfer from Keleti to Nyugati train station'' in order to continue on EC 270 "Metropolitan" to Bratislava. Trains from Serbia are often delayed, but in Budapest you have a 2-hour gap. Alternative: 11½ hr with [https://czech-transport.com/index.php?train=2248&amp;lang=en INT 342 "Ivo Andrić"]{{Dead link|date=March 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} to Budapest, there changing onto EN 476 "Metropol", with a transfer time of 20 minutes at the same train station. (There is no direct train anymore.) &lt;!-- The connections with change cost almost half of the direct-train fare, because you can buy discounted tickets Belgrade–Budapest and Budapest–Bratislava. --&gt;
:* '''[[Kyiv]]:''' 23 hr, minimum travel time with only one change, starting on overnight train [https://czech-transport.com/index.php?train=3626&amp;lang=en D 40749 "Hortobágy"]{{Dead link|date=March 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} to Budapest, there ''transfer from Keleti to Nyugati train station'' (gap of 1 hr 40 min), and continuing on train EC 278 "Metropolitan". &lt;!-- 28 hours, daily night train with through cars from Moscow (42 hr). --&gt;
:* '''[[Rijeka]]''' nightly via [[Ljubljana]] and Csorna, continuing to [[Břeclav]], [[Brno]], [[Pardubice]] and Prague. It's run by [https://www.regiojet.com/ Regiojet], booking essential.

{{go
| name=Bratislava-Petržalka | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.1213 | long=17.0997| directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=
| lastedit=2020-11-27
| content=The other principal station is Bratislava-Petržalka, situated in a residential district, south of the river Danube. The station serves as a terminus for some of the trains from Vienna.
}}
Bus 80 (direction: ''Kollárovo námestie'') departs from outside the Petržalka station building or use the underground passageway in the station hall, then hop on any of the buses that leave from the opposite side of the road. Buses 91 and 191 (direction: ''Nový most''), 93 and 94 (direction: ''Hlavná stanica'' and ''Vazovova'' respectively) all go directly to city centre.

=== By bus ===
[[File:Kosciol Elzbiety w Bratyslawie.JPG|thumb|Church of St. Elisabeth]]
Coach lines connect Bratislava with all of [[Slovakia]], a high number of Czech cities and a number of EU destinations, including [[London]], [[Paris]]. Between Bratislava and Budapest there are daily connections, so does, for example, Flixbus provide a [https://shop.global.flixbus.com/search?departureCity=1795&amp;arrivalCity=1745&amp;route=Budapest-Bratislava&amp;rideDate=&amp;backRideDate=8&amp;adult=1 bus service] about every two hours.

From southern Germany there are a few connections as well. For more on the newly emerging domestic market as well as some information on international routes (operated by mostly the same companies) see [[Long distance bus travel in Germany]].

The most frequent international coach connection by far is '''[[Vienna]]''', though.
There are three companies – Postbus/Slovak Lines, Flixbus, and RegioJet – providing bus services between Vienna and Vienna International Airport and Bratislava, each in hourly intervals from different points of departure within Vienna. In Bratislava, all buses stop at ''Einsteinova'' (Petržalka) and ''Most SNP'' (under UFO Bridge) and/or Coach Terminal (''Autobusová stanica (Mlynské Nivy)'', in timetables abbreviated as ''Bratislava AS''). All but RegioJet buses continue towards Bratislava Airport every two hours. A trip from/to Vienna takes about 1½ hours.

The fare to Bratislava is the same, irrespective of whether the travel starts in Vienna or at Vienna Airport. To Bratislava airport the fare may be the same or higher with Flixbus, while Postbus/Slovak Lines generally charge a higher fare.

Hourly departures from Vienna (schedules and prices as of June 2018):
:
* ''Slovak Lines:'' from Vienna Central Train Station (''Wien Hauptbahnhof''; Bus Terminal is adjacently situated at [https://web.archive.org/web/20180625190425/http://www.postbus.at/en/Internat._Bus_Terminal/index.jsp Südtiroler Platz / Wiedner Gürtel]) 06:00–22:00, 23.30; to Bratislava airport from 06:00–14:00 and 15:00–19:00 every 2 hours. ''You can book [https://online.slovaklines.sk/home.aspx?l=en&amp;type=eu&amp;aid=postbus&amp;dep=999002905&amp;arr=&amp;jtype=2 online here]{{Dead link|date=May 2025 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}.''
* ''Flixbus:'' from [https://vib-wien.at/en Vienna U3 Erdberg VIB (''Vienna International Busterminal'')] 06:30–23:30, 0:45; to Bratislava airport from 07:30–21:30 every 2 hours. To Bratislava centre there are two additional buses from Vienna Central Train Station operated by Polski Bus under the umbrella of Flixbus. ''You can book [https://shop.global.flixbus.com/search?departureCity=1394&amp;arrivalCity=1745&amp;route=Vienna-Bratislava&amp;adult=1 online here].''
* ''RegioJet:'' from Vienna Central Train Station (''Wien Hauptbahnhof''; Bus Terminal is adjacently situated at [https://web.archive.org/web/20180625190425/http://www.postbus.at/en/Internat._Bus_Terminal/index.jsp Südtiroler Platz / Wiedner Gürtel]) 06:25, 08:25–22:25. ''You can book [https://fahrkarten.regiojet.com/Booking/from/10202052/to/10202001/tarif/REGULAR/false/ online here].''
:''For more details see [[Bratislava#Vienna International Airport|Vienna International Airport / Flughafen Wien]].''

{{go
| name=Bus Station | alt=Autobusová stanica, Nivy | url= | email=
| address=Mlynské nivy | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q67032897
| lastedit=2026-03-01
| content=At the eastern border of the city centre, which is a massive construction site with lot of new development happening around. The bus station is in the underground of the shopping center. To get there from within the city, most likely you will want to target the station "Autobusova stanica" or "Košická".
}}

=== By boat ===
[[File:Bratislava, Devín, Twin City liner.jpg|thumb|Twin City liner connects Bratislava with Austria's capital Vienna]]
Regular tourist boat lines operate on the Danube from spring through fall on routes from Vienna. You can find routes and schedules [https://www.lod.sk/en/cruises-2/regular-cruises/detail/bratislava-vienna-bratislava/ here].

A [http://www.twincityliner.com high speed ferry boat] travels to Vienna at a higher cost than other means of transport. A one-way ticket from Vienna to Bratislava by Twin City Liner costs about €25-30 (whereas a return train ticket is less than €15). The Twin City Liner's boats travel at 60 km/h and the journey takes about 1 hr 15 min from Vienna to Bratislava and about 1 hr 30 min from Bratislava to Vienna (almost as much as the train). Unlike the train though, which stops at stations distant from the center (about 2–3&amp;nbsp;km), the boat stops are in the very centres of both Vienna (Schwedenplatz) and Bratislava (Novy Most).

=== By kayak and canoe ===
Danube river is getting very popular for multi-day tours. Some people do their paddling all the way from Germany to Black Sea (more than 2516&amp;nbsp;km / 1563&amp;nbsp;mi), also known as TID. Bratislava is well developed for paddling. There are several paddling clubs at "Karloveske rameno" with accommodation possible at [http://club.paddler.sk Paddler Club] at river km 1872, near "Stary most" at r.km 1868. Free camping is possible along river shore; good places are around km 1872 right, 1864-60 left.

=== By car ===
Bratislava lies on the border of two other countries and has a relatively good road system. The town can be accessed by motorways (i.e. limited access highway) from northern Slovakia and Poland, Czech Republic, Hungary as well as Austria. As a result, you can pass the town without having to leave the motorway at all. Similar to most countries in Central Europe, you have to pay for using the highways. Similar to Hungary, the payment is all done electronically (so you do not have to have a sticker on the windshield) and can be bought [http://www.eznamka.sk online], on most petrol stations and in kiosk on border. The motorways within the boundaries of Bratislava town can be used for free.

After entering the city, a parking information system is in place to lead you to the next free parking spot. In the center of town you either can use one of the paid underground garages or buy a parking card from vendors in yellow vests and try to find a free spot in the streets. The former is recommended on weekends as finding a parking place in the one-ways can turn into a real head breaking puzzle. If you do find a spot in the street and it's a weekday between 08:00 and 16:00 you have to pay for parking. Parking meters are usually available at the corners, are signed posted with blue and yellow sign and take coins only.

It may be a good idea to leave the car at the '''Aupark parking lot''' which also serves as a "Park and Walk" facility for tourists (note that the indoor parking facilities as well as parts of the outdoor parking lot are closed from 24:00-06:00, the rest of the parking space is free to use 24/7). You can leave your car here and walk through the park and across the Danube to the city center, which is a 10-minute stroll, or just use public transport. It is not recommended to leave the car in residential areas outside of the city center to avoid paid parking, as foreign cars may attract car thieves.

Renting a car is also an option, especially if you are visiting destinations outside of Bratislava. All major rental companies have a stall at the airport but most have a city office as well plus there is a lot of local car rental companies, some even deliver the car to your hotel/apartment. Use common sense to pick the reliable one.

=== By bike ===
Bratislava has nice surroundings for biking and an international bike route leads along the southern shore of the Danube river (Donauradweg, or EuroVelo 6). The route from Austria via Bratislava down to Hungary is well marked, and also accessible for hiking on foot. Motorised transport is prohibited on the bike route.

However, the town has not many biking routes and they are mostly ignored by car drivers. There are millions of ways though to [http://www.cyklotrasy.sk bike in the Carpathian hills and along the rivers Danube and Morava]{{Dead link|date=August 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}. Read some more in "Do" below.

== Get around ==
{{mapframe|48.1446304| 17.111|zoom=15|name=The city center of Bratislava}}
{{mapshapes|Q1582299}}
Generally, Bratislava is a walking city, though as of the early 2020s with increasing number of cycling lines. The centre is very small and cosy and you can easily walk from one side to another in a few minutes. The city centre is a [[Car-free destinations|pedestrian zone]], but be aware of cyclists and occasional cars that can sometimes drive rather quickly in between the pedestrian area and outdoor cafes.

===Public transport===
[[File:Ba tram map v2.svg|thumb|[[File:Tram-Logo.svg|20px]] Network (2024)]]
[[File:Škoda-30T.JPG|thumb|Škoda 30 T tram in Bratislava]]
[[File:New Bridge by night.JPG|right|thumb|Most SNP, across the Danube.]]
[[File:Mercedes-Benz Capacity Bratislava line 95.JPG|right|thumb|A typical red bus in Bratislava.]]
If you want to travel outside of the centre, use the trams or trolley buses if you need to get from one point to another quickly. Bratislava has a rather good '''[https://www.idsbk.sk/en/ public transport system]''' mainly operated by the city transport company [https://www.dpb.sk/ DPB] ''(website in Slovak only)''. Buses tend to be the slowest means of transport. '''Stops''' typically have to be requested, except for trams. To enter bus/trolleybus one has to be standing visibly on the bus stop. To exit, one needs to press a button nearby doors and the driver will stop at the next stops. '''Bus doors''' have to be opened by passengers (except for few oldest buses), just push a button on the door or near the door.

A single-journey ticket costs €1.09, valid for 30 minutes only. There is a longer validity ticket available for €1.60 (valid for 60 minutes). All tickets can be used for any number of travels within the specified time period. If you are staying for a holiday, consider buying one from a choice of longer term tickets valid for 1, 3 and 7 days (24, 72, and 168 hours from validation) for €4.80, €10.8 and €14.40 respectively. For more information about tickets, check the [https://www.idsbk.sk/en/ticket-prices/ IDS BK] (Integrated Transport System) website. '''Note''' that you also need to buy a [https://www.idsbk.sk/en/ticket-prices/baggage/ separate ticket] for your suitcase or other large luggage; buy a luggage ticket for {{EUR|0.55}} which covers 180 mins.

You must '''validate your ticket''' in the validation machines on the bus/tram immediately after boarding (via any door) – on buses and trams, you can also validate your debit/credit card on any card machine, though sometimes they can be clunky and slow to process (if this happens, try a different reader). When it comes to proving that you have not exceeded the time stated on your ticket (e.g. 30 minutes on a 30-minute ticket), official schedule times are decisive — not the actual travel times (do not give in to unfriendly ticket inspectors claiming the contrary). You can find out the scheduled travel times in the left-most column of the schedules, left of the stop name or via the internet (see below).

Bus and tram drivers in Bratislava ''do not'' sell tickets, therefore you ''either'' need to obtain a ticket ''before'' entering a bus or a tram, or use '''contactless payment''' (credit/debit card). To use contactless on board, select the ticket you need, then tap your card. There are ticket vending machines at most stops in the town. Only coins and contactless credit cards can be used at the yellow machines (which sells all short term tickets and some longer term tickets), but at larger stops there are also new big red machines which sell the full range of tickets and accept all cards and even banknotes. Yellow machines at some stops do not accept contactless credit cards, which can be frustrating if you do not have coins on hand. '''SMS tickets''' are also available, but only if you send a text message from a cell phone with a Slovak SIM card, which rules out all short-term foreign tourists. SMS tickets cannot be used on S-trains.

If you purchased a "Eurgion Bratislava-Ticket" return ticket in Vienna, it also serves as a pass for all public transport on the date shown on the ticket, and does not need to be validated on Bratislava public transport.

Besides vending machines, tickets are also sold in many news stands and — very conveniently for travellers arriving by train, late in the evening or at weekends — in railway stations at the ticket counters (ticket counter 16 at the main railway station). You can also purchase tickets for public transport in every tourist information bureau. Try asking for the [https://card.visitbratislava.com/ Bratislava Card] which combines a 1 to 3-day ticket with various discounts and is available at information bureaus, but note that the City Card is significantly more expensive than public transport tickets alone, so make sure it is the best option for you!

Tickets can also be bought using an app for [https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.casperise.urbi.online.bid Android] or [https://apps.apple.com/app/id1360894243 iOS].

There are 3 '''main interchange points''' in the close city centre where you can get a bus or tram to nearly anywhere else:
* Hodžovo námestie (Presidential palace) for Northwest- and East-bound bus connections
* Námestie SNP / Kamenné námestie (down the pedestrian area below Hodžovo námestie, on the northern edge of centre) for trams
* Most SNP (close to St. Martin's Cathedral and the Danube banks) for trams and for west-bound buses as well as bus connections to Petržalka.

Main tram, bus and trolleybus lines operate from 04:30 until approximately 23:30. If you need to '''travel by bus at night''', go to the main railway station which is the main night line interchange point or use the bus stops at Presidential palace (Hodžovo námestie). All night lines have common departure times from the main railway station at 23:30 and then every 60 minutes for every line and outbound direction until 03:30. Some lines have an extra outbound departure at midnight. When travelling by night lines, every stop must be requested. Especially around midnight on Fridays and Saturdays, the buses tend to be very crowded on some lines as young people return from clubs.

The routes of the public transport do change sometimes, especially due to trackworks and renovation. For example, in June 2019 the tram lines were all completely changed. If you have an older map, old tourist guide, etc., chances are the transport lines (numbers, destinations, transfer points) are no longer valid. Even Google Maps occasionally shows wrong terminal name or missing a stop, but the general direction of the route is accurate. Check online at either the official [https://www.idsbk.sk/en/information/maps-schemes/ IDS BK] site or at the unofficial [https://imhd.sk/ba/maps iMHD] site which has a wider range of maps, the information at stops (available in English), or ask your fellow passengers if not sure.

If necessary, it is also possible to '''walk to Petrzalka station''' from the city (some 25 minutes). The path is clearly marked now but note that Petržalka is just a little more than the biggest block flats housing estate in Central Europe. Head for the bridge with the flying saucer-like looking tower atop it (Most SNP or also known as Nový most). Once you reach the bridge, you will notice that there is a walkway running along the underside of it, for pedestrians. Once on the other side of the Danube river, follow the right hand-side of the bridge with a walkway made of red paving. This will lead you to the station. Alternatively, you can walk through Bratislava's equivalent of the Central Park called Sad Janka Kráľa and visit the Aupark Shopping Mall at the park. Once exiting Aupark on the other side, turn right and follow the street to get to the pavement mentioned above. The route is very safe during the day, but for typically western-looking tourists, it might be dangerous at night (although not more than in any other European "panelák" (see above) housing estate). Take a guide, if needed. If you want to walk from the station to the city, turn right outside of the station building and follow the path described above in reverse direction.

=== Taxis ===
Do not take taxis waiting outside of major transfer points and tourist areas, such as main railway station, airport, bus station, Petrzalka train station, in front of Alizee nightbar at the northern corner of the city centre, etc. as they ''will'' rip you off. Taxis are cheaper in Bratislava when called in advance than when hailed on street. As a tourist, your best bet is to use one of the apps - '''Uber''' and '''Bolt''' are both present in Bratislava, although sometimes with longer waiting times compared to other cities. Other reliable taxi apps are '''Liftago''' and '''Hopin''', they support both payment by card or cash to the driver if you do not want to enter your card details (payment method has to be selected before ordering the taxi).

== See ==

{{mapframe|48.141| 17.114|zoom=13}}
{{mapshapes|Q1582299}}
[[File:Bratislava, Hrad, Slovensko.jpg|right|thumb|Bratislava Castle]]

===Bratislava Castle===
If your time in Bratislava is limited, try to make a concerted effort to visit the castle. It's the main highlight of Bratislava, though it does require a short climb up several flights of stairs.

To access the general castle precinct, use tram line 9 to Kapucínska. From Kapucínska, cross the dual carriageway on the overpass and then head south (left in direction from tram stop) onto Židovská. There will be a divide, but keep right and follow the cobblestone road. After a climb, you should see some stairs on your right – follow those stairs up until you reach the castle precinct.
* {{see
| name=Bratislava Castle | alt=Bratislavský hrad | url=http://www.snm.sk/?2003 | email=
| address= | lat=48.1420 | long=17.1000 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 54411444 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-Su 10:00-18:00 | price=Adult €14
| wikidata=Q593311
| lastedit=2026-03-01
| content=The castle contains a Museum of Bratislava History, and a baroque garden. There is also a restaurant open till after the actual castle tours into the night. The general precinct area immediately outside the castle, including the vantage points of the city are usually always open during the daytime, and is free to access.
}}

===Museums and galleries===
[[File:St Martin's cathedral, Bratislava, Slovakia.jpg|right|thumb|St. Martin's cathedral]]
[[File:Ba-Franciscan church-interior.jpg|right|thumb|Franciscan church, interior]]
For museum-goers, Bratislava is the place to go, with some bigger and loads of small '''museums''' around town. Every year in the weekend around 24 April Bratislava celebrates a festival called "Bratislava for All", giving locals and visitors the possibility to visit most of the facilities governed by the city for free or a reduced fee, this including most of the museums and galleries. In May, the city's museums and galleries keep their gates open to visitors until late at night, this being called the "Night of Museums and Galleries".

* {{see
| name=Red Crayfish Pharmacy Pharmacological Museum 
| alt=Farmaceutické múzeum | url=https://muzeumbratislava.sk/en/red-crayfish-pharmacy 
| email=
| address=Michalská 28 
| lat=48.14523 | long=17.10666 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=10:00–18:00, closed Tuesdays 
| price=
| wikidata=Q7303948
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Slovak National Gallery (SNG) | alt= | url=http://www.sng.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.14008 | long=17.10858 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1744024
| content=For a taste of '''visual arts''', pay a visit to the National Gallery at the embankment between Starý most and Nový most with permanent collections of Slovak and European medieval art pieces, although the temporary exhibitions tend to be far more interesting.
}}
* {{see
| name=Bratislava City Gallery (GMB) | alt= | url=http://www.gmb.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.144825 | long=17.107822 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q913415
| content=Bratislava City Gallery is also a good pick to see displays of historical fine arts, paintings and sculptures along with interesting temporary exhibitions.
}}
* {{see
| name=Danubiana Meulensteen Art Museum | alt= | url=http://www.danubiana.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat=48.0341 | long=17.2326 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=€12
| wikidata=Q1165115
| lastedit=2026-02-28
| content=If you like modern art better, pay a visit to the Danubiana Art Museum on the southern edge of Bratislava but be aware that it is too far for a stroll, with little to no public transport connections, and is best reached by car or taxi. It is located on the Gabčíkovo Dam, a hydroelectric power plant.
}}
* {{see
| name=Milan Dobes Museum | alt= | url=http://www.milandobes.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=This small museum features modernist Op-art. It lies in the city center and is recommended to all interested in the development of modern art.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Museum | alt= | url=http://www.snm.sk/?lang=eng&amp;section=home&amp;org=3 | email=
| address=Žižkova 14 | lat=48.14024 | long=17.11395 | directions=At the foot of Castle Hill
| phone=+421 2 59207273 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Permanent archaelogical collections.
}}
* {{see
| name=Bratislava City Museum | alt= | url=http://www.muzeum.bratislava.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.14377 | long=17.10875 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1512466
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Natural Science Museum | alt= | url=http://www.snm.sk/?lang=eng&amp;section=home&amp;org=2 | email=
| address=Vajanského nábrežie 2 | lat=48.14025 | long=17.11300 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 59349122 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Echoing the communist era, the natural science exhibitions have an interesting collection of artifacts and is slowly being transformed into a modern era exhibition.
}}
* {{see
| name=Gerulata | alt= | url=https://muzeumbratislava.sk/en/ancient-gerulata | email=
| address=Gerulatská 7, 851 10 Rusovce | lat=48.0557 | long=17.1494 | directions=
| phone=+421 2591 008 12 | tollfree=
| hours=Closed November to March | price=€4
| wikipedia=Gerulata
| lastedit=2026-02-28
| content=This is an ancient Roman military camp with archeological findings on display. If you're into all things Roman, you should also consider a visit to the nearby '''[http://www.carnuntum.at/de Carnuntum]''' which has a large archeological site and is a few minutes by car from Bratislava.
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Transport | alt= | url=https://stm-ke.sk/en/branches/museum-of-transport-in-bratislava/basic-information | email=
| address=Šancová 1/B | lat=48.156389 | long=17.106111 | directions=at the NE corner of the intersection for Pražská and Šancová, turn right to the pedestrian overpass and go up the stairs
| phone=+421 2 52444163 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-Su 10:00-17:00 (closed M) | price=Adults €8, students and seniors 65-70 €4, children 3-6 and seniors 70+ €1, children under 3 free. Free entry on first Wednesday of each month
| wikidata=Q4958040
| lastedit=2024-09-23
| content=With a display of historical vehicles (automobiles, farm vehicles, bicycles, firefighting vehicles, railway, model ships and model buses) in the first railway station in the city, very close to the current Main Railway Station. Free parking in front of the museum for up to 4 hours by displaying the ticket on the dashboard.
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of Trade | alt= | url=http://www.muzeum.sk/?obj=muzeum&amp;ix=mo | email=
| address=Linzbothova 16 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 45243167 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=This museum has some remarking pieces of historic advertising plates and other artifacts.
}}
* {{see
| name=Jewish Community Museum | alt= | url=http://www.synagogue.sk | email=
| address=Heydukova 11-13 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 5441 6949 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Rare Jewish ritual tools, gold-embroidered mantles protecting the holy biblical scrolls, unique photographs of students who had attended the famed Bratislava rabbi school that reveal even to this day the atrocities of the Holocaust. It is situated in the Heydukova Street Synagogue, which is the only synagogue in Bratislava. Constructed in 1923-1926, it is a Cubist building designed by the Bratislava-based Jewish architect Artur Szalatnai-Slatinský and is listed as a national cultural monument. Orthodox in orientation, the synagogue still serves as an active Jewish house of worship. The Jewish Community Museum with a permanent exhibition “The Jews of Bratislava and Their Heritage” is installed upstairs and during the summer season is open to the public up till September, every Friday 13:00 till 16:00 and every Sunday 10:00-13:00.
}}
* {{see
| name=Museum of City History | alt= | url=http://www.muzeum.bratislava.sk/en/vismo/dokumenty2.asp?id_org=700016&amp;id=1110&amp;p1=1107 | email=
| address= | lat=48.14369 | long=17.10913 | directions=in the old town hall
| phone=+421 2 59205130 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-F 10:00–17:00, Sa Su 11:00–18:00 | price=€8
| lastedit=2026-03-01
| content=Including the museums of history and music as well as the city dungeon and the exhibition on medieval justice.
}}
* {{see
| name=Devín Castle | alt=Hrad Devín | url=https://hraddevin.mmb.sk/en/ | email=
| address=Muránska 10, 841 10 Devín | lat=48.174 | long=16.979 | directions=5 miles west, overlooking the Danube
| phone=+421 2657 301 05 | tollfree=
| hours=10:00–16:00, closed Mondays | price=€8 April to October, €6 November to March
| wikipedia=Devín Castle
| lastedit=2026-02-28
| content=There has been a fortress on this site since Roman times. In the 19th and early 20th century it became a Slovak national symbol. During the Communist dictatorship, it was part of the border zone which prevented people from escaping the country.
}}

===Churches===
* {{see
| name=St. Martin's Cathedral | alt=Dóm sv. Martina | url=http://dom.fara.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat=48.1421 | long=17.1049 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours=Nov-Mar: M-Sa 09:00-11:30, 13:00-16:00, Su 13:30-16:00; Apr-Oct: Mon-Sa 09:00-11:30, 13:00-18:00, Su 13:30-16:00 | price=Entrance €2
| wikidata=Q239560
| content=The largest and one of the oldest churches in Bratislava, situated below Bratislava Castle. The Gothic cathedral, formerly the coronation-church of several Hungarian kings, begun in 1204, and reconsecrated in 1445, was restored in 1861-80. The tower is surmounted by a pyramid bearing a gilded Hungarian royal crown.
}}
* {{see
| name=St. Clare's Church | alt=Kostol sv. Kláry | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=A Gothic church on Klariská street, in the historical center; now used as a concert hall.
}}
* {{see
| name=Church of the Annunciation | alt=Kostol Zvestovania / Františkáni / Františkánsky kostol | url=http://www.frantiskani.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.14489 | long=17.10836 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1450292
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Church of the Holy Savior | alt=Kostol Najsvätejšieho Spasitel'a | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.143889 | long=17.108611 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q6188001
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Church of St. Elisabeth | alt=Kostol svätej Alžbety | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.143389 | long=17.116833 | directions=Located on Bezručova street
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q579043
| content=Nicknamed the '''Blue Church''' (Modrý kostolík), this is a beautiful Jugendstil church finished in 1913.
}}
* {{see
| name=Trinitarian Church of Bratislava | alt=Kostol trinitárov | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.146111 | long=17.106667 | directions=On the Župné námestie square in the old town
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=free
| wikidata=Q928414
| content=
}}

===Other prominent buildings===
[[File:Bratyslawa Teatr Narodowy.jpg|thumb|The historic building of the Slovak National Theatre]]
* {{see
| name=Primate's Palace | alt=Primaciálny palác | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.143962 | long=17.108674 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q938516
| content=Now the seat of the Mayor of Bratislava.
}}
* {{see
| name=Old Town Hall | alt=Stará radnica | url=https://muzeumbratislava.sk/en/old-town-hall | email=
| address=Primaciálne square 3 | lat=48.14382 | long=17.10958 | directions=next to Primate's Palace
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=€8
| lastedit=2026-03-01
| content=The Old Town Hall and Apponyi Palace is open to the public as a museum, with an exhibition of city history.
}}
* {{see
| name=Grassalkovich Palace and gardens | alt=Grassalkovičov palác | url=http://bratislava-slovakia.eu/places/sightseeing/presidential-grassalkovich-palace-garden | email=
| address= | lat=48.1492 | long=17.1078 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Also know as the '''Presidential Palace''' (Prezidentský palác) - a Rococo/late Baroque summer palace with a French garden, used as a seat of the President of Slovakia. In one of the garden's alleys you will see a row of trees planted by famous people such as Juan Carlos I (King of Spain). In front of the Palace you will see the Slovak National Guard.
}}
* {{see
| name=Gallery Nedbalka
| alt= 
| url=https://www.nedbalka.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.1441 | long=17.1111 | directions=
| phone=+421 2207 660 31 | tollfree= 
| hours=13:00–19:00, closed Mondays 
| price=€8
| content=Gallery of modern Slovak art from the late 19th century, in a building reminiscent of the New York Guggenheim.
}}
* {{see
| name=Mirbach Palace | alt=Mirbachov palác | url= | email=
| address=Františkánske námestie 11, 811 01 | lat=48.14491 | long=17.10784 | directions=
| phone=+421 2544 315 56 | tollfree=
| hours=11:00–18:00, closed M | price=€8. Free entry with Bratislava Card
| wikidata=Q752582
| lastedit=2026-03-01
| content=Rococo Palace built 1768–1770. Today it hosts the Bratislava City Gallery.
}}
* {{see
| name=Palffy Palace | alt=Pálffyho palác | url= | email=
| address=Panská 19, 811 01 | lat=48.1421 | long=17.1073 | directions=
| phone=+421 949 002 147 | tollfree=
| hours=11:00–18:00, closed M | price=€8. Free entry with Bratislava Card
| lastedit=2026-03-01
| content=Rebuilt in the classical style in the 19th century by Count John Pálffy. Part of the Bratislava City Gallery.
}}
* {{see
| name=Academia Istropolitana | alt= | url= | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=The oldest historic university in the area, which is now occupied by the state of Slovakia, from the 13th century.
}}
* {{see
| name=Slovak National Theatre | alt=Slovenské národné divadlo | url= | email=
| address= Hviezdoslavovo square | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=The historic building of the Slovak National Theatre, built in 1886.
}}
* {{see
| name=Slovak Radio Building | alt=Slovenský rozhlas | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.154167 | long=17.114167 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=Slovak Radio Building | image=Upside down Pyramid, Bratislava 01.jpg | wikidata=Q7541547
| content=Its main building is a peculiar 60-m-high reversed pyramid from the communist era and a landmark in sharp contrast with the building of the Slovak National Bank just across the street.
}}

===Monuments===
[[File:Slavin memorial, Bratislava.jpg|right|thumb|Slavín]]
[[File:Ba-michalská brána.jpg|thumb|Michael's Gate]]

* {{see
| name=Slavín monument | alt= | url=http://bratislava-slovakia.eu/places/sightseeing/slavin | email=
| address= | lat=48.15278 | long=17.09988 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1553111
| content=On the top of the hill behind the castle, overlooking the entire city. This is a monument in memory of Soviet casualties in the liberation battle of Bratislava in World War II. It is the highest place in the city, and thus the best place for viewing the city. Slavin is a cemetery and thus rather quiet. On warm nights it's a very romantic place, allowing you to sit in the shadows of the monument and look at the traffic below. To get there, take trolleybus no. 203 from Hodžovo námestie (in front of the Presidential Palace) in the direction Búdková and get off in 9 minutes at the last stop, then walk 500 m along Stará vinárska and then Pažického streets. Slavin is near an embassy district.
}}
* {{see
| name=Roland Fountain | alt=Rolandova fontána | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.14335 | long=17.10814 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q4178866
| content=Built by stone cutter Andreas Luttringer and commissioned by Hungarian king Maximilian in 1527, this was the first fountain in Bratislava.
}}
* {{see
| name=Michael's Gate with Tower | alt=Michalská brána | url=https://muzeumbratislava.sk/en/michaels-tower | email=
| address=Michalská 22 | lat=48.14513 | long=17.10674 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 5443 3044 | tollfree=
| hours=10:00–18:00, closed Tuesdays | price=
| wikidata=Q1717975
| content=This 51-m-high tower above the gate with its green copper roof is one of the best known and the oldest buildings in Bratislava. It was built in the 14th century as one of the four gates to the city.
}}
* {{see
| name=Laurin's Gate | alt=Laurinská brána | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.143617 | long=17.110872 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q1870194
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Chatam Sofer Mausoleum | alt= | url=http://www.chatamsofer.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.14189 | long=17.09188 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikidata=Q4180493
| content=
}}
* {{see
| name=Jewish Cemetery, Jewish Community Museum and Bratislava Synagogue | alt= | url=http://www.synagogue.sk | email=
| address=Heydukova | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=The only synagogue in Bratislava.
}}

===Other sights===
* {{see
| name=SNP Bridge | alt=Most Slovenského národného povstania, called Nový most from 1993 to 2012 | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.13686 | long=17.10458 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=Entrance €6.50, but is free of charge if you eat in the restaurant
| wikidata=Q837291
| content=A bridge over the Danube river, with its flying saucer-shaped structure housing a restaurant called [http://bratislava-slovakia.eu/places/sightseeing/ufo-tower "UFO"]. There is an observation deck on its roof, open from 10:00-23:00 daily, offering great views of the old town, as well as the apartment blocks in Petržalka.
}}
* {{see
| name=Main Indoor Market | alt=Tržnica at Trnavské mýto | url= | email=
| address= | lat=48.15745 | long=17.12610 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}

===Sightseeing pass===
If you are visiting several attractions, you will be saving money by buying a Bratislava Card as this card is financially supported by the Slovak Ministry of Tourism and Sports to encourage tourism.

* {{see
| name=Bratislava Card | alt= | url=https://card.visitbratislava.com/discount/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=With unlimited public transportation: €30 for 24 hr, €36 for 48 hr, €39 for 72 hr. Without public transportation: €27 for 24 hr, €32 for 48 hr, €35 for 72 hr
| lastedit=2026-03-01
| content=This is very good value, particularly if visiting for more than 24 hours. You can purchase either a physical or digital card. Available for 24, 48 or 72 hrs. Time starts when you first use the physical card or activates the digital card in its app and expires at the end of the purchased duration (not calendar day). Includes free guided downtown walking tour. Free access to 23 museums and galleries around Bratislava region and discounts in some museums and restaurants. Price is reasonable and you are likely going to recoup the cost of the card on the first day just by doing the walking tour and two attractions.
}}

==Do==
{{mapframe|name=Map of the region around Bratislava}}
[[File:Bratislava Silvester 2006.jpg|right|thumb|Main Square during the New Year's Eve celebration, 2006]]
Take a stroll through the centre of the town. Bratislava has one of the smallest historical centers of any European capital but the charm is more concentrated. The streets have been completely renovated over the last ten years, bringing life back here. Since then a multitude of cafes, bars and restaurants of all kinds have opened here, accompanied by a few souvenir shops and fashion stores. On warm days almost every cafe has an outdoor seating section in the street, bustling with life and giving the city a unique cozy feeling.

When it comes to sightseeing, Bratislava Castle generally is a must and is already opened after the reconstruction. You can visit also '''[http://bratislava-slovakia.eu/places/sightseeing/slavin Slavin]''' memorial for some really astounding views of the city. It's a calm and romantic spot but beware, it can get really windy up there. The City Museum located in the '''Old Town Hall''' offers visitors climbing up the steep stairwells of the clock tower or seeing the town's historical dungeons, an exhibition that was quite outdated but still scary in 2008.

In summer, you can also visit '''[http://www.zoobratislava.sk/?home Bratislava Zoo]''', providing a nice walk between the animal enclosures, the latest addition being some rare white tigers. The facilities of the zoo are slowly being renovated to attract more visitors and the zoo is a favourite for families on sunny days. You can also go to the '''Botanical Gardens''' of Comenius University (Botanická 3, take tram X6 to stop Botanická záhrada) for quiet and peaceful strolls in this green space. There are also several lakes opened for bathing. The biggest and probably the most famous lake is called [https://www.bratislava-slovakia.eu/things-to-do/lakes/zlate-piesky '''Zlaté piesky'''] (Golden Lakes) or [https://www.bratislava-slovakia.eu/lakes/bager '''Vajnorské jazerá'''], known as Bager lake (the later is used for bating only unofficially).

For a relaxed afternoon in the '''park''', head either to Sad Janka Kráľa park (on the right bank of the river Danube and next to Aupark shopping centre), the oldest public park in central Europe, relax at the embankments on both sides of the river or head to Horský park (Forest Park) north off Slavin memorial for a civilized stroll through the forest. There's a small café here as well as a pub, the latter mostly populated by students from the nearby campus. For a more outdoorsy experience, hop on bus No 203/213 to Koliba and walk up to Kamzík (takes about 30 minutes uphill) or try the newly renovated facilities of Partizánska lúka and Snežienka, all with extensive '''picknicking areas''' and loads of fireplaces for grilling. The area is several kilometers long and you can either walk here from the terminal station of bus No 212 (Vojenska nemocnica) or take a bus to Patronka and use bus No 43 driving up the area and back every 15–30 minutes (depending on time of day/year as well as weather). Only cars with a permit can enter the area but there is a parking lot at the entrance, close to a bus stop. Snezienka's grass fields and the top of Kamzik hill are connected with a chairlift, operating Thursdays through Sundays and on holidays, the price for one ride being approx. €3.

In December, be sure to indulge in the scents and flavours of the traditional '''[https://www.bratislava-slovakia.eu/things-to-do/christmas-market Christmas Market]''' in front of Old Town Hall and on the Hlavné námestie (main square). The market - compared to the ones in Prague and Vienna - is smaller, but has a much friendlier, almost family-like atmosphere and feels much more traditional and less overtly commercialized than others in the region. The people of Bratislava love to meet here for a drink and a bite to eat; try the 'varene vino' (mulled wine).

* {{do
| name=Speedboats.sk | alt= | url=http://www.speedboats.sk/en/ | email=info@speedboats.sk
| address=Kúpeľná 6 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 903 610 716 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2015-04-27
| content=Enjoy the beautiful view of Bratislava and the surrounding nature of the river Danube during a Bratislava boat trip.
}}
*'''[http://www.befreetours.com Bratislava Free Tour]'''. Free walking tour covering the city's sights, culture &amp; history. Every day at 11:00 and 15:00.

=== Culture ===
Bratislava is the home of the world famous [http://www.filharm.sk/ Slovak Philharmonic Orchestra] so if you love '''classical music''', you should consider attending one of the concerts in the historic Reduta building. For more cultural indulgence, the [http://www.snd.sk/?home Slovak National Theatre] offers a wide selection on '''ballet, opera and theatre performances'''. Although most of the activities have been moved to a city-district-in-the-making on the banks of the Danube, some performances are still being held in the historical theatre building, which gives them a unique feeling but a higher price tag as well. The old theatre building is right in the middle of the city at Hviezdoslavovo námestie. The new theatre is accessible by bus No 88 from the Coach Terminal at Mlynske nivy (get off at Landererova) or by buses No 50, 70 and 78 (stop is called Wüstenrot). None of these stop directly at the theatre though, so you should count on a 5- to 10-minute walk from the bus stop to the theatre. You cannot miss the building as it is of unmistakably communist megalomaniac design covered in white marble. The entrance is facing the Danube so you need to walk around the building to get in.

=== Cultural events ===
* {{do
| name=International Film Festival Bratislava | alt= | url=http://www.iffbratislava.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia=International Film Festival Bratislava | wikidata=Q5860972
| content=Forever in December.
}}
*'''[http://comics-salon.sk/index.php?eng Comics-Salón]''' - An event dedicated to Japanese Anime &amp; Manga, Fantasy and Sci-fi and its fans, but not only them! Great atmosphere, friendly folk and lots of fun awaits you there. The roots of this event stretch back to 2004, when it was held for the first time. Now, once every year early in September [[Bratislava]] enjoys the rush of people from all over Europe to participate in this unique event.

===Music events===

* {{do
| name=The Uprising Music Festival | alt= | url=http://www.uprising.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=Smaller multigenre music festival. Yearly in the end of August in [[Bratislava]].
}}

===Sports===
* '''Football:''' The men's national soccer team play at Tehelné pole (capacity 22,500) 2 km northeast of city centre. [https://www.skslovan.com/ SK Slovan Bratislava] the leading club also play here in Slovak Super Liga, the top tier. 
* '''Ice hockey''' is the national sport of Slovakia. The local hockey team, [http://www.hcslovan.sk/en/ HC Slovan Bratislava], plays games frequently throughout each year beginning in September and concluding in the spring of the following year. Home games are played at [http://bratislava-slovakia.eu/places/hockey-stadium Ondrej Nepela Arena stadium], Odbojárov 9. Many Slovaks are passionate about both watching and playing ice hockey. The stadium can be reached easily by public transport.
* '''Adventure sports:''' A popular activity among locals and tourists especially during a stag party is [https://bratislavashootingclub.com/ target shooting in Bratislava]. For some extreme adventure in the pure nature Slovaks and visitors can try to [https://www.canoetrips.sk/ sail the river Small Danube in a canoe]. Water sports in general are among the most beloved sports activities with many successful sportsmen such as the Hochschorner brothers. Centrally located option for adventure is [https://theaxethrowing.com/en/bratislava/ axe throwing] with location on right bank of Danube.

===Meet people===

Over the last two decades, many foreigners have been moving to Bratislava to study and work at the many international companies that created new jobs. After work, many expatriates and their Slovak friends hang out at casual events where everybody speaks English and enjoys the evening together. For travelers to Bratislava, joining these usually free events is an excellent and fun opportunity to meet local people and learn from them about what one should see or do in Bratislava next day.

A few recommendations are:

'''Bratislava Language Exchange Meeting''', where people from different countries get together at tables and teach each other a foreign language.

'''[http://www.toastmasters.org/Find-a-Club/01174714-01174714 Toastmasters Club Bratislava]''', a speech club where people practice their public speaking skills.

'''Bratislava Expat Meetup''' and '''International Meetings''' for the more business-oriented crowd that seeks to expand their network while having a glass of Martini in a stylish sky bar.

'''International Students Parties''', where the foreign exchange students dance the night away and knock out their brains.

Upcoming events can be found in this '''[https://www.visitbratislava.com/event/ calendar of events]'''.

'''City Tours'''

* [https://bratislavacitytours.sk Bratislava City Tours] — Licensed tour operator offering guided day trips from Vienna to Bratislava, walking tours of Bratislava Old Town, and private city tours. Guided tours include Old Town walking tour, panoramic city tour by minivan, and Bratislava Castle. Tours operate year-round in English and German. Departure from Vienna Hauptbahnhof.

==Work==
Slovakia is a member of the European Union, therefore, any citizen of a European Union, European Economic Area country or Switzerland can work and live there without restrictions.

Qualified third nationals can get a work permit. This system still uses bribes.

For more information on working in the Slovak Republic, see [[Slovakia#Work]].

==Buy==
Tourists seeking duty-free goods should be warned to make their purchases before returning to the airport as duty-free goods available in the departure lounge are roughly double the cost of identical goods purchased in local supermarkets.

Shop in the large and expanding [https://www.bratislava-slovakia.eu/things-to-do/bratislava-shopping shopping centers]:

* {{buy
| name=Aupark | alt= | url=http://www.aupark.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.13293 | long=17.10766 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-10-22
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Polus City Center | alt= | url=http://www.polus.sk | email=
| address= | lat=48.16856 | long=17.13886 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-10-22
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Avion | alt= | url=http://www.avion.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat=48.1658 | long=17.1808 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-10-22
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Shopping Palace | alt= | url=http://www.shoppingpalace.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat=48.186 | long=17.1785 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-10-22
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Eurovea | alt= | url=http://www.eurovea.com/en/ | email=
| address= | lat=48.14011 | long=17.12403 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-10-22
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Central | alt= | url=http://www.central.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat=48.15715 | long=17.12982 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-10-22
| content=
}}

== Eat ==
[[File:paparazzi.jpg|thumb|The Paparazzo statue which stood in the Old Town until 2013 has been moved to Restaurant UFO.]]

'''Bryndzové halušky''' (small, spaetzle-like dumplings with sheep's cheese and topped with pieces of meat) is the national dish of Slovakia and recommended to try. Potent garlic soup (but perhaps not on a date) and Slovak white wine (due to its cooler climate, Slovakia's reds pale in comparison with some of Europe's other offerings), schnitzels, goulashes and other typically Central European foods. Fresh vegetables are more common here thanks to the large amount of land given over to agriculture.

In December, don't miss the '''Christmas market''' in front of the Old Town Hall. The traditional foods of the Christmas market are roasted pork or chicken sandwich burgers ("ciganska pecienka") with mustard and onions, potato pancakes ("loksa") with various fillings ranging traditionally from plain ones with goose fat, with garlic or goose liver to poppy seed, nut or chocolate. Bread with pork fat and onions is also popular. Also there are a few stands which offer specialities from other European countries. You can wash down the food with a cup of red or white mulled wine or a small cup of honey wine, also tea with or without rum is available, as well as grog or other "hot mixed drinks" like the Červený medveď (red bear).

There are a large number of restaurants in the center of Bratislava in all price ranges so there are plenty to choose from.

===Budget===

Bratislava's special form of junk food is '''richman''', a big bread roll filled with cabbage and cheese and/or meat with mayonnaise. Richman stands can be found on Kamenné námestie, in front of the Tesco building, and in Safarikovo square. You can also try a sub sandwich from one of the many cafeterias in the city. Another excellent cafeteria is on Zelená Ulica between Ventúrska Ulica and Hlavné námestie. A big sandwich, a '''bageta''' (from the French baguette) with cheese, ham and eggs would cost you about €1.50.

Another specialty in Bratislava (but also available in other regions of Slovakia) is '''treska'''. It is a cold salad made of cod (fish) with mayonnaise. There are also vegetables such as onions and carrots in the salad. It has a distinctive taste, somewhere between sour and bitter. You can buy it fresh in most "Lahôdky" shops, which means something like "delicacies", but generally stands for old-fashioned fast food shops which sell salads, soups, etc. Treska is very good with rolls. Can also buy it packed to take home.

If you want to '''self-cater''', the largest supermarket near the centre is the underground Tesco on Kamenné námestie ({{rint|tram}} Centrum).  You could easily have lunch consisting of a couple of bread rolls, ham, cheese, fruit and maybe a cake or two, for €3-4. New shopping malls with big cinemas and of course food courts within reach of the centre are '''Aupark''' on the right bank of the Danube (next to Sad Janka Kráľa park, some 10 minutes from St Martins's Cathedral), '''Eurovea''' (next to the old bridge on the old town bank of river, close to the bus station), '''Polus City Center''' on Vajnorská Street to the north of the city (some 10–15 minutes from the city by tram) and '''Bory Mall''' on the north-western edge of the city.

====In the city centre====
* {{eat
| name=Góvinda reštaurácia | alt= | url=https://www.govinda-bratislava.sk/ | email=
| address=Obchodná 518/30 | lat=48.14711 | long=17.11047 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 5296 2366, +421 911 947 108 (cell.) | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 10:30-16:00 | price=| lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=Hare Krishna-operated restaurant popular with vegans and very affordable.
}}
* {{eat
| name=KGB Krčma Gurmánov Bratislavy | alt= | url=http://kgbpub.sk/ | email=
| address=Obchodná 530/52 | lat=48.14800 | long=17.11167| directions=| lastedit=2022-05-01
| phone=+421 2 527 312 79 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-W 11:00-00:00, Th 11:00-01:00, F 11:00-02:00, Sa 16:00-02:00 | price=
| content=Communism-themed pub with high-quality beers and affordable prices.
}}
* {{eat
| name=U Sedliaka | alt= | url= | email=
| address=55, Obchodná 567 | lat=48.1485642 | long=17.1124898 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2024-08-20 | content=Good typical Slovak dishes and great background music. Nice atmosphere at affordable price.}}
* {{eat
| name=Olive Tree | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Vysoká 14 | lat=48.1487318 | long=17.1103387 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2022-05-01 | content=Good selection of Slovac cuisine}}

====Near the city centre====
* {{eat
| name=Divný Janko Reštaurácia | alt= | url=https://www.facebook.com/restauraciadivnyjanko/ | email=
| address=Jozefská 2991/2 | lat=48.15088 | long=17.10966 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 442 515 58 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-Th 11:00-23:00, F-Sa 11:00-00:00, Su 11:00-23:00 | price=| lastedit=2022-05-01
| content=Slovak and international dishes in a nice, retro ambience, the only downside is that the staff can be rude.
}}

===Mid-range===
Interestingly, it is rather hard to find a '''Slovak restaurant''' among all the Italian, Chinese, Mexican, Indian and other eateries.

* {{eat
| name=Slovak Pub | alt= | url=http://www.slovakpub.sk/en/ | email=rezervacie@slovakpub.sk
| address=Obchodná 62 | lat=48.14844 | long=17.11254 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 52926367 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia= | wikidata=
| lastedit=2024-08-21
| content=For good and reasonably priced halušky, the unique Slovak national meal, visit the Slovak Pub on Obchodna. This is a traditional eatery with a nice ambience. Portion size leans towards the small side. Not wheelchair accessible.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Flagship | alt= | url=https://bratislavskarestauracia.sk/ | email=
| address=Námestie SNP 8, 811 02 | lat=48.14603 | long=17.11014 | directions=
| phone=+421 917 927 673 | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-28
| content=Slovak national cuisine including halušky, in a converted theatre. Lacklustre service. Same company as Slovak Pub, who also own brewery Kláštorný pivovar, and café Franz Xaver Messerschmidt next door.
}}
* {{eat
| name=San Marten | alt= | url=http://www.sanmarten.sk/ | email=
| address=Panská 172/33 | lat=48.14148 | long=17.10569 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia= | wikidata=
| lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=San Marten is an Italian restaurant with great food and excellent service at affordable prices.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Bistro SOHO | alt= | url=https://www.facebook.com/soho.dunajska/ | email=
| address=Laurinská 141 | lat=48.14409 | long=17.11170 | directions=
| phone=+421 948 380 530 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-S 10:00-22:00 | price=
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=Asian fusion cuisine.
}}
* {{eat
| name=Mille Baci | alt= | url=http://www.millebaci.sk | email=ordine@millebaci.sk
| address=Námestie SNP č.1 | lat=48.14576 | long=17.11036 | directions=
| phone=+421 917 138 767 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
 | lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=Italian restaurant specializing in dishes from Veneto.
}}

===Splurge===
* {{eat
| name=UFO | alt= | url=http://www.u-f-o.sk/en/index.html  | email=
| address=Most SNP 1 | lat=48.1368316 | long=17.1046142 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia= | wikidata=
| lastedit=2022-08-01
| content=You can get a nice view and can meet some local celebrities at the übercool and very expensive UFO restaurant and disco on top of Nový most bridge.
}}
* {{eat
| name=ECK | alt= | url=https://www.eckrestaurant.com/  | email=
| address=K zlatému rohu 36, 841 10 Devín | lat=48.1738 | long=16.9951 | directions=About 5 miles west of the city centre
| phone=+421 911 513 387 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu–F 18:00–22:00| price=€150 for the tasting menu
| wikipedia= | wikidata=
| lastedit=2026-02-25
| content=Regarded as one of the best restaurants in Slovakia, bookings open two months in advance and sell out almost immediately.
}}

==Drink==
[[File:Hlavné námestie-The napoleonic soldier, Old Town Hall and Roland Fountain-Bratislava.JPG|right|thumb|Hlavné námestie (Main Square), Bratislava Old Town]]
Try '''Kofola''', a Slovak and Czech soft drink with a similar colour to Coca-Cola, but lower in sugar and caffeine (and carbonation). Some places serve "draft Kofola" which indeed is draft from a barrel in a way similar to beer (it used to be co-produced by a Bratislava brewery). Some Slovaks say draft Kofola is even better than the bottled version and that it is best enjoyed outside in the sun, for example after a hike or a bike or rollerblade ride. Kofola is a popular alternative to beer if you want to hang out but don't want to drink alcohol. '''Vinea''' is another genuine Slovak soft drink made from grapes, offered both in "white" (green grapes) and "red" varieties (red grapes) and even in a rather sweet and maybe not-so-tasty "soft" version without carbon dioxide.

There are quite a few Slovak beer brands, e.g. '''Zlatý Bažant, Šariš, Smädný Mních and Topvar'''. '''Stein''' beer is a local Bratislava variety which used to be brewed practically in the city centre. There are three micro-breweries offering beer in Bratislava, Mestiansky Pivovar, Richtar Jakub and Patronka.

If spirits are more your thing, perhaps you will enjoy '''Slivovica''', a fruit-plum brandy of high quality that is associated with Slovakia.

===Coffee===

* {{drink
| name=Čiary | url= | email=
| address=Laurinská 138/11, 811 01 
| lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= 
| hours=F–M 10:05–18:55; closed Tu–Th
| price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=grão | url= | email=
| address=Jesenského 194/12, 811 02 
| lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 944 294 763 | tollfree= 
| hours=M–F 08:00–19:00; Sa–Su 09:00–19:00
| price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Kaviareň Vták | url=https://www.kaviarenvtak.sk | email=
| address=Špitálska 2214/20, 811 08
| lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= 
| hours=M–F 08:00–17:00; Sa–Su 09:00–17:00
| price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=KOFI | url=https://www.kofi.sk | email=
| address=Karadžičova 4105/33, 811 08
| lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 905 372 561 | tollfree= 
| hours=M–F 07:30–17:30; Sa 09:30–15:00; closed Su
| price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=MONO | url= | email=
| address=1062, Budovateľská 1062/25, 821 08 
| lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= 
| hours=M–Th 08:30–15:00; closed F–Sa; Su 10:00–15:00
| price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Brew Bar Café 
| url=https://www.brewbar.sk | email=
| address=Rožňavská 1/A, 831 04 Nové Mesto 
| lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 918 411 737 | tollfree= 
| hours=M–F 07:30–19:00; Sa 08:00–16:00; closed Su
| price=
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=SVÄG TO GO | url= | email=
| address=Kozia 22, 811 03 
| lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 911 246 553 | tollfree= 
| hours=M–F 07:00–17:00; Sa 09:00–14:00; closed Su
| price=
| content=
}}

===Bars===
The best pubs offering Slovak beers can be found in the Old Town: Kristian in Michalska street or Bar Parada in Hviezdoslavovo square. All of them are quite cheap (about €1 per half-liter glass of beer). Obchodna street is also full of cheap bars targeting students and younger crowds, for example Baron and Starter (you can also smoke inside).

* {{drink
| name=BeAbout | url=http://www.beabout.sk | email=
| address=Presernova 4 | lat=48.148376 | long=17.10731 | directions=Vajanskeho nabrezie 10, near Safarikovo námestie
| phone=+421 948-050107 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Su-Th 10:00-00:00, F Sa 10:00-05:00 | price=
| content=Music club near the riverside popular with younger crowd. Good selection of beers including Belgian specialty beers.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Casa del Havana | alt= | url=http://www.havanacafe.sk/index.php?lang=en | email=havanacafe@havanacafe.sk
| address=Michalská 26 | lat=48.14498 | long=17.10686 | directions=
| phone=+421 910 797 222 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=11:00-02:00 mostly | price=
| content=A Cuban-style restaurant and bar near the centre of the Bratislava Old Town. Not very spacious, but has a comfortable terrace. Particularly famous for the mojito, which has been considered the best in Bratislava, if not in all Slovakia. Mojito €6.49.
}}
* {{drink
| name=UFO | url=http://www.u-f-o.sk | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| content=If you want to go for extraordinary, visit UFO. It looks like a cliché flying saucer and it's a high on the SNP Bridge (the member of great-towers.com), and you have to use a lift to go there. There is a good restaurant and lounge bar and observation deck. The view is incomparable.
}}
* '''[https://www.bukowski.sk/ Bukowski],''' Namestie SNP 24. Cozy bohemian bar with a nice courtyard next to Fuga Club. Drinks are cheap, beers at €2. 
* '''[https://www.bohemabar.sk/web/?dt_portfolio=project001 Bohema Bar]{{Dead link|date=January 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }},''' Namestie SNP 30. Similar to Bukowski, more upscale, very busy on weekends. Sometimes they play music with dj sets or live bands. Gin Tonic €4.10.

===Clubs===

Larger clubs in Bratislava include Luna Bar (entry only with passport) and [http://www.theclubbratislava.com/ The Club]. There are a few small underground clubs with electronic music, such as [http://fuga.forumabsurdum.sk/ Fuga] on Namestie SNP, Teleport at Michael's Gate and [http://www.mojaradost.sk/ Radost]{{Dead link|date=January 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} (very small but atmospheric) on Obchodná Street. Avoid places like Channels and Trafo where it's 90% men and bouncers are rude.

=== Gay and lesbian ===

* {{drink
| name=ruido.cafe
| url=http://www.ruido.cafe | email=
| address=Michalská 7, 811 03 Staré Mesto
| lat= | long= 
| directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Tu–Th 17:00–00:00, F–Sa 17:00–02:00,  Su 12:00–20:00
| price=
| content=Gay bar.
}}
* {{drink
| name=Apollon Gay Club
| url= | email=
| address=Panenská 24, 811 03 Staré Mesto 
| lat= | long= 
| directions=
| phone=+421 948 900 092 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=W–Th 21:00–01:00, F–Sa 21:00–04:00 
| price=
| content=Gay bar.
}}

==Sleep==
[[File:Castle Devin - walls and river.JPG|right|thumb|Danube River in Bratislava]]

Accommodation prices usually do not include city tax. For 2024 the city tax was €3.50/person/night for Old Town, 3.00€ for other districs. Students up to age 26 and youths up to 18 do not need to pay city tax.

===Budget===
*{{sleep
| name=Patio Hostel | alt= | url=https://www.patiohostel.com/ | email=
| address=Špitálska 35 | lat=48.147400 | long=17.114900 | directions=opposite Mariánska tram stop
| phone=+421 2 529 257 97 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-08
| content=Very popular, in the centre, close to the train &amp; bus stations, easily reachable from the airport. Dorms and privates, free Internet, parking lot, laundry.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hostel Chors | alt=Capsule &amp; NFT Boutique Hostel Bratislava | url=https://www.cho.rs/ | email=reservations@cho.rs
| address=Obchodná 43 | lat=48.148200 | long=17.111700 | directions=middle of the centre of Old City
| phone=+421 910 127 878 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-08
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Wild Elephants Hostel | alt= | url=https://elephants.sk/ | email=info@elephants.sk
| address=Františkánske námestie 413/8, 811 01 Staré Mesto | lat=48.146100 | long=17.109500 | directions=
| phone=+421 908 821 174 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-08
| content=Accommodations available for people aged 18-40 years old only.
}}

===Mid-range===
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Arcus | alt= | url=https://www.hotelarcus.sk/ | email=bratislava@hotelarcus.sk
| address=Moskovská 5 | lat=48.151400 | long=17.121300 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 5557 2522 | tollfree= | fax=+421 2 5557 6750
| checkin= | checkout=11:00 | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-08
| content=Nice family hotel, big rooms and bathrooms, fresh cooked breakfast.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Aston Business Hotel | alt= | url=http://hotelaston.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Boutique Apartments Possonium | alt= | url=https://www.possonium.sk/en | email=
| address=Šancová 20 | lat=48.155700 | long=17.109700 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 2072 0007 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-08
| content=Only 3 minutes by walk from Hlavna stanica (main railway station). Free breakfast, Wi-Fi, internet, free laundry, cosy bar, great chill out in the garden.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Downtown Bratislava Hotel | alt=Downtown Bratislava B&amp;B | url=https://us2.cloudbeds.com/en/reservation/3JyXub?currency=eur | email=
| address=Panenská 31 | lat=48.148200 | long=17.106000 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 5464 1191 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| lastedit=2026-02-08
| content=18 minutes' walk from the central station.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Bratislava | alt= | url=http://hotelaston.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Holiday Inn | alt= | url=http://www.holidayinn.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Ibis | alt= | url=https://all.accor.com/hotel/3566/index.en.shtml | email=
| address=Zamocka 38 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Double rooms from €48, in central location, just a short walk from the Old town.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Mercure Bratislava Centrum Hotel | alt= | url=https://all.accor.com/hotel/6840/index.en.shtml | email=
| address=Zabotova 2 | lat= | long= | directions=Hlavná stanica 400 m
| phone= | tollfree=
| checkin=14:00 | checkout=12:00 | price=From €55
| lastedit=2017-10-17
| content=Mid-scale business hotel (with aggressively modern decorations), a short walk from the main railway station. About 15–20 minutes’ walk from the old town, with frequent trams and buses available. Rate includes wired and wireless Internet access.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Saffron Hotel | alt= | url=https://www.hotelsaffron.sk/ | email=
| address=Radlinského 27, 811 07 
| lat=48.1528 | long=17.1176 | directions=
| phone=+421 2212 993 01 | tollfree=
| checkin=14:00 | checkout=11:00 | price=Around €100
| lastedit=2026-02-28
| content=Business Hotel, walking distance to the old town, or a 10 minute tram. Parking available for €12/day. Superb gym, which unfortunately is only open 10am–10pm.
}}

===Splurge===
* {{sleep
| name=Albrecht | alt= | url=https://www.hotelalbrecht.sk/ | email=
| address=Mudronova 82 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 672 000 91 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Design hotel with 12 rooms and suites nestled on hill above Bratislava castle and Old Town. The Albrecht features flagship restaurant and lounge bar as well as lavish urban spa - unique in Bratislava.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Arcadia | alt= | url=https://www.arcadia-hotel.sk/homesite/ | email=
| address=Františkánska 3 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 594 905 00 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Boutique hotel with heritage-style decor.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Devín | alt= | url=http://www.hoteldevin.sk/ | email=
| address=Riečna 4 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content= Traditional hotel with 100 rooms and suites in the historical centre of Bratislava, walking distance to all main attraction. It provides accommodation, restaurant, conference services and relaxation center with pool.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Gate One | alt= | url=http://www.hotelgateone.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=Business and conference hotel near airport.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Kempinski Hotel River Park | alt= | url=http://www.kempinski.com/bratislava | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=Directly overlooking the Danube.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Marroll's | alt= | url=http://www.hotelmarrols.sk/ | email=
| address=Tobrucka 4 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 57784600 | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Park Inn by Radisson Danube Bratislava | alt= | url=https://www.radissonhotels.com/en-us/hotels/park-inn-bratislava-danube | email=info.bratislava@rezidorparkinn.com
| address=Rybne Namestie 1 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 5934 0000 | tollfree= | fax=+421 2 5441 4311
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=Central location.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Perugia | alt= | url=http://www.perugia.sk/ | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content=Near the main square.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Radisson Blu Carlton Hotel, Bratislava | alt= | url=https://www.radissonhotels.com/en-us/hotels/radisson-blu-bratislava-carlton | email=reservation.bratislava@radissonblu.com
| address=Hviezdoslavovo nam 3 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 59390000 | tollfree= | fax=+421 (2) 5939 0010
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=In the heart of Bratislava, it has been fully renovated and retains many of its original features.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Sheraton Bratislava Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.sheratonbratislava.com/ | email=
| address=Pribinova 12 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content= In Bratislava's sophisticated new city center EUROVEA, the first Sheraton hotel in Slovakia offers 186 stylish guest rooms and 23 suites and Shine Spa - wellness center with indoor swimming pool, saunas, 24/7 gym and many different massages.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Falkensteiner Bratislava Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.falkensteiner.com/sk/hotel/bratislava | email=
| address=Pilarikova 5 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| price= | checkin= | checkout=
| content= Close to city centre, business hotel.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Beigli Hotel &amp; Garden | alt= | url=https://www.hotelbeigli.sk/ | email=
| address=Baštová 4, Staré Mesto | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 904 006 026 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=In the city center - no car access.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Hradná Brána | alt= | url=https://www.hradnabrana.sk/ | email=
| address=Slovanské nábrežie 15 | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2-601 025 11 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=
| content=First class hotel has a panoramic view over the Devín castle. It provides accommodation, restaurant, congressional and relaxation services.
}}

==Connect==

As of Sept 2021, Bratislava has 4G from O2, Orange and Swan, and 5G from Telekom. You might also get a signal from any of the Austrian or Hungarian carriers. Wifi is widely available in the city and establishments. City offers Wifi hotspots in some areas of downtown under the SSID name "VisitBratislava".

Similarly with mobile calls, check before dialling which country's network your phone is latched onto.

==Stay safe==
Bratislava is generally very safe by Western standards. It is quite small and the crime rate is low. There is a significant police presence in the city, especially the historical parts, and it is generally not a problem to walk around the city at night. The centre especially is under camera surveillance.

There is very little violent crime in Bratislava. Walking alone after midnight outside of the historical centre is not recommended on Fridays, since you could have an unpleasant encounter with rowdy drunks who could congregate around cheaper establishments. If a problem occurs, you can reach the police on phone number 158. General emergency number (police, fire dept., ambulance) can be reached by dialing 112.

Always ask for printed receipts in establishments to avoid being overcharged. Especially taxi drivers might try to do that. For reference, the usual fare is around €4 around the town, and you shouldn't be charged more than around €10 getting anywhere in Bratislava. Your best bet is to call a taxi dispatch or use one of the mobile apps (see above). Ask around for a recommendation in your hotel/hostel.

On pedestrian crossings without traffic lights, watch out for aggressive drivers. Some of them might not give you the right of way.

==Cope==

===Embassies===

*{{flag|Austria}} {{listing
| name=Austrian embassy | url=http://www.bmeia.gv.at/botschaft/pressburg.html | email=pressburg-ob@bmeia.gv.at
| address=Hodžovo námestie 1/A | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 593 015 | tollfree= | fax=+421 2 544 324 86
| hours=
}}
* {{flag|Finland}} {{listing
| name=Finland | url=http://www.finlandembassy.sk| email=sanomat.brt@formin.fi
| address=Palisády 29/A, 4. poschodie, 811 06 Bratislava | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2-5980 5111 | tollfree= | fax=+421 2-5980 5120
| hours=M-F 09:00-11:30 | price=
| content=
}}
* {{flag|Georgia}} {{listing
| name=Georgia | url=http://www.slovakia.mfa.gov.ge | email=bratislava.emb@mfa.gov.ge
| address=Michalska 9, 811 01 Bratislava 1 | lat=48.144706 | long=17.106673 | directions=
| phone=+421 2 5464 6484 | tollfree= | fax=+421 2 5464 6486
| hours= | price=
| content=
}}
*{{Flag|Poland}} {{Listing|name=Poland|alt=|url=http://bratyslawa.msz.gov.pl|email=bratyslawa.amb.sekretariat@msz.gov.pl|address=Paulínyho 7, 814 91 Bratislava|lat=|long=|directions=|phone=+421 2 59490211|tollfree=|fax=|hours=|price=|wikidata=|lastedit=2019-08-24|content=}}
* {{flag|Romania}} {{listing
| name=Romania | alt= | url=http://bratislava.mae.ro/en | email=bratislava@mae.ro
| address=Fraňa Kraľa 11, Staré Mesto | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+421 2 207 27 147 | tollfree= | fax=+421 2 207 27 547
| hours=M-F 9:00-17:00 | price=
| lastedit=2021-12-03
| content=
}}
* {{Flag|Spain}}{{Listing|name=Spain|url=https://www.exteriores.gob.es/Embajadas/bratislava/es/Paginas/index.aspx|email=emb.b​ratislava@maec.es|address=Prepoš​tská 10, 811 01 Bratislava|phone=+421 2 5441 57 24|fax=+421 2 432 917 27|hours=M-F 09:00 - 15:00|lastedit=2023-04-09}}
*{{Flag|United Kingdom}} {{Listing|name=United Kingdom|alt=|url=https://www.gov.uk/world/organisations/british-embassy-bratislava|email=britishembassybratislava@fco.gov.uk|address=Panská 16, 811 01 Bratislava|lat=|long=|directions=|phone=+421 2 5998 20 00|tollfree=|fax=+421 2 5998 22 37|hours=|price=|wikipedia=|wikidata=|image=|content=}}

==Go next==
* The castle [https://hradcervenykamen.sk/?lang=en Červený kameň] is located about 30&amp;nbsp;km north-east of Bratislava; it can be reached by bus from Mlynske Nivy bus terminal.
* Do like the locals and hike in the Small Carpathians mountain range. Bratislava lies on the southeast slopes of these mountains. Hiking routes are well indicated.
* Visit the [[Small Carpathians Wine Region]]; on the southern slopes of the Small Carpathians there are extensive vineyards and typical wine villages and towns like [[Rača]], [[Pezinok]] or [[Modra]]. If you are more interested in local wines, follow the Little Carpathians Wine Route.
* Visit Cachtice castle, associated with the blood-thirsty deeds of countess Bathory. It is a large and picturesque ruin set on a hilltop above the small village of Visnove. Take the train north from Bratislava to Nove Mesto nad Vahom (75 minutes), and then change to a small local train for the short journey west to Visnove (15 minutes).
* The [[Mutenice Wine Region|Mutěnice Wine Region]] near the Slovak border in the [[Czech Republic]] is well worth a weekend visit. It has some of the best wine in the Czech Republic and many great small cellars to visit.  You'll need to take a train to [[Breclav|Břeclav]] and then from there to [[Hodonin|Hodonín]].
* Take the train to [[Trencin|Trenčin]] (one hour and forty minutes), a Slovak town to the north of the capital with a towering hill-top castle and a picturesque old town centre spread out below it.
* The [http://www.carnuntum.co.at Carnuntum archaeological park] is located 25&amp;nbsp;km from Bratislava, across the [[Austria]]n border. The site offers the chance to see the excavations of an ancient Roman city. It is worth a one-day visit together with a stop in the old walled city of Hainburg, the first major town in Austria after crossing the Slovak border.
* [[Lednice-Valtice]] in the south-eastern corner of the Czech Republic is a [[UNESCO World Heritage]] site containing one of Europe's largest Palacial parklands.
* [[Senec]] is a small town 30&amp;nbsp;km to the west of Bratislava, with the lake resort "Slnečné jazerá" ("Sunny Lakes"). It is a cool place to swim or relax at the beach in the summer months.
* You can use the bus no. 91 of the public transport company of Bratislava (DPB) going to Čunovo in order to cross between Rajka (Hungary) and Bratislava (Slovakia). In Bratislava, the bus has Nový most as its terminus, and near the Hungarian border you get on/off at the stop Čunovské jazerá (you need to signal to the driver if you plan to get off at this stop). From Čunovské jazerá it's a four-kilometer-long straight walk through a flat terrain to the town of Rajka, two kilometers on each side of the border. You may detour to visit a monument at the Austrian-Hungarian-Slovakian three country border.
* The public transport company of Bratislava (DPB) runs a cross-border bus line no. 901 between Hainburg an der Donau (Austria) and Bratislava (Slovakia), with a stop also in the Austrian town of Wolfsthal. In Bratislava, the terminus is the stop Nový most. Note that even though the bus stops at Einsteinova street before crossing the border, it is not possible to alight until reaching Wolfsthal.
* Surrounding major/capital cities [[Vienna]] ([[Austria]]), [[Budapest]] ([[Hungary]]), [[Brno]]/[[Prague]] ([[Czech Republic]]) are easily accessible by inter-state buses and trains.

{{routebox| placename=Bratislava 
| image1=EV 6 Atlantic Ocean to Black Sea.svg
| imagesize1=30
| directionl1=W
| majorl1=[[Vienna]]
| minorl1=
| directionr1=E
| majorr1=[[Budapest]]
| minorr1=[[Gyor]]
| link1=[[ EuroVelo cycling routes]]
| caption1= 
}}


{{usablecity}}
{{geo|48.143889|17.109722}}
{{isPartOf|Western Slovakia}}</text>
      <sha1>qyh765c1dvfnxh84zuynuzcc6qs10wq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
