<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikivoyage</sitename>
    <dbname>enwikivoyage</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.46.0-wmf.23</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikivoyage talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="1728" case="first-letter">Event</namespace>
      <namespace key="1729" case="first-letter">Event talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mullerthal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>151555</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4931740</id>
      <parentid>4922686</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-09-01T12:55:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>2253620</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 0 sources and tagging 1 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.9.5</comment>
      <origin>4931740</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9932" sha1="jsythnacyd32m4tvigjpn8qt6n6q6tn" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Mullerthal Wikivoyage Banner.jpg}}

[[File:Bridge in Mullerthal.jpg|thumb|300px|Bridge over a small stream in Mullerthal]]
'''Mullerthal''' (Luxembourgish: ''Mëllerdall'') is a natural region in eastern [[Luxembourg]]. It is commonly referred to as ''Luxembourg's Little Switzerland''. Its biggest city is [[Echternach]], and the region consists of the same area as the canton of Echternach.

==Cities and towns==
{{mapframe|49.785|6.385|zoom=11}}
{{mapshape|wikidata=Q720221}}
* {{Marker|type=city |lat=49.835 |long=6.289 |zoom=12 |name=[[Beaufort (Luxembourg)|Beaufort]] |image=}}, small town with a large castle and its own liqueur.
* {{Marker|type=city |lat=49.823 |long=6.351 |zoom=12 |name=[[Berdorf]] |image=}}, small town with the Hohllay (Hollow rock) as its main feature.
* {{Marker|type=city |lat=49.780 |long=6.338 |zoom=12 |name=[[Consdorf]] |image=}}, small town with ~1.200 citizens. 
* {{Marker|type=city |lat=49.812 |long=6.422 |zoom=12 |name=[[Echternach]] |image=}}, the oldest settlement in Luxembourg, founded in 698.
* {{Marker|type=city |lat=49.785 |long=6.218 |zoom=12 |name=[[Larochette]] |image=}}, small commune with a large castle as its main feature

==Other destinations==
[[File:Berdorf (LU), Hohllay -- 2015 -- 6408.jpg|thumb|''Hohllay'' (Hollow rock) near Berdorf]]
&lt;div style="column-count:4;-moz-column-count:2;-webkit-column-count:4"&gt;
* ''Bech''
* ''Bourglinster''
* ''Boursdorf''
* ''Christnach''
* ''Dickweiler''
* ''Dillingen''
* ''Eppeldorf''
* ''Girst''
* ''Haller''
* ''Herborn''
* ''Junglinster''
* ''Medernach''
* ''Mompach''
* ''Nommern''
* ''Osweiler''
* ''Reisdorf''
* ''Rosport''
* ''Stegen''
* ''Wolper''
* ''Zittig''
&lt;/div&gt;

==Understand==
[[File:04-05-31_M%C3%BCllertal_Lxb_02.jpg|thumb|Schéissendëmpel]]
The Mullerthal is a region filled with nature. If you have ever visited [[Switzerland]], then the region's nickname should give you a fair idea of what you'll find in the Mullerthal: Nature, sloping terrain and beautiful panoramas. You'll also find an abundance of hiking and cycling trails and routes. 
The Mullerthal covers about the same area as the canton of Echternach does. Occasionally cities as [[Diekirch]] are counted as part of Mullerthal, but generally speaking the Mullerthal is the same as the canton of Echternach, with, surprisingly, [[Echternach]] as its biggest city.

==Get in==
===By car===
Assuming you're travelling from [[Luxembourg City]], head for the A7, which can be reached by using the A1 in the direction of [[Trier]] ([[Germany]]). Shortly after joining the A7, turn onto the E29 (rue d'Echternach) heading for Echternach. This road will take you to Echternach directly.
When travelling from [[Frankfurt am Main]], use the [[File:Bundesautobahn_60_number.svg|frameless|25px|Autobahn 60]], followed by the [[File:Bundesautobahn_61_number.svg|frameless|25px|Autobahn 61]], followed by the [[File:BE-E42.svg|frameless|25px|European route 42]]. At the Bitburg interchange, head onto the [[File:European_Road_29_number_DE.svg|frameless|25px|European route 29]] heading for [[Bitburg]]. Once having reached Bitburg, stay on the E29 and head for Echternach.

When travelling from the north of Germany, use the [[File:Bundesautobahn_1_number.svg|frameless|25px|Autobahn 1]] to go south. Once having reached the end of the A1 at exit 114, take a right onto the Bundesstraße 51/E29. Once having reached Bitburg (exit 6) on the [[File:Bundesautobahn_60_number.svg|frameless|25px|Autobahn 60]], head onto the [[File:European_Road_29_number_DE.svg|frameless|25px|European route 29]] heading for Echternach.

===By bus===
There are direct buses to Echternach from both [[Trier]] and Luxembourg city.

==Get around==
Mullerthal can be travelled both by car, bicycle or foot. Bicycle paths have been built throughout most of the region, and more are being built to this day. Bicycles themselves can be rented at one of the many RentaBike locations around the region. At least one can be found in every town. For long distances, however, a car may be more helpful if you want to visit, for instance, a tourist attraction. Furthermore, many hiking trails are found throughout the region.

==See==
[[File:Lac_D%27Echternach,_AUG2016.jpg|thumb|Lac d'Echternach]]
The natural beauty of the Mullerthal region is breathtaking, with on the one side the Mullerthal forest with sights such as the '''Schéissendëmpel''' a picturesque waterfall, the '''Hohllay''', a hollow rock near Berdorf, once used to get millstones and the '''Beaufort castles''', some of which are no more than ruins, but others are well-maintained and open for visits. 

The Mullerthal features the city of [[Echternach]] on the other hand, which features several '''museums''' on the city's past in Christianity, a mostly intact '''city wall''' with housing built into the towers, and has several '''festivals''' to its name, the biggest of which being the ''E-Lake Festival'' held annually by the ''Lac d'Echternach''. Other man-made sighs include the '''Aquatower''' in [[Berdorf]]. It features a panorama deck at 55 meters high, giving you a good view of the Mullerthal.

==Do==
[[File:Waldbillig_(LU),_Tal_der_Schwarzen_Ernz_--_2015_--_4499.jpg|thumb|Mullerthal Hiking Trail markings]]
[[File:Rue d'Echternach, Consdorf.jpg|thumb|Two cyclists by the church in Consdorf]]
The Mullerthal is a region best fit for '''outdoor sports''' such as [[Hiking in the Mullerthal|Hiking]] and [[Cycling in the Mullerthal|Cycling or Mountain biking]]. Sports however, aren't the only thing to do in the Mullerthal. There are several '''festivals''' to attend as well as '''sightseeing''', which can be combined with hiking or mountain biking, though it can very well also be done by car.

==Buy==

==Eat==
[[File:Rue de Luxembourg, Consdorf.jpg|thumb|Rue de Luxembourg in Consdorf with the church on the left and a restaurant on the right]]
The Mullerthal region has a lot of regional products, varying from sausages to cheese to liqueur. For a full list of these products and where to get them, see [http://www.mullerthal.lu/en/eat-stay/regional-products the Mullerthal website]{{Dead link|date=September 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}.

==Drink==
The castle of Beaufort makes its own liqueur; ''Cassero''. It can be bought in local produce shops, such as the bakery in Consdorf, but of course it can be bought in Beaufort as well.

==Connect==
* {{listing
| name=Beaufort Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.beaufort-tourisme.lu | email=
| address=87 Grand Rue, L-6310 Beaufort | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 83 60 99-301 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=8:00-12:00, 13:00-17:00 on weekdays, 8:00-20:00 in July and August | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-17
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Berdorf Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.berdorf-tourist.lu | email=
| address=3 Beim Maartbësch, L-6550 Berdorf | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 79 05 45 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-17
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Consdorf Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.campconsdorf.lu | email=
| address=35 Rue Burgkapp, L-6211 Consdorf | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 79 02 71 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-17
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Echternach Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.echternach-tourist.lu | email=
| address=9-10 Parvis de la Basilique, L-6486 Echternach | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 72 02 30 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-17
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Larochette Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.larochette.eu | email=
| address=33 Chemin J.A. Zinnen, L-7626 Larochette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 83 70 38, +352 83 76 76 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-17
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Reisdorf Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.reisdorf.lu | email=
| address=Rue de la Sûre, L-9390 Reisdorf | lat= | long= | directions=in the former train station
| phone=+352 83 67 78 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Available from the beginning of June to mid-way August | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-17
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Rosport Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.rosport-tourism.lu | email=
| address=L-6580 Rosport | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 73 01 60 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-17
| content=
}}

==Stay safe==
* Stay safe when exploring a hiking or mountain bike trail. Even though they are well maintained an accident can occur at any moment. Wear the right shoes when hiking, and stay on the trail at all times. There are drops of a good 30 meters that are poorly visible, even from five meters distance. When cycling, always look around before crossing a big road and listen whether or not you hear any traffic approaching, as the trails occasionally cross major roads, with cars driving at speeds up to 90 km/h.
* When travelling by car or any other motorised vehicle, look out for other vehicles cutting corners by driving on the wrong side of the road. They aren't frequent, but be sure to not cut corners yourself, and be aware that some road users cut corners, especially motorbikers.

==Go next==
From the Mullerthal, [[Germany]] is quite close-by, specifically:
* [[Trier]], the oldest city in Germany, dating back to Roman times.
* [[Bitburg]], German town with beer and scenery to offer.
If you'd like to stay in Luxembourg, however, why not head for places such as
* [[Diekirch]], city with beer and a museum on the Second World War.
* [[Luxembourg City]], The country's picturesque capital. Historically being an unconquerable fortress, any tourist can conquer the city in modern times.
* [[Vianden]], a delightful historic town with a stunningly restored medieval castle, spectacularly situated on a rock high above town.

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}
{{usableregion}}
{{geo|49.795|6.406|zoom=11}}</text>
      <sha1>jsythnacyd32m4tvigjpn8qt6n6q6tn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Category:Mullerthal</title>
    <ns>14</ns>
    <id>151612</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3036549</id>
      <timestamp>2016-08-19T21:23:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Traveler100</username>
        <id>79350</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created page with "{{RegionCat}}  {{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}"</comment>
      <origin>3036549</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="38" sha1="it7f7rx56fms9iby72lvw8g4fk8acym" xml:space="preserve">{{RegionCat}}

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}</text>
      <sha1>it7f7rx56fms9iby72lvw8g4fk8acym</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Land of the Red Rocks</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>151627</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4951018</id>
      <parentid>4949649</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-10-07T09:44:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>2253620</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 0 sources and tagging 1 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.9.5</comment>
      <origin>4951018</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="31398" sha1="b518sbt1l6u2feb5fotw1blf96242dt" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Land of the Red Rocks Wikivoyage Banner.jpeg|pgname=Land of the Red Rocks}}

[[File:Nature reserve Brucherbierg-Lallengerbierg 2013-08 --3.jpg|thumb|300px|The Land of the Red Rocks is, as its name would imply, known for its rocks, which are red due to high quantities of iron ore]]
The '''Land of the Red Rocks''' (French: ''Région Terres Rouges''), also known as the '''Esch-sur-Alzette canton''', is the southwestmost region of [[Luxembourg]].

==Understand==
The Land of the Red Rocks, also known as the Esch-sur-Alzette Canton, is a former mining region in southern Luxembourg that is filled to its brim with industrial heritage.

The name ''Land of the Red Rocks'' comes from the reddish iron ore that was found and extracted from the ground in high amounts. The growth the region experienced during the 1900s can still be seen in numbers: Six of the ten biggest cities and towns of Luxembourg are located in the ''Land of the Red Rocks''.

==Get in==
{{mapframe|height=300|width=500}}
{{mapshape|wikidata=Q188283}}
===By car===
The A13 services the entire canton, starting at Pétange, combining with the A4 near Esch-sur-Alzette to continue eastward as the A13 again in the direction of [[Mondorf-les-Bains]]. After passing the German border, the Autobahn 8 connects to [[Saarlouis]], [[Neunkirchen]] and [[Homburg]].

====From Luxembourg City====
The Land of Red Rocks can be accessed via three main highways when travelling from [[Luxembourg City]], namely the A3, which links up to the A13 near Dudelange, the A4, which connects to Esch and the E44, which connects to Pétange.

====From Belgium====
Coming from Belgium, use the E25 (when travelling from [[Liège]] or the E411 (when traveling from [[Namur]]) to head for Luxembourg, but before the border, at exit 32, turn right onto the N81. When the road turns into the A28, take the first exit (Pétange), and take a left onto the N88. Ater the border crossing, you will find yourself on a roundabout in the west of Pétange. Turning left here will get you onto the E44/A13, which connects to the rest of the canton. Alternatively, the A6 can be used to get to Luxembourg City, followed with the E44, A4 or A3 as described above. This does however result in a longer route.

====From France====
When travelling from France, first get to [[Metz]] or [[Thionville]], from which you take the A31 heading north. Not long after crossing the border you will find yourself at the ''Croix de Bettembourg'', from which you can turn left onto the A13 heading for Esch-sur-Alzette to connect to the entire canton.

===By train===
Most of the region is covered in railway tracks, most of which service(d) the mines. The bigger cities such as {{marker|name=Dudelange|type=go|lat=49.4834 | long=6.0832|image=GareDiddeleng.JPG}}, {{marker|name=Esch-sur-Alzette|type=go|lat=49.4939 | long=5.9855|image=Gare_Esch-Alzette_2011.jpg}}, {{marker|name=Differdange|type=go|lat=49.5226 | long=5.8916|image=GareDéiferd01.jpg}} and {{marker|name=Pétange|type=go|lat=49.5539 | long=5.8781|image=Gare Péiteng vu vir.jpg
}} can easily be accessed by rail. Trains from [[Luxembourg City|Luxembourg]] to [[Nancy]] (and vice versa) both stop in {{marker|name=Bettembourg|type=go|lat=49.5161 | long=6.1014|image=Beetebuerger_Gare.jpg}}, from where the entire canton can be reached.

==Get around==
While all of the cities can easily be explored on foot, getting from one city of town to another usually takes a long time and a lot of effort. If you still want to see the best parts of the region while hopping between places, then use a mountainbike. The region is filled with cycling routes and dedicated cycling lanes and roads (''pistes cyclable''), most of the touristic routes will go off-road.

The best way to get around quickly is by either car or train. You will be able to easily drive from one city over to another via the highway network, which is one of the densest in Luxembourg. Trains service only the most important cities and some of the towns in between them. They connect directly to Luxembourg City and [[Namur]] (Belgium). Alternatively, most of the heritage railways listed ''[[Land of the Red Rocks#Do|here]]'' connect several towns and cities. Using them as a daily way of travel may get expensive, though visiting just one town for a day using the heritage rail network may very well be a welcome addition to your visit.

==See==
[[File:Belval_aus_der_Loft.JPG|thumb|Aerial view of the Rockhal in Esch surrounded by industrial heritage.]]
* {{see
| name=Centre d'Art Nei Liicht / Dominique Lang | alt= | url=http://www.galeries-dudelange.lu | email=
| address=25 Rue Dominique Lang, L-3505 Dudelange | lat=49.48255 | long=6.08584 | directions=
| phone=+352 51 61 21 29 2 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=Free
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=Two joint museums in the town of Dudelange focused on showing and facilitating access to modern art for the people of Dudelange, and provide a platform for up and coming local artists.
}}
* {{see
| name=National Resistance Museum | alt= | url=http://www.musee-resistance.lu | email=
| address=Place de la Résistance, L-4041 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.49240 | long=5.97605 | directions=
| phone=+352 54 84 72 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Tuesday-Sunday: 14:00-18:00 | price=Free entrance
| image=LUX Esch-Alzette 020 2016 - Musee de la Resistance.jpg
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=The National Resistance Museum traces the history of Luxembourg from 1940 to 1945. There is also an exhibition of the Nazi concentration camps and the treatment of Luxembourg Jews.
}}
* {{see
| name=Parc Merveilleux | alt=Parc Bettembourg | url=http://www.parc-merveilleux.lu | email=
| address=Route de Mondorf, L-3260 Bettembourg | lat=49.5107 | long=6.1198 | directions=Use the A13 heading for exit 8. Head towards Bettembourg and turn right onto National Road 13. The park will be to your left as soon as you've passed underneath the A3.
| phone=+352 51 10 48 1 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Easter until early October | price=
| wikidata=Q2392584| wikipedia=Parc Merveilleux | image=Eingang Park Bettembourg 01.jpg
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=The Parc Merveilleux is an amusement park just east of Bettembourg in the south of Luxembourg. Designed above all for children, the park has a wide range of attractions including exotic birds, animals in their natural habitats, a pony ranch, a miniature railway, children's self-drive cars, adventure playgrounds, scenes from fairy tales, a restaurant and a cafeteria.
}}

==Do==
[[File:2011-05-01_steam_loc_energie_507_and_railcar_551669_(former_german_VT_95_painted_in_belgian_color_scheme)_at_Fond-de-Gras_station_(Luxemburgisch_heritage_railway_Train_1900).jpg|thumb|Steam locomotive 507 at Fond-de-Gras railway station]]
The Land of the Red Rocks is not only covered in rocks, rich in iron, but is also covered in railway tracks built to transport the mined iron to smelting works. Some of these have been converted into [[heritage railways]], namely:
* {{do
| name=Train 1900 | alt=Fond de Gras | url=http://www.train1900.lu | email=
| address=Fond-de-Gras, L-4676 Niederkorn | lat=49.5349 | long=5.8577 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 50 41 24 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Pétange to FdG: 14:15, 16:15, 18:15. FdG--Pétange: 13:30, 15:30, 17:30. Available from May to the last Sunday of September | price=
| image=Train 1900 - Ready to departure from Fond de Gras.jpg
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=A touristic steam train between Fond-de-Gras and Pétange
}}
* {{do
| name=Train 1900 | alt=Pétange | url= | email=
| address=Route de Niederkorn, L-4762 Pétange | lat=49.5535 | long=5.8770 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| image=Luxemburg train 1900 1.jpg
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=
}}
* {{do
| name=''Minièresbunn'' | alt= | url=http://www.minettpark.lu | email=
| address=Rue Principale, L-4640 Lasauvage | lat=49.5271 | long=5.8380 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=From Fond-de-Gras: 14:45, 15:00, 16:00 and 17:00. Available from May to the last Sunday of September | price=
| image=Bâtiments minière Dhoil 01.jpg
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=Narrow gauge track connecting Fond-de-Gras with Lasauvage. The track goes through the abandoned mine galleries.
}}
* {{do
| name=Musée National des Mines de Fer Luxembourgeoises | alt=National Museum of the Luxembourgian Iron Mines | url=http://www.mnm.lu | email=
| address=26 Rue de la Bruyere, L-3714 Rumelange | lat=49.46082 | long=6.02292 | directions=
| phone=+352 56 56 88 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| image=Musée National des Mines.jpg
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=Small museum on local mining activities and a guided tour through the mines. Entry to which is serviced by a narrow-gauge railway. The tour guides speak mostly Luxembourgish and French, translations are available in the form of audio guide, which is available in Dutch, English, French, German.
}}
* {{do
| name=Circular hikes and tours | alt= | url=https://www.redrock.lu/en/things-to-do/hiking | email=
| address= | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree=
| hours= | price=
| wikipedia= | wikidata=
| lastedit=
| content=
}}
The region also houses a major nature reserve, large zoo and large swimming pool, all of which can be found around Esch.
* {{do
| name=''Ellergronn'' nature reserve | alt= | url=http://www.centresnatureetforet.lu | email=
| address=Rue Jean-Pierre Bausch, L-4114 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.4737 | long=5.9763 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 54 42 1 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| image=Liegeois-Weier Ellergronn Esch-Alzette 2012-04.JPG
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=Expositions and guided viewings
}}
* {{do
| name=Escher Déirepark-Gaalgebierg | alt= | url=http://www.deierepark.lu | email=
| address=Rue du Stade, Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.4833 | long=5.9859 | directions=
| phone=+352 27 54 37 50 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=Large terrain with sport-infrastructure, playgrounds, animal park, rosary and waterfall.
}}
* {{do
| name=''Bains du Parc'' indoor pool and sauna | alt= | url=http://www.lesbainsduparc.lu | email=
| address=1 Place des Sacrifiés 1940-1945, L-4115 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.49981 | long=5.97744 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 53 13 53 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* '''Football:''' [https://www.csfola.lu/home CS Fola Esch]{{Dead link|date=October 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} play soccer in the National Division, the country's top tier. Their home ground is Stade Émile Mayrisch (capacity 7800) south side of Esch-sur-Alzette city. [https://www.f91.lu/home F91 Dudelange]{{Dead link|date=October 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} or Diddeleng also play in National Division at Stade Jos Nosbaum, capacity 2500.

==Buy==
===Malls===
[[File:LUX Esch-Alzette Belval 037 2016.jpg|thumb|Belval Plaza]]
The region offers just one mall, which are rare in Luxembourg. Aside from ''Belval Plaza'', another mall can be found in [[Mersch]], about 30-40 minutes from Esch-sur-Alzette when travelling by car.
* {{buy
| name=Cine &amp; Shopping-Center ''Belval Plaza'' | alt= | url=https://belvalshopping.lu/ | email=
| address=Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.5010 | long=5.9448 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}

===Supermarkets===
While malls are limited in the area, supermarkets are found in much higher quantities. The major chains have shops throughout the region, though mostly located in and around the major cities.
* '''Aldi''' - German discount supermarket
** {{buy
| name=Aldi | alt=Bascharage
| address=Avenue du Luxembourg, L-4950 Bascharage | lat=49.5614 | long=5.8987 | directions=
| phone=+352 50 59 69 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=8:30-19:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Aldi | alt=Dudelange
| address=Route du Luxembourg, 3515 Dudelange | lat=49.4952 | long=6.0863 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=8:30-19:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Aldi | alt=Esch-sur-Alzette
| address=59 Rue d'Audun, L-4018 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.4891 | long=5.9769 | directions=
| phone=+352 54 36 36 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=8:30-19:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Aldi | alt=Foetz
| address=Rue du Brill - Zone Commerciale, L-3898 Foetz | lat=49.5200 | long=6.0108 | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=8:30-19:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
* '''Carrefour''' - French hypermarket
** {{buy
| name=Carrefour | alt=Esch-sur-Alzette
| address=5-7 Rue de l'Alzette, L-4011 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.4961 | long=5.9856 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 53 03 23 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=07:00-20:00 (-18:30 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
* '''Cactus''' - Luxembourgian supermarket
** {{buy
| name=Cactus | alt= Bascharage
| address=6 Avenue de Luxembourg, L-4950 Käerjeng | lat=49.5606 | long=5.9002 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 50 50 1 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=08:00-20:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Cactus | alt=Esch-sur-Alzette/Lallange
| address=136 Rue de Luxembourg, L-4222 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.5048 | long=5.9888 | directions=
| phone=+352 55 14 14 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=08:00-20:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Cactus | alt=Kayl
| address=Rue Principale, L-3612 Kayl | lat=49.4803 | long=6.0418 | directions=
| phone=+352 28 28 90 15 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=08:00-20:00
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Cactus | alt=Pétange
| address=1 Rue Pierre Grégoire, L-4702 Pétange | lat=49.5558 | long=5.8675 | directions=
| phone=+352 28 28 90 18 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=08:00-20:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
* '''Delhaize''' - Belgian supermarket
** {{buy
| name=Delhaize | alt=Differdange
| address=19 Rue du chemin de Fer, L-4556 Differdange | lat=49.5246 | long=5.8916 | directions=
| phone=+352 58 46 44 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=07:30-19:00 (closed on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Delhaize | alt=Dudelange
| address=12 An Hinnefen, L-3491 Dudelangen | lat=49.4795 | long=6.0906 | directions=
| phone=+352 27 51 03 71 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=07:30-20:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Delhaize | alt=Esch-sur-Alzette (Located at Belval Plaza)
| address=14 Avenue du Rock'n'Roll, L-4361 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.5020 | long=5.9456 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 57 89 13 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=07:30-20:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
* '''Match''' - Hungarian supermarket (part of Delhaize)
** {{buy
| name=Match | alt=Dudelange
| address=75 Rue du Commerce, L-3450 Dudelange | lat=49.4771 | long=6.0830 | directions=
| phone=+352 52 07 61 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=08:00-20:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Match | alt=Esch-sur-Alzette
| address=29 Rue de Moedling, L-4246 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.5103 | long=5.9567 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 17 98 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}
** {{buy
| name=Match | alt=Livange
| address=Rue de Bettembourg, L-3378 Livange | lat=49.5319 | long=6.1245 | directions=
| phone=+352 51 95 27 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=08:00-20:00 (-13:00 on Sundays)
| lastedit=2017-06-10
}}

==Eat==
* {{eat
| name=Stella Rosa | alt= | url= | email=
| address=273 Rue Metzerlach, L-4441 Soleuvre | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 59 39 02 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=W-Su 12:00-14:00, 18:00-22:00, | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Moustache | alt= | url=http://www.moustache.lu | email=
| address=52 Grand-Rue, L-4132 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 53 02 90 | tollfree=
| hours=Tu-F 12:00-0:00, Sa 18:30-00:00, Su 12:00-0:00 | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Brasserie K116 | alt= | url=http://www.k116.lu | email=
| address=116 r. de Luxembourg, L-4221 Esch an der Alzette, | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 17 59 74 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Restaurant le Pavillon | alt= | url=http://www.pavillon.lu {{dead link|August 2018|December 2020}} | email=
| address=Rue du Stade, L-4142 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 54 02 28 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=12:00-14:00, 18:00-22:30 | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Restaurant Postkutsch | alt= | url=http://www.postkutsch.lu | email=
| address=8 Rue Xavier Brasseur, L-4040 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 54 51 69 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=Tu-F 12:00-23:00, Sa 18:00-23:00, Su 12:00-15:00 | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Dimmi Si | alt= | url=http://www.dimmisi.lu | email=
| address=12 Avenue du Rock'n'Roll, L-4361 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 54 33 33 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=11:45-14:30, 17:45-23:00 | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Happy House | alt= | url=http://www.happyhouse.lu | email=
| address=68 Rue Emile Mark, L-4620 Differdange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 58 15 86 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Villa Hadir | alt= | url=http://www.villa-hadir.lu | email=
| address=51 Rue Emile Mark, L-4620 Differdange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 58 02 15 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Lagano | alt= | url=http://www.lagano.lu {{dead link|December 2020}} | email=
| address=67 Grand-Rue, L-4575 Differdange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 58 22 04 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Asia Garden | alt= | url=http://www.asiagarden.lu | email=
| address=13 Rue Jean-Baptiste Gillardin, L-4735 Pétange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 50 35 28 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Restaurant Annapurna | alt= | url=http://www.anpurn.lu | email=
| address=13 Rue de la Reconnaissance Nationale, L-4936 Pétange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 50 01 79 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Restaurant Kathmandu | alt= | url=http://www.restaurantkathmandu.lu | email=
| address=29 Rue Jean Jaurès, L-3490 Dudelange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 51 64 09 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{buy
| name=Antica Bari - Ristorante Pizzeria | alt= | url=http://www.anticabari.com | email=
| address=28 Rue de la Fontaine, L-3470 Dudelange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 51 07 32 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{eat
| name=Les 3 amis | alt= | url= | email=
| address=4734, 33 Avenue de la Gare, L-4734 Pétange | lat=49.55422 | long=5.87756 | directions=
| phone=+352 50 71 12 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=
}}

==Drink==
* {{drink
| name=Café Belami | alt= | url=http://www.belami.lu {{dead link|December 2020}} | email=
| address=135 av. d'Oberkorn, L-4640 Differdange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 26 58 38 01 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 09:00-00:00; Sa-Su 09:00-02:00 | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-02
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Coyote Café | alt= | url=http://www.coyote.lu | email=
| address=10-12 Avenue du Swing, L-4367 Belvaux | lat=49.50247 | long=5.94128 | directions=
| phone=+352 42 85 86 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Bar/Lounge/Café La Strada | alt= | url= | email=
| address=2 Rue de Belvaux, L-4025 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.50034 | long=5.97698 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 55 06 17 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Amadeus Bar | alt= | url= | email=
| address=23 Rue de l'Église, L-4106 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.49785 | long=5.98174 | directions=
| phone=+352 53 23 70 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Café Casablanca | alt= | url= | email=
| address=110 Rue de l'Alzette, L-4010 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.49294 | long=5.97820 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 53 18 34 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=
}}
* {{drink
| name=Café du Parc | alt= | url= | email=
| address=1 Rue du Parc, L-4771 Pétange | lat=49.55720 | long=5.87799 | directions=
| phone=+352 50 41 72 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-03
| content=
}}

==Sleep==
{{sleeppricerange|Under €65|€65–90|Over €90}}

===Budget===
Budget hotels in the region are mostly located where travellers wouldn't normally go. Some of them will be distanced from the highways, located some ways out from the cities. Changing your travel routes to end up in cheaper hotels that are just as decent as mid-range hotels might end up being rewarding.
* {{sleep
| name=Hôtel-Restaurant de la Frontière | alt= | url=http://www.hoteldelafrontiere.lu {{dead link|December 2020}} | email=
| address=52 Robert Schuman Strooss, L-5751 Frisange | lat=49.5064 | long=6.1926 | directions=Located on the south side of exit 10 (Frisange) of the A13, meters before the border crossing into France. The hotel is best to use when travelling from or to the [[Grevenmacher]] district.
| phone=+352 23 61 51 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€55
| lastedit=2017-06-04
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Logis Hotel Cottage Dudelange | alt= | url=http://www.logishotels.com | email=
| address=Rue Auguste Liesch., Dudelange | lat=49.4799 | long=6.0804 | directions=
| phone=+352 52 05 91 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€64
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}

===Mid-range===
* {{sleep
| name=Threeland Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.hotelthreeland.lu | email=
| address=50 Rue Pierre Hamer, Pétange | lat=49.5576 | long=5.8671 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 50 80 0 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€85
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=4-star hotel
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel-Restaurant Gulliver | alt= | url=http://www.gulliver.lu | email=
| address=58 Rue Nicolas Meyers, L- 4918 Käerjeng | lat=49.5563 | long=5.8971 | directions=
| phone=+352 50 44 55 1 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€86
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=3-star hotel
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Ibis Luxembourg Sud | alt= | url=http://www.accorhotels.com | email=
| address=Rue de Turi, L-3378 Livange | lat=49.53223 | long=6.11136 | directions=Located on the west side of exit 2 (Livange) on the A3.
| phone=+352 26 52 01 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€89
| lastedit=2017-06-04
| content=
}}
===Splurge===
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel de la Poste | alt= | url=http://www.hoteldelaposteluxembourg.com | email=
| address=107 Rue de l'Alzette, L-4011 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.4927 | long=5.9781 | directions=
| phone=+352 54 00 18 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€92
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Logis Hotel Acacia | alt= | url=http://www.logishotels.com | email=
| address=10 Rue de la Libération, L-4210 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.4931 | long=5.9803 | directions=
| phone=+352 54 10 61 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€99
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=3-star hotel
}}
* {{sleep
| name=Hotel Ibis Esch Belval | alt= | url=https://all.accor.com/hotel/7071/index.en.shtml | email=
| address=Avenue du Rock n Roll, 12, L-4361 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.5011 | long=5.9467 | directions=
| phone=+352 26 17 31 | tollfree=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€109
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=3-star hotel.
}}
* {{sleep
| name=The Seven Hotel | alt= | url=http://www.thesevenhotel.lu | email=
| address=50 Galgebierg (rue du stade), L-4142 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat=49.4869 | long=5.9851 | directions=
| phone=+352 54 02 28 | tollfree= | fax=
| checkin= | checkout= | price=€115
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=4-star hotel
}}

==Connect==
===Tourist Offices===
Whenever you need information on the region, visit tourist offices. They will be the best places to get your information from people that know what they are talking about.
* {{listing
| name=Esch-sur-Alzette Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.esch.lu/tourisme | email=
| address=Place du l'Hôtel de Ville, L-4138 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 54 16 37 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 09:00-17:00 During summers: M-Sa 09:00-17:00 | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-18
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Differdange Tourist Office | alt= | url=http://www.stadhaus.lu | email=
| address=38 Avenue Charlotte, L-4530 Differdange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 58 77 1-1900 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Pétange Tourist Information | alt= | url=http://www.petange.lu | email=
| address=Place J-F Kennedy, L-4760 Pétange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone= | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Dudelange Tourist Office | alt= | url=http://www.dudelange.lu | email=
| address=Plade de l'Hôtel de Ville, L-3401 Dudelange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 51 61 21-1 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2016-08-20
| content=
}}

===Post offices===
All post offices in the region can be found [http://www.post.lu/en/particuliers online]. Post Luxembourg offers, aside from typical mail-related items, a wide range of telecom solutions. May you be in need of for instance a Luxembourgian SIM-card for cheaper data and phone calls in the country, your solution is as easy as browsing their site or visiting one of their many offices, located in most every town.
* {{listing
| name=Bureau des Postes Bettembourg | alt= | url= | email=
| address=8 Rue de l'Indépendance, L-3238 Bettembourg | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 51 12 31 21 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 08:00-12:00, 13:30-17:15 | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Bureau des Postes Rumelange | alt= | url= | email=
| address=1 Place Grande-Duchesse Charlotte, L-3710 Rumelange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 56 50 31 21 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Bureau des Postes Esch-Lallange | alt= | url= | email=
| address=5 Boulevard Pierre Dupong, 4086 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 800 28 004 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 13:30-17:00 | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Bureau de Poste Esch-sur-Alzette | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Rue Zénon Bernard/Rue Xacier Brasseur, L-4030 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 800 28 004 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 07:00 - 17:00, Sa 09:00 - 18:00 | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Bureau des Postes Pétange | alt= | url= | email=
| address=13 Avenue de la Gare, L-4734 Pétange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 800 28 004 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours=M-F 08:00-12:00, 13:30 - 17:00| price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}

===Emergencies===
[http://www.police.public.lu/fr/index.html Luxembourgian Police] (''Police Grand-Ducale'') can be reached on phone number {{phone|113}}. Their offices are found in the bigger cities. In case of medical help, phone {{phone|112}}. Hospitals are found in Esch-sur-Alzette and Niederkorn. Almost all major cities and town have a drug store (''Pharmacie'') for the non-severe cases.
* {{listing
| name=Police Bettembourg | alt= | url= | email=
| address=33 Rue de l'Indépendance, L-3238 Bettembourg | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 24 46 12 00 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Police Esch Sud | alt= | url= | email=
| address=104 Boulevard J.-F. Kennedy, L-4171 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 24 45 82 00 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Police Esch Nord | alt= | url= | email=
| address=46 Rue du N, L-4260 Esch-sur-Alzette | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 24 45 42 00 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Police Dudelange | alt= | url= | email=
| address=30 Rue Jean Wolter, L-3544 Dudelange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 24 46 22 00 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Police Pétange | alt= | url= | email=
| address=Place du Marché, L-4756 Pétange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 24 45 62 00 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}
* {{listing
| name=Police Mondercange | alt= | url= | email=
| address=10 Rue de Reckange, L-3943 Mondercange | lat= | long= | directions=
| phone=+352 24 45 52 00 | tollfree= | fax=
| hours= | price=
| lastedit=2017-06-11
| content=
}}

==Go next==
* [[Luxembourg City]], the only {{Unesco}} in the country is Luxembourg's old quarters and fortifications. The city can easily be reached via the highway or rail network.
* [[Echternach]], the oldest town of the country, being founded in the 7th century. The city is filled with historical heritage and is surrounded by the beautiful landscapes of the [[Mullerthal]].
* [[Namur]] (Belgium), the capital of the [[Wallonia]] region, located along the river Meuse, which can be reached effortlessly by train.
* [[Metz]], [[Nancy]] and [[Strasbourg]] are all French cities worth visiting and they too are reached easily by train via the capital.
* [[Vianden]], a delightful historical town and one of Luxembourg's biggest tourist attractions, featuring a wonderfully restored medieval castle.

{{routebox
| image1=Luxemborg - Autostrasse 3.png
| imagesize1=
| directionl1=N
| majorl1=[[Luxembourg (city)|Luxembourg]]
| minorl1=''Bettembourg''
| directionr1=S
| majorr1=[[Nancy]]
| minorr1=[[Metz]]
| link1=
| caption1=Autostrasse 3

| image2=Luxemborg - Autostrasse 4.png
| imagesize2=
| directionl2=NE
| majorl2=[[Luxembourg (city)|Luxembourg]]
| minorl2=
| directionr2=SW
| majorr2=''Esch-sur-Alzette''
| minorr2=
| link2=
| caption2=Autostrasse 4

| image3=Luxemborg - Autostrasse 13.png
| imagesize3=
| directionl3=W
| majorl3=''Pétange''
| minorl3=''Esch-sur-Alzette''
| directionr3=E
| majorr3=[[Saarbrücken]]
| minorr3=[[Mondorf-les-Bains]]
| link3=
| caption3=Autostrasse 13

| image4=E44 Luxembourg.svg
| imagesize4=
| directionl4=W
| majorl4=[[Le Havre]]
| minorl4=[[Amiens]]
| directionr4=E
| majorr4=[[Giessen]]
| minorr4=[[Trier]] → [[Koblenz]]
| link4=
| caption4=European Road E44

| image5=BSicon BAHN.svg
| imagesize5=
| directionl5=N
| majorl5=[[Luxembourg (city)|Luxembourg]]
| minorl5=''Bettembourg''
| directionr5=S
| majorr5=[[Nancy]]
| minorr5=[[Metz]]
| link5=
| caption5=Intercity and TGV trains

| image6=BSicon BAHN.svg
| imagesize6=
| directionl6=W
| majorl6=[[Arlon]]
| minorl6=''Pétange'' ← ''Differdange''
| directionr6=E
| majorr6=[[Luxembourg (city)|Luxembourg]]
| minorr6=''Esch-sur-Alzette''
| link6=
| caption6=CFL Intercity train
}}

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}
{{guideruralarea}}
{{geo|49.510|5.993}}</text>
      <sha1>b518sbt1l6u2feb5fotw1blf96242dt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Moselle Valley (Luxembourg)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>157007</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5244326</id>
      <parentid>4085102</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-26T15:21:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Andyrom bot</username>
        <id>235382</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* By boat */ Bot: "listing | type=X" -&gt; X</comment>
      <origin>5244326</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9331" sha1="1xa557x9y627cw3eqsjp3jmtcugk00h" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Moselle_District_Wikivoyage_Banner.jpg}}
:''For other places with the same name, see [[Moselle Valley]].''
The '''Moselle Valley''' is one of five regions of [[Luxembourg]], located along the eastern border with [[Germany]].

==Cities==
{{mapframe|height=350}}
{{mapshape|wikidata=Q836002,Q691781}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Grevenmacher]]|lat=49.6786|long=6.4422|wikidata=Q215826}} — capital of the region.
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Mondorf-les-Bains]]|lat=49.5073|long=6.2828|wikidata=Q798747}} — An old [[spa towns|spa town]] and the only larger destination not located along the Moselle river.
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Remich]]|lat=49.5459|long=6.3662|wikidata=Q734284}} — Former Roman settlement that over time turned into the town it is today.
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Schengen]]|lat=49.466667|long=6.366667|wikidata=Q183841}} — Signing place of the [[Schengen Agreement]].
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Wasserbillig]]|lat=49.7147|long=6.5019|wikidata=Q1026497}} — City on the merging point of the Sûre (Sauer) into the Moselle.
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Wormeldange]]|lat=49.6113 | long=6.4057}}

==Understand==
The Moselle Valley is the most eastern territory of Luxembourg, bordering Germany on the other side of the Moselle river. The region lends itself to the cultivation of wines, which is why the hills will be filled with vineyards.

==Get in==
[[File:Schëlter_op_der_N10.jpg|thumb|N10 near Wasserbillig.]]
===By car===
The N10 road runs along the Moselle and Sauer rivers, and connects nearly all of the cities along the eastern Luxembourgian border together. When travelling from [[Thionville]] or [[Metz]], the road is marked as the D654, which connects to the A31/E25 at Illange. North of the Moselle Valley the N10 connects to the [[Mullerthal]] after following the same road as the N1 between [[Grevenmacher]] and [[Wasserbillig]]. The N10 passes straight through [[Echternach]], then passes by [[Vianden]], only to end near [[Clervaux]]. Other routes through the region are the A1, which connects [[Luxembourg City]] with [[Trier]] via Grevenmacher, and the A13, which connects [[Esch-sur-Alzette]] with [[Merzig]] and [[Saarbrücken]] via [[Mondorf-les-Bains]] and [[Schengen]].

===By public transit===
[[File:CFL_2306_-_Wasserbillig_-_2016.jpg|thumb|CFL train crossing over the Moselle into Germany.]]
While none of the cities have a proper train station themselves, on the German side of the Moselle, a train link exists, connecting Perl (Schengen), Nennig (Remich), Wellen (Grevenmacher) and Oberbillig (Wasserbillig) with Trier. This line's services terminate at the border tripoint.
The CFL Line 30 runs through the northern part of the region via Mertert and Wasserbillig and connects Luxembourg City with Trier and [[Schweich]] across the border. This line roughly passes by Luxembourg-Findel airport. The nearest station to the airport is Cents-Hamm

Bus services run between Luxembourg City and Remich via Mondorf-les-Bains (177) and Schengen (185). Remich connects to Grevenmacher via line 450, which connects to Luxembourg City (135) and Echternach (485).

===By boat===
Schengen shares a harbor with Remich, {{go|name=Port de Schwebsange|url=http://www.camping-port.lu/|price=[http://www.camping-port.lu/fr/Tarifs-du-port-0324 €10 and over]|lat=49.5102|long=6.3639}}, located in between both towns, near Schwebsange. Mertert does have a harbor, but this is an industrial port, which offers no service to recreational boats or yachts.

==Get around==
The N10 makes it easy to get around the region by car, but it is highly recommended that, given if you have the time, you rent a bike instead. Especially during the summer this is a highly recommended mode of transport, as you will get to see more of the region than if you were to go by car. In the Moselle Valley ''[http://www.entente-moselle.lu/fr/rentabike/presentation Rentabike Miselerland]'' is the most popular company when it comes to renting a bike. They can be found in Wasserbillig, Mertert, Flaxweiler, Grevenmacher, Ehnen, Remich, Schwebsange, Remerschen and Schengen. Regular bicycles go for €12 per day. You would pay €5 more if you'd rather have a mountainbike, or €8 more should you prefer an e-bike. You'd save the €12 should you have purchased a ''[http://www.visitluxembourg.com/en/luxembourg-card Luxembourg Card]''.

==See==
* Though Luxembourg has many '''beautiful castles''' on offer, the Moselle Valley only have one prominent castle, being the [[w:Schengen Castle|Schengen Castle]].

{{panorama|image=Junglinster_with_transmitters_2016-07.jpg|width=850px|caption=View over Junglinster}}

==Do==
[[File:Schengen_-_panoramio_(3).jpg|thumb|The Schengen castle.]]
[[File:Mondorf-les-Bains, the Centre thermal.jpg|thumb|Water fixture by the entrance of the Mondorf spa.]]
* As mentioned previously, the region is perfect for '''cycling'''. If you don't have a bicycle available, you best bet would be checking up with ''[http://www.entente-moselle.lu/fr/rentabike/presentation Rentabike Miselerland]'', which has a handful of locations in towns along the river Moselle.
* Besides cycling, '''hiking''' is also a popular activity. Mertert, for one, has a route circumnavigating the town.
* Visit the '''Mondorf Spa''', which make Mondorf-les-Bains Mondorf-les-Bains, as without them, it would simply be called Mondorf(!)
* Besides a spa, Mondorf also has the only casino in the area, '''Casino2000'''.
* Some of the '''vineyards and wine cellars''' in the region are open to give visitors a tour, occasionally with a wine tasting included.
* Aside from the wine-related tours in the region, places like Schengen have their own city tours, and the same goes for Wintrange.

==Eat==

==Drink==

==Stay safe==
* Though the region borders the Moselle River and seen that it is notable in nearly all parts of the region, it is highly ''discouraged'' to go for a '''swim in the river''', as it is actively used by shipping vessels. The currents caused by these ships can be very misleading. When you do not have your feet on the riverbed, you can easily get pulled in towards the rotors with all consequences involved.

==Go next==
===Nearby places within Luxembourg===
* [[Land of the Red Rocks]] — The mining region of Luxembourg, which gives the region its industrial character. The region is, however, focusing more and more on tourism, offering tours of former mines, making heritage railways out of old industrial railways, whilst also housing ''the'' university city of the country, Esch-sur-Alzette, which brings a lively nightlife to the city.
* [[Central Luxembourg]] — The more business-side of the country, revolving mostly around the capital, [[Luxembourg City]]
* [[Mullerthal]] — Also known as ''Luxembourg's Little Switzerland'' due to its stunningly beautiful terrain. The region is located around [[Echternach]], which is the oldest city of Luxembourg. The city's basilica contains the crypt of Saint Willibrord.

===Nearby places across the border===
* [[Trier]] — The oldest town of Germany, being founded during Roman times, is located not far downstream.
* Bordering the Moselle Valley is [[Saarland]], a small federal state by German terms, but in contrast about the size of Luxembourg as a whole. The ''compact'' state holds natural wonders to behold and quite a bit of interesting heritage.

{{routebox
| image1=Autoroute 1 (Luxemburg) number.png
| imagesize1=
| directionl1=W
| majorl1=[[Luxembourg City]]
| minorl1=[[Luxembourg-Findel Airport]]
| directionr1=E
| majorr1=[[Trier]]
| minorr1=[[Grevenmacher]]
| link1=
| caption1=Autoroute 1

| image2=Autoroute 13 (Luxemburg) number.png
| imagesize2=
| directionl2=W
| majorl2=[[Esch-sur-Alzette]]
| minorl2=[[Mondorf-les-Bains]]
| directionr2=E
| majorr2=[[Saarbrücken]]
| minorr2=[[Schengen]]
| link2=
| caption2=Autoroute 13

| image3=E29 Luxembourg.svg
| imagesize3=
| directionl3=N
| majorl3=[[Cologne]]
| minorl3=[[Echternach]] ← [[Luxembourg City]]
| directionr3=S
| majorr3=[[Sarreguemines]]
| minorr3=[[Remich]]
| link3=
| caption3=

| image4=Route nationale française 10.svg
| imagesize4=
| directionl4=N
| majorl4=[[Schengen]]
| minorl4=[[Grevenmacher]]
| directionr4=S
| majorr4=[[Clervaux]]
| minorr4=[[Echternach]]
| link4=
| caption4=

| image5=BSicon BAHN.svg
| imagesize5=
| directionl5=W
| majorl5=[[Luxembourg City]]
| minorl5=[[Luxembourg-Findel Airport]]
| directionr5=E
| majorr5=[[Trier]]
| minorr5=[[Mertert]]
| link5=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CFL_Line_30
| caption5=CFL Line 30

| image6=Deutsche_Bahn_AG-Logo.svg
| imagesize6=
| directionl6=S
| majorl6=[[Schengen]]/Perl
| minorl6=
| directionr6=N
| majorr6=[[Trier]]
| minorr6=[[Grevenmacher]]/Wellen
| link6=
| caption6=Deutsche Bahn: Elbling-Express

| image7=
| imagesize7=
| directionl7=
| majorl7=
| minorl7=
| directionr7=
| majorr7=
| minorr7=
| link7=
| caption7=

| image8=
| imagesize8=
| directionl8=
| majorl8=
| minorl8=
| directionr8=
| majorr8=
| minorr8=
| link8=
| caption8=

| image9=
| imagesize9=
| directionl9=
| majorl9=
| minorl9=
| directionr9=
| majorr9=
| minorr9=
| link9=
| caption9=

| image10=
| imagesize10=
| directionl10=
| majorl10=
| minorl10=
| directionr10=
| majorr10=
| minorr10=
| link10=
| caption10=
}}

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}
{{usableregion}}
{{geo|49.639|6.389|zoom=10}}</text>
      <sha1>1xa557x9y627cw3eqsjp3jmtcugk00h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Éislek</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>157009</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5011597</id>
      <parentid>4782126</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-25T15:26:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Procrastineur49</username>
        <id>2293928</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Nearby places across the border */</comment>
      <origin>5011597</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="7180" sha1="sh2k7n73tzymasbj4v5gnvfg333hcmw" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Pafemillen_banner.jpg}}
[[File:District_DiekirchLocatie.png|thumb|250px|1. Clervaux, 2. Diekirch, 3. Redange, 4. Vianden, 5. Wiltz]]
'''Éislek''' in the Ardennes hills, is the northernmost part of [[Luxembourg]]. 

==Cities==
{{mapframe|49.959|6.025|zoom=9}}
{{mapshape|wikidata=Q691842,Q691793,Q835980,Q845600,Q550021}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Clervaux]]|lat=50.055|long=6.025|wikidata=Q836075}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Diekirch]]|lat=49.866|long=6.167|wikidata=Q16050}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Ettelbruck]]|lat=49.846|long=6.102|wikidata=Q659351}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Redange]]|lat=49.765|long=5.888|wikidata=Q687100}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Troisvierges]]|lat=50.118|long=5.998|wikidata=Q24454}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Vianden]]|lat=49.934|long=6.207|wikidata=Q836082}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Wiltz]]|lat=49.967|long=5.933|wikidata=Q741589}}

==Other destinations==
* {{marker|type=vicinity|name=[[Esch-sur-Sûre]]|lat=49.911|long=5.935|wikidata=Q986392}}

==Understand==
Not only filled with stunning terrain dotted with countless panoramic points, but also full of well-preserved and restored castles giving the region a medieval look and feel, Éislek is definitely a must-see. The region can easily be explored via one of many hiking or biking trails.

==Get in==
[[File:Lac_de_la_Haute_Sure_-_panoramio.jpg|thumb|Lake of the Upper Sûre.]]
===By car===
The most notable roads in the region are the E421, N12 and N15. The first of which runs from the northern tip of the region to [[Colmar-Berg]], where it links to the A7 heading for [[Luxembourg City]]. The road passes by [[Clervaux]], [[Bourscheid]], [[Diekirch]] and [[Ettelbruck]]. The N12 connects the same northern tip of the region to ''Luxembourg City'', though it does so via [[Witz]], [[Esch-sur-Sûre]] and [[Redange]]. The N15 connects [[Ettelbruck]] with [[Bastogne]], crossing the N12 near Esch-sur-Sûre. Additionally, the N10 connects to the E421 near Clervaux, from which it connects to [[Vianden]], [[Echternach]], which allows access into the [[Mullerthal]], and continuing towards [[Wasserbillig]], which is the road's gate to the [[Moselle Valley (Luxembourg)|Moselle or Grevenmacher District]].

===By public transport===
The '''train''' network in the region consists of one main line and several branches of it. These branches connect to most of the notable destinations. The line, CFL line 10, runs from [[Luxembourg City]] to [[Liège]]. The line connects to [[Mersch]] and [[Colmar-Berg]] in Central Luxembourg, and to [[Ettelbruck]] and [[Clervaux]] in the Ardennes. [[Wiltz]] can be accessed by train via the branch at ''Kautenbach'', [[Diekirch]] via the branch at Ettelbruck and [[Troisvierges]] via the branch at ''Maulusmuhle''. '''Buses''', most of which stop at the major stations listed above, connect to all other destinations.

==Get around==
Some tourist offices, campsites and hotels rent out push bikes and mountain bikes should you not have one. The prices tend to differ. A map of these rental locations can be found [http://www.visitluxembourg.com/nl/map?themes%5B0%5D=503&amp;luxcard=0 here]{{Dead link|date=January 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }}. Travel between cities and towns is made easy by intercity buses, as well as the network of national roads consisting of the N10, N12 and N15, as well as the E421, which mostly offers easy travel from north to south and vice versa. Travel from east to west and vice versa will have to do without these national roads.

==See==
[[File:0_Clervaux_101021_CH5.JPG|thumb|Inner courtyard of the Clervaux Castle]]
* '''[http://www.steichencollections-cna.lu/eng/collections/1_the-family-of-man The Family of Man]''', a collection of 503 photographs by 273 artists from over 58 countries has been travelling the globe since 1955. After having toured over 150 museums, it was permanently housed in the [[Clervaux]] castle in 1994, where it remains to this day. Since 2003 the collection has been a part of the UNESCO 'Memory of the World' register.
* '''Many castles''' are spread throughout the region, the most notable and popular of which is the '''[[Vianden]] castle'''. Others include [[Bourscheid]] and [[Esch-sur-Sûre]]. Additionally, some castles have failed to stand the test of time, though some, such as the Brandenbourg Castle, consist of only '''castle ruins''' with can be toured regardless. 
* '''The [http://www.naturpark-our.lu/index.php?id=1;lang=en Our] and [http://www.naturpark-sure.lu/index.php?id=1;lang=en Upper-Sûre] nature parks''' are a great demonstration of the untouched nature found in the region.
* '''Museums''' are also found throughout the region, though [[Diekirch]] has the most notable, such as the ''National Conservatory of Historical Vehicles'' and the ''National Museum of Military History''.
* Some towns are worth visiting because of their general atmosphere, such as '''[[Esch-sur-Sûre]]''', which only counts a few hundred inhabitants, yet its location in a narrow loop of the river Sûre with a castle in the center, gives it a fantastically beautiful appeal.

==Do==
[[File:Vianden_10.JPG|thumb|Overview of Vianden and its namesake castle]]
* The terrain in the region's countryside is filled with rock formations as you'll most likely have never seen before, making the marked hiking trails in the region to be considered the most beautiful trails of Luxembourg. A new network of high-quality trails called [https://www.visit-eislek.lu/explore-nature/eislek-pied Éislek Pied] can be enjoyed across the region.
* '''The lake of the Upper Sûre''' (''Lac de la Haute Sûre'') has been created with the dam near Esch-sur-Sûre. The lake's surroundings have been adapted for tourism, featuring sporty activities such as kayaking on or off-road cycling around the lake.

==Eat==

==Drink==

==Stay safe==
* The terrain can be misleading, especially when outside of the urban parts of the region. Stay on the trails when hiking or cycling.

==Go next==
===Nearby places within Luxembourg===
* [[Central Luxembourg]] — The more business-side of the country, revolving mostly around the capital, [[Luxembourg City]]
* [[Mullerthal]] — Also known as ''Luxembourg's Little Switzerland'' due to its stunningly beautiful terrain. The region is located around [[Echternach]], which is the oldest city of Luxembourg. The city's basilica contains the crypt of Saint Willibrord.

===Nearby places across the border===
* [[Luxembourg_(Belgium)|Luxembourg]] — Though it doesn't particularly sound like this is across the border, Luxembourg is also a region in [[Wallonia]], [[Belgium]]. The region is in many ways like the Éislek, though it does have Wallonia's somewhat industrial character. The region on the other hand, is the most sparsely populated region of the Benelux and features cities such as [[Arlon]] and [[Bastogne]].
* [[Rhineland-Palatinate]], specifically the [[Eifel_(Rhineland-Palatinate)|Eifel]] can be found on the other side of the river Our featuring most notably [[Bitburg]], known for its beer which is popular in Luxembourgian regions bordering Germany.

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}
{{usableregion}}
{{geo|49.959|6.025|zoom=10}}</text>
      <sha1>sh2k7n73tzymasbj4v5gnvfg333hcmw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Central Luxembourg</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>157016</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5255020</id>
      <parentid>4649524</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-05T18:44:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ground Zero</username>
        <id>1423298</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Cities */ remove red links</comment>
      <origin>5255020</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8661" sha1="dvu7yqrg0gkw8hgxph4zesh9zmsjq7n" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner|Guttland Wikivoyage Banner.jpg}}

'''Central Luxembourg''' is the region located around the capital, [[Luxembourg City]].

==Cities==
{{mapframe|49.665|6.073|zoom=10}}
{{mapshape|wikidata=Q397678,Q691741,Q753917}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=Capellen|lat=49.645 | long=5.988|wikidata=Q1988543}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=Colmar-Berg|lat=49.813 | long=6.093|wikidata=Q676957}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Luxembourg (city)|Luxembourg City]]|lat=49.612 | long=6.131|wikidata=Q1842}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=Mamer|lat=49.627 | long=5.939|wikidata=Q921291}}
* {{marker|type=city|name=[[Mersch]]|lat=49.751 | long=6.107|wikidata=Q284855}}

==Understand==
[[File:Mamer_Gemeng.jpg|thumb|Mamer Castle.]]
[[File:Panorama_Schoenfels_01.jpg|thumb|Panorama of Schoenfels.]]
Being built upon the foundations of previous centuries, Central Luxembourg is a region where modern and medieval architecture go hand in hand, having the City of Luxembourg listed as UNESCO World Heritage. The region is the creative centre of the country, housing many theatres and museums. Nature is an important part of the region. A third of the capital is dedicated to ''green zones'', aside from being surrounded by Guttland, which in itself is filled with barren forests. Being the capital, the region, especially the capital, makes up the country's biggest business centre, housing many banks and European institutions. 

==Get in==
===By car===
The A1 and A6 make up the ring-road system of the capital. These intersect with: the A3 and A4 which connect to the [[Land of the Red Rocks]] and [[Metz]]; the A7, which connects to [[Éislek]]; the A1 and A6 which both continue to [[Trier]] and [[Arlon]] respectively.

===By plane===
:''Also see [[Luxembourg (city)#Findel Airport|Luxembourg City]] for a more complete guide.''
Central Luxembourg is served by the {{Marker|type=city |lat=49.6268 |long=6.2125 |zoom=14 |name=Luxembourg-Findel Airport ({{IATA|LUX}}) |image=Check-in TK1354 LUX-IST inaugural flight.jpg}} in Sandweiler, a municipality just northeast of the capital. Compared to other major airports serving European capitals, it has quite limited connections - there are no long-haul flights scheduled to Findel, and the European network only encompasses several other capitals and destinations, meaning that flying in even from major European airports may require a transfer on your way.

The airport is dominated by the country's flag carrier, [http://www.luxair.lu/ Luxair], who operate a network of connections to selected other European capitals, some [[Germany|German]] cities and holiday destinations in the Mediterranean. This is complemented by some of the Star Alliance European members flying singular connections to Findel from their hubs. Luxair is not a Star Alliance member, but was partially owned by the Alliance's founding partner Lufthansa and shares its [[frequent flyer programme]] with them. Oneworld and Skyteam offer few connections to Luxembourg, but there is growing traffic from some regional and low-fare airlines.

Interestingly, while its passenger traffic is limited, Luxembourg Findel Airport is a major cargo hub thanks to the prominence of the cargo airline Cargolux with its base there. Both Cargolux and other major international players in the cargo market fly in huge intercontinental jets in and out of Findel daily.

===By public transit===
The imposing neobaroque Gare Lëtzebuerg, the country's main railway station, adored with a clock tower and huge windows is Luxembourg's main train station. It is relatively well served by connections from neighbouring countries. The railway station can be reached by most local buses. The city centre is within walking distance (around 1.5 km).

* The domestic train operator [http://www.cfl.lu/en CFL]{{Dead link|date=January 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot }} has EuroCity-class trains going to [[Paris]] and [[Brussels]]
* CFL also obviously connects ''Gare Lëtzebuerg'' with pretty much every other station within the country of Luxembourg
* The Belgian SNCB/NMSB also has trains connecting Luxembourg with ''Bruxelles-Midi''. Some trains continue to [[Strasbourg]] in France and [[Basel]] in Switzerland
* Deutsche Bahn operates the IC35 ''Ostfriesland'' from Luxembourg through [[Koblenz]], [[Cologne]], [[Dusseldorf]] and [[Münster]]
* Additionally, Deutsche Bahn's regional services operate the ''DeLux Express'' from Luxembourg to [[Trier]]
* The French SNCF operates a high-speed TGV train from ''Gare de l'Est'' in [[Paris]] to Luxembourg. There is also a slower ''Intercite'' connection via [[Nancy]] all the way south to [[Nice]]
* '''TER Lorraine''' line 1 goes from [[Nancy]] via [[Metz]] and [[Thionville]] to Luxembourg
* The Swiss SBB operates several long distance trains from stations in [[Switzerland]] such as [[Zurich]], [[Geneve]], [[Chur]] and [[Interlaken]] to Brussels that stop in Luxembourg on their way

==Get around==
[[File:Alles_op_de_Vëlo_Schoenfels_01.jpg|thumb|Cyclists on route between Mamer and Mersch.]]

==See==
[[File:Luxembourg American Cemetery.jpg|thumb|The Luxembourgian American Cemetery and Memorial.]]
[[File:Luxemburg_trammuseum_5.jpg|thumb|Luxembourgian Tram Museum.]]
* '''Luxembourg's historical value''' can be found by walking the city. The atmosphere and architecture in the city centre are rather uncommon in capital cities.
* '''Museums''' are mostly found in the capital city, such as the MUDAM (''Musée d'Art Moderne Grand-Duc Jean''; ''Museum of Modern Art Grand-Duke Jean''), though the rest of Central Luxembourg definitely has museums on offer, such as the ''Musée international d’effets de gendarmerie et police''; ''International Museum of Police'' in [[Capellen]].

==Do==

==Eat==
Luxembourg city is home to a surprisingly high number of Michelin star establishments, though having a star doesn't make a restaurant worth visiting per se. Above that, Pizzerias in Luxembourg are in high numbers.

==Drink==

==Stay safe==

==Go next==
* '''The [[Land of the Red Rocks]]''' — The mining region of Luxembourg, which gives the region its industrial character. The region is, however, focusing more and more on tourism, offering tours of former mines, making heritage railways out of old industrial railways, whilst also housing the university city of the country, Esch-sur-Alzette, which brings a lively nightlife to the city.
* '''The [[Mullerthal]]''' — Also known as Luxembourg's Little Switzerland due to its stunningly beautiful terrain. The region is located around [[Echternach]], which is the oldest city of Luxembourg. The city's basilica contains the crypt of Saint Willibrord.
* '''[[Éislek]]''' — The green region of Luxembourg, featuring many castles and a life-long supply of hiking and cycling trails to explore through the vast and never-ending forests.
* '''The [[Moselle Valley (Luxembourg)|Moselle Valley]]''' — Obviously located along the river Moselle, which makes up part of the border with Germany, the Luxembourgish Moselle Valley is mostly known for its wines, which can be bought in the entire country. The region is also home to [[Schengen]], the town nearest to the border tri-point with France and Germany as well as the namesake town of the [[Schengen Agreement]], and [[Mondorf-les-Bains]], one of the country's best-known [[spa towns]].

{{routebox
| image1=Autoroute 1 (Luxemburg) number.png
| imagesize1=
| directionl1=W
| majorl1=[[Arlon]]
| minorl1=[[Mamer]]
| directionr1=E
| majorr1=[[Luxembourg City]]
| minorr1=
| link1=
| caption1=

| image2=Autoroute 3 (Luxemburg) number.png
| imagesize2=
| directionl2=N
| majorl2=[[Luxembourg City]]
| minorl2=[[Land of the Red Rocks]]
| directionr2=S
| majorr2=[[Metz]]
| minorr2=[[Thionville]]
| link2=
| caption2=

| image3=Autoroute 6 (Luxemburg) number.png
| imagesize3=
| directionl3=W
| majorl3=[[Luxembourg City]]
| minorl3=
| directionr3=E
| majorr3=[[Trier]]
| minorr3=[[Grevenmacher]]
| link3=
| caption3=

| image4=Autoroute 7 (Luxemburg) number.png
| image4a=BE-E421.svg
| imagesize4=
| imagesize4a=
| directionl4=N
| majorl4=[[Clervaux]]
| minorl4=[[Ettelbruck]]
| directionr4=S
| majorr4=[[Luxembourg]]
| minorr4=[[Mersch]]
| link4=
| caption4=

| image5=BSicon BAHN.svg
| imagesize5=
| directionl5=N
| majorl5=[[Luxembourg City]]
| minorl5=[[Mersch]]
| directionr5=S
| majorr5=[[Clervaux]]
| minorr5=[[Liège]]
| link5=
| caption5=CFL Line 10

| image6=BSicon BAHN.svg
| imagesize6=
| directionl6=W
| majorl6=[[Luxembourg City]]
| minorl6=
| directionr6=E
| majorr6=[[Trier]]
| minorr6=[[Wasserbillig]]
| link6=
| caption6=CFL Line 30
}}

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}
{{outlineregion}}
{{geo|49.583333|6.166667|zoom=10}}</text>
      <sha1>dvu7yqrg0gkw8hgxph4zesh9zmsjq7n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Category:Moselle Valley (Luxembourg)</title>
    <ns>14</ns>
    <id>157427</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4083499</id>
      <parentid>3250517</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-10-26T11:16:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Andyrom75</username>
        <id>107092</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Andyrom75 moved page [[Category:Moselle District]] to [[Category:Moselle Valley (Luxembourg)]] without leaving a redirect</comment>
      <origin>3250517</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="38" sha1="it7f7rx56fms9iby72lvw8g4fk8acym" xml:space="preserve">{{RegionCat}}

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}</text>
      <sha1>it7f7rx56fms9iby72lvw8g4fk8acym</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Guttland</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>181131</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4083486</id>
      <parentid>4082908</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-10-26T11:10:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Andyrom75</username>
        <id>107092</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>4083486</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="286" sha1="a9h3qduhuqb74nxorey75zs70tjzqqm" xml:space="preserve">{{pagebanner}}
__NOTOC__
'''Guttland''' is the name of a large area of Luxembourg that includes the following tourist regions:
* [[Central Luxembourg]]
* [[Land of the Red Rocks]]
* [[Moselle Valley (Luxembourg)|Moselle Valley]]
* [[Mullerthal]]

{{Extraregion}}
{{isPartOf|Luxembourg}}</text>
      <sha1>a9h3qduhuqb74nxorey75zs70tjzqqm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Category:Central Luxembourg</title>
    <ns>14</ns>
    <id>186567</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4267355</id>
      <timestamp>2021-08-04T02:01:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SelfieCity</username>
        <id>2183461</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created page with "{{RegionCat}}  {{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}  &lt;!-- From article LocationA that has Breadcrumb : &gt; CountryD &gt; RegionC &gt; SubRegionB &gt; LocationA, you are now creating Category:SubRegionB --&gt; &lt;!-- replace the comment in IsPartOf above with what is the correct name of RegionC --&gt;"</comment>
      <origin>4267355</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="269" sha1="ao0fd56vm2sf3h96d3mnxv5lexfqa9y" xml:space="preserve">{{RegionCat}}

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}

&lt;!-- From article LocationA that has Breadcrumb : &gt; CountryD &gt; RegionC &gt; SubRegionB &gt; LocationA, you are now creating Category:SubRegionB --&gt;
&lt;!-- replace the comment in IsPartOf above with what is the correct name of RegionC --&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ao0fd56vm2sf3h96d3mnxv5lexfqa9y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Category:Éislek</title>
    <ns>14</ns>
    <id>194630</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4508716</id>
      <timestamp>2022-08-26T10:33:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SHB2000</username>
        <id>2248002</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created page with "{{RegionCat}}  {{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}  &lt;!-- From article LocationA that has Breadcrumb : &gt; CountryD &gt; RegionC &gt; SubRegionB &gt; LocationA, you are now creating Category:SubRegionB --&gt; &lt;!-- replace the comment in IsPartOf above with what is the correct name of RegionC --&gt;"</comment>
      <origin>4508716</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="269" sha1="ao0fd56vm2sf3h96d3mnxv5lexfqa9y" xml:space="preserve">{{RegionCat}}

{{IsPartOf|Luxembourg}}

&lt;!-- From article LocationA that has Breadcrumb : &gt; CountryD &gt; RegionC &gt; SubRegionB &gt; LocationA, you are now creating Category:SubRegionB --&gt;
&lt;!-- replace the comment in IsPartOf above with what is the correct name of RegionC --&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ao0fd56vm2sf3h96d3mnxv5lexfqa9y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
