<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="63.2">
  <metadata>
    <title>Amsterdam</title>
    <name_it>Amsterdam</name_it>
    <flag>🇳🇱</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>6</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>157.25</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="72.5"/>
    <environment green_score="78"/>
    <cost_index value="85.0"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="15.0"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>From Schiphol Airport. The train station is located directly beneath the airport. From the arrivals hall, walk through Schiphol Plaza to reach the train station.</transport>
  <accommodation>
    <hotel>
      <name>Gaasper Camping Amsterdam</name>
      <price>Off-season from €16.25, from €18.50 during high-season</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>A&amp;amp;O Amsterdam Zuidoost</name>
      <price>€24</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Campanile Hotel Amsterdam</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Tulip Inn Amsterdam Riverside</name>
      <price>€78</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>EasyHotel Amsterdam Arena Boulevard</name>
      <price>Doubles from €49</price>
    </hotel>
  </accommodation>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="52.36" lon="4.8852">
      <name>Rijksmuseum</name>
      <description>National museum dedicated to Dutch arts and history.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3752" lon="4.884">
      <name>Anne Frank House</name>
      <description>Historic house where Anne Frank hid during WWII.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3584" lon="4.8811">
      <name>Van Gogh Museum</name>
      <description>World's largest collection of artworks by Vincent van Gogh.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.358" lon="4.8686">
      <name>Vondelpark</name>
      <description>The city's most famous and largest public park.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3731" lon="4.8926">
      <name>Dam Square</name>
      <description>The historic center of Amsterdam and site of the Royal Palace.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3578" lon="4.8917">
      <name>Heineken Experience</name>
      <description>Interactive museum in the former brewery of the pilsner brand.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.358" lon="4.8797">
      <name>Stedelijk Museum</name>
      <description>Major museum for modern and contemporary art and design.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3693" lon="4.9013">
      <name>Rembrandt House</name>
      <description>The former home and workshop of the painter Rembrandt.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3842" lon="4.9023">
      <name>A'DAM Lookout</name>
      <description>Observation deck with a 360-degree view of the city.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3725" lon="4.8792">
      <name>Jordaan District</name>
      <description>Charming neighborhood known for its narrow canals and boutiques.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Zuidoost</name>
      <description>Zuidoost (Dutch for Southeast), often colloquially referred to as the Bijlmer, is a borough of Amsterdam. It is an exclave, separated from the mainland by Duivendrecht and Diemen. With no shared borders with Amsterdam, Zuidoost is a separate entity. It was built up in the 1960s and 70s as a residential utopia of sorts with apartment blocks separated by tracts of green. Also known as ‘De Bijlmer’,...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Canal District</name>
      <description>The Canal District (Dutch: Grachtengordel) is the famous 17th-century district surrounding the Binnenstad of Amsterdam. The whole district is designated as a UNESCO World Heritage Site for its unique cultural and historical value, and its property values are among the highest in the country. This article also deals with the Leidseplein and the Rembrandtplein, the two prime nightlife spots of the...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Oost</name>
      <description>Oost (Dutch for East) is a borough of Amsterdam. It lies between the Amstel River in the west and the IJ in the east. It should not be regarded as a homogeneous area, as there are many different neighbourhoods with their own cultures and identities. The main area is around the Oosterpark. The Eastern Docklands and IJburg are also lively upper middle class areas and their modern architecture shows...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Jordaan</name>
      <description>The Jordaan is a district in the centre of Amsterdam. It used to be a working-class neighbourhood, but has become one of the most upscale areas of the Netherlands, known for its art galleries, speciality shops and boutique restaurants. Among the Dutch, the Jordaan is known for its folk singers; several of its most popular musicians now have a statue in their memory at the corner of Prinsengracht...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Noord</name>
      <description>Noord (Dutch for North) is the borough of Amsterdam north of the IJ. It is a residential district, and with about 86,000 inhabitants, it is a medium-sized city (and it is growing at a rapid pace—three new neighbourhoods are under construction). This district has remained well off the radar among tourists visiting Amsterdam, so amenities are not well-developed. It looks strikingly different from...</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Hub globale dell'innovazione sostenibile, Amsterdam eccelle nella mobilità ciclistica e nella gestione creativa degli spazi acquatici. Unisce un dinamismo economico unico a una rete di sicurezza sociale e urbana di primo livello.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Zuidoost (Dutch for Southeast), often colloquially referred to as the Bijlmer, is a borough of Amsterdam. It is an exclave, separated from the mainland by Duivendrecht and Diemen. With no shared borders with Amsterdam, Zuidoost is a separate entity. It was built up in the 1960s and 70s as a residential utopia of sorts with apartment blocks separated by tracts of green. Also known as ‘De Bijlmer’,...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Rijksmuseum_Amsterdam_2016.jpg</landmark_image>
</city_report>
