<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="62.3">
  <metadata>
    <title>Berlin</title>
    <name_it>Berlino</name_it>
    <flag>🇩🇪</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>21</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>137.27</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="60.8"/>
    <environment green_score="82"/>
    <cost_index value="74.2"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="25.8"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>The area covered in this guide is expansive, but the most popular attractions are almost all near the Zoologischer Garten train station and the Ku'damm, and thus easily within walking distance. If you want to visit the outlying ones, you may want to use Berlin's excellent public transportation system - the U-Bahn, S-Bahn and the bus networks. West Berlin, unlike East Berlin, had its tram network dismantled and you will find no trams here.</transport>
  <accommodation>
    <hotel>
      <name>Amstel House Berlin</name>
      <price>Four-bedded dorms from €12/person/night. Single and twin rooms en-suite also available</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Gasteiner Hof</name>
      <price>Rooms from €30, breakfast included</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Jet Pak City</name>
      <price>Double rooms start at €30 per person, sleeping hall starts at €18 per person</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Meininger Hotel Berlin Central Station</name>
      <price>Double Rooms start at €39 per person, dormitory starts at €21</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Three Little Pigs Hostel</name>
      <price>€13</price>
    </hotel>
  </accommodation>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="52.5163" lon="13.3777">
      <name>Brandenburg Gate</name>
      <description>Neoclassical monument symbolizing German unity.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5186" lon="13.3761">
      <name>Reichstag</name>
      <description>Historic parliament building with a modern glass dome.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.505" lon="13.4397">
      <name>East Side Gallery</name>
      <description>Longest remaining section of the Berlin Wall with murals.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5169" lon="13.3999">
      <name>Museum Island</name>
      <description>UNESCO site housing five world-renowned museums.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.519" lon="13.4011">
      <name>Berlin Cathedral</name>
      <description>Grand 19th-century cathedral on the Spree river.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5208" lon="13.4094">
      <name>TV Tower</name>
      <description>Iconic landmark offering views from 203 meters up.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5074" lon="13.3904">
      <name>Checkpoint Charlie</name>
      <description>Famous former border crossing between East and West.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5139" lon="13.3786">
      <name>Holocaust Memorial</name>
      <description>Memorial to the murdered Jews of Europe.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5212" lon="13.2958">
      <name>Charlottenburg Palace</name>
      <description>Largest palace in Berlin with beautiful gardens.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5094" lon="13.3767">
      <name>Potsdamer Platz</name>
      <description>Public square and symbol of Berlin's urban renewal.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>City West</name>
      <description>City West is the heart of former West Berlin and even after reunification it represents the main retail centre of Berlin — all the best and most expensive shops are here. The area also includes some landmarks of great historical and cultural interest, as well as a large number of accommodation and entertainment options. After Berlin was split into two by the division of Germany, West Berlin had...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>East</name>
      <description>The East is a district of Berlin. It consists of the boroughs Pankow (except for Prenzlauer Berg), Lichtenberg, Hohenschönhausen, Marzahn and Hellersdorf. The most interesting places for tourists are in Lichtenberg: the Stasi (secret service of the GDR) relics and museums, the Tierpark (zoo) and some remarkable architecture such as the Mies van der Rohe house. Lichtenberg is a district in the...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>East Central</name>
      <description>East Central is a trendy, bohemian, artsy area that consists of Kreuzberg, Friedrichshain, Prenzlauer Berg (sometimes called Prenzlberg), Wedding and Gesundbrunnen. The western district Kreuzberg was merged with the eastern district Friedrichshain in 2001. They skew towards a young and alternative, often politically left-oriented crowd. Both districts feature a very heterogeneous architecture,...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Mitte</name>
      <description>Mitte, literally meaning "the middle" and being a contraction of Stadtmitte (city centre), contains the historical heart of Berlin and represents in many ways the real centre of the city. It is here that you will find the vast majority of the most popular sights. "Mitte" can refer both to a larger district (Bezirk) and its smaller borough (Ortsteil), which was a separate district until 2001 when...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Reinickendorf and Spandau</name>
      <description>The northwest of Berlin consists of the boroughs of Spandau and Reinickendorf was urbanized in the 19th century. Before that, it largely consisted of small towns. In the early 20th century, it was the working-class area with heavy industry where Siemens was founded; indeed, part of Reinickendorf is called Siemensstadt. The area is more residential today, though big industrial complexes remain....</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Capitale della resilienza e della cultura underground, Berlino offre una vastità di parchi pubblici senza eguali tra le grandi metropoli europee. Il mercato immobiliare e la sicurezza la rendono un magnete per talenti tecnologici e creativi.</description>
  <wiki_intro>City West is the heart of former West Berlin and even after reunification it represents the main retail centre of Berlin — all the best and most expensive shops are here. The area also includes some landmarks of great historical and cultural interest, as well as a large number of accommodation and entertainment options. After Berlin was split into two by the division of Germany, West Berlin had...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Brandenburger_Tor_abends.jpg</landmark_image>
</city_report>
