<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="48.4">
  <metadata>
    <title>Rome</title>
    <name_it>Roma</name_it>
    <flag>🇮🇹</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>3</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>132.28</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="46.8"/>
    <environment green_score="60"/>
    <cost_index value="71.5"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="28.5"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>Testaccio is a short walk from the metro station and Circus Maximus also has its own metro station on the rome line (Circo Massimo). Near Piramide Metro station is Ostiense railway station, with regular connections to and from Fiumicino Airport. From Piramide you can also get trains to Ostia.</transport>
  <accommodation>
    <hotel>
      <name>Gazometro B&amp;amp;B Rome</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Hotels Aventine, San Anselmo and San Pio</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Testaccio Hotel, Sonder</name>
      <price>Single €99, double €121</price>
    </hotel>
  </accommodation>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="41.8902" lon="12.4922">
      <name>Colosseum</name>
      <description>The largest ancient amphitheatre ever built.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.8986" lon="12.4769">
      <name>Pantheon</name>
      <description>Ancient Roman temple with a massive dome.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9009" lon="12.4833">
      <name>Trevi Fountain</name>
      <description>Iconic Baronque fountain where tourists throw coins.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.8925" lon="12.4853">
      <name>Roman Forum</name>
      <description>Ruins of the heart of ancient Roman public life.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9065" lon="12.4548">
      <name>Vatican Museums</name>
      <description>Art museums including the Sistine Chapel.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9022" lon="12.4539">
      <name>St. Peter's Basilica</name>
      <description>Major Renaissance church in Vatican City.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.8992" lon="12.4731">
      <name>Piazza Navona</name>
      <description>Square built on an ancient stadium with Bernini fountains.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9059" lon="12.4828">
      <name>Spanish Steps</name>
      <description>Famous monumental stairway of 135 steps.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9031" lon="12.4663">
      <name>Castel Sant'Angelo</name>
      <description>Hadrian's mausoleum converted into a papal fortress.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9142" lon="12.4921">
      <name>Borghese Gallery</name>
      <description>Museum in a villa housing Bernini and Caravaggio.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Aventino-Testaccio</name>
      <description>Aventino and Testaccio are neighbourhoods of Rome. Aventino is named for the hill which rises up near the Tiber river and is one of the legendary seven hills of Rome. Diagonally opposite at the end of Circus Maximus is the Celian Hill, another of the seven hills.
Testaccio is an area to the southwest of Aventino along the bank of the Tiber and is named for the eighth hill of Rome, a man made hill...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Colosseo</name>
      <description>The Colosseo district is the heart of ancient Rome and the Roman Empire. It has the Colosseum, the Forum, and the Capitoline Museum. Via dei Fori Imperiali cuts through the centre of the Rome/Colosseo district, connecting Piazza Venezia with the Colosseum. It is well served by buses, although if you are into serious sightseeing you are likely to want to walk instead as the Roman Forum is on your...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Esquilino-San Giovanni</name>
      <description>Esquilino and San Giovanni are adjacent neighborhoods in Rome. Esquilino is named for the Esquiline hill on which it stands. It lies south of the Termini station and is centred more or less on the Piazza Vittorio Emmanuele II. It is now partly a Chinese immigrant neighbourhood, and specialty groceries and shoe stores abound. San Giovanni is named after the Basilica, which is the Roman Catholic...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Modern Centre</name>
      <description>The Modern Centre of Rome, home to the Via Veneto, Quirinale, Castro Pretorio, Repubblica, and Trevi neighbourhoods, is the city's hub of activity, especially shopping and nightlife. It's also home to a huge assortment of hotels, and it's likely that you'll be staying here, despite the fact that most of Rome's historic attractions are elsewhere. The Modern Centre of Rome is not hard to find as...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Nomentano</name>
      <description>Nomentano is a district of Rome. The San Lorenzo neighborhood is a student area south-east of Rome's main train station (Termini). It has a small street market (food, clothing), unpretentious caffès and is a major centre of Rome's night life. The Nomentano area is easily reachable by bus from Termini Station (90) from Piazza Venezia or via Nazionale (60) or by Metro Line (stops: Castro Pretorio,...</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Città eterna dalla bellezza stratificata, Roma sta affrontando la sfida della modernizzazione nel rispetto dei suoi vincoli archeologici. Il suo fascino monumentale resta un asset insostituibile nel panorama mondiale.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Aventino and Testaccio are neighbourhoods of Rome. Aventino is named for the hill which rises up near the Tiber river and is one of the legendary seven hills of Rome. Diagonally opposite at the end of Circus Maximus is the Celian Hill, another of the seven hills.
Testaccio is an area to the southwest of Aventino along the bank of the Tiber and is named for the eighth hill of Rome, a man made hill...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Colosseum_in_Rome-April_2007-1-_copie_2B.jpg</landmark_image>
</city_report>
