<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "/Users/lauratonsi/ELABORAZIONE/data/city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="63.2">
  <metadata>
    <title>Amsterdam</title>
    <name_it>Amsterdam</name_it>
    <flag>🇳🇱</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>6</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>157.25</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="72.5"/>
    <environment green_score="78"/>
    <cost_index value="85.0"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="15.0"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>From Schiphol Airport. The train station is located directly beneath the airport. From the arrivals hall, walk through Schiphol Plaza to reach the train station.</transport>
  <accommodation>
    <hotel>
      <name>Gaasper Camping Amsterdam</name>
      <price>Off-season from €16.25, from €18.50 during high-season</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>A&amp;amp;O Amsterdam Zuidoost</name>
      <price>€24</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Campanile Hotel Amsterdam</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Tulip Inn Amsterdam Riverside</name>
      <price>€78</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>EasyHotel Amsterdam Arena Boulevard</name>
      <price>Doubles from €49</price>
    </hotel>
  </accommodation>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="52.36" lon="4.8852">
      <name>Rijksmuseum</name>
      <description>National museum dedicated to Dutch arts and history.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3752" lon="4.884">
      <name>Anne Frank House</name>
      <description>Historic house where Anne Frank hid during WWII.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3584" lon="4.8811">
      <name>Van Gogh Museum</name>
      <description>World's largest collection of artworks by Vincent van Gogh.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.358" lon="4.8686">
      <name>Vondelpark</name>
      <description>The city's most famous and largest public park.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3731" lon="4.8926">
      <name>Dam Square</name>
      <description>The historic center of Amsterdam and site of the Royal Palace.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3578" lon="4.8917">
      <name>Heineken Experience</name>
      <description>Interactive museum in the former brewery of the pilsner brand.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.358" lon="4.8797">
      <name>Stedelijk Museum</name>
      <description>Major museum for modern and contemporary art and design.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3693" lon="4.9013">
      <name>Rembrandt House</name>
      <description>The former home and workshop of the painter Rembrandt.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3842" lon="4.9023">
      <name>A'DAM Lookout</name>
      <description>Observation deck with a 360-degree view of the city.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.3725" lon="4.8792">
      <name>Jordaan District</name>
      <description>Charming neighborhood known for its narrow canals and boutiques.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Zuidoost</name>
      <description>Zuidoost (Dutch for Southeast), often colloquially referred to as the Bijlmer, is a borough of Amsterdam. It is an exclave, separated from the mainland by Duivendrecht and Diemen. With no shared borders with Amsterdam, Zuidoost is a separate entity. It was built up in the 1960s and 70s as a residential utopia of sorts with apartment blocks separated by tracts of green. Also known as ‘De Bijlmer’, Zuidoost is a vibrant multicultural district renowned as the home of the Ajax football team. Zuidoost lies southeast of the A10 ring motorway and west of the Weespertrekvaart waterway that connects with the Amsterdam-Rijn canal. To the north are the town of Diemen and its forest Diemerbos. To the south lies Nieuw Utrechtseweg (A2 motorway) and open fields, beyond which is the Amstel River-side town of Oudekerk aan de Amstel. The A9 motorway runs through Bijlmer from Haarlem and connects to the A1 for Eastern destinations. The architecturally-acclaimed Amsterdam Bijlmer ArenA railway station provides easy access to Amsterdam and the rest of the Netherlands. It serves the Bijlmermeer neighbourhood. *From Schiphol Airport. The train station is located directly beneath the airport. From the arrivals hall, walk through Schiphol Plaza to reach the train station.
*Trains run to and from the Randstad (Amsterdam, The Hague, Rotterdam, Utrecht region) A night train also stops between 1:00&amp;amp;ndash;2:00 on F&amp;amp;ndash;M. On Tuesday night, they run between 1:00&amp;amp;ndash;4:00. The fare for the night train is the same as the day train. In the night of Friday on Saturday, one night train between Maastricht and Schiphol and run by Arriva stops at Amsterdam Bijlmer ArenA. Special tariff. Sprinter (local) trains on the Amsterdam - Utrecht and Amsterdam - Gouda - Rotterdam routes also stop at the Amsterdam Holendrecht station near the Amsterdam UMC, location AMC hospital, about 2&amp;amp;nbsp;km south of Bijlmer ArenA. Metro lines 50, 53 and 54 link the Bijlmer to the rest of Amsterdam. * Metro line runs from Isolatorweg to Gein along the same route as 54 and connects Bijlmer to the south and west of Amsterdam.
* Metro line runs from Amsterdam Centraal Station to Gaasperplas and services the north and east of Bijlmer.
* Metro line also from Amsterdam Centraal Station, runs parallel to the railway along the west of Bijlmer, then turns east to Gein in the south. The two bigger stations of Zuidoost, both on lines 50 and 54, and are also train stations serviced with Sprinter services (Bijlmer ArenA and Holendrecht) and Intercity services (Bijlmer ArenA). The latter, Bijlmer ArenA may be particularly crowded during matches of local football club Ajax or the Dutch national team. *
* 
* 
*  *
* 
*
*
*
* * As this is a new part of Amsterdam, shopping malls are generally modern and large. From Bijlmer Station, west of the railroad you can find large retail stores, such as IKEA, MediaMarkt and others.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Canal District</name>
      <description>The Canal District (Dutch: Grachtengordel) is the famous 17th-century district surrounding the Binnenstad of Amsterdam. The whole district is designated as a UNESCO World Heritage Site for its unique cultural and historical value, and its property values are among the highest in the country. This article also deals with the Leidseplein and the Rembrandtplein, the two prime nightlife spots of the city. The Weteringschans is also included. The most convenient way to get into the Canal District is by tram.
* Trams and all run through the middle of the Canal District on their way between Amsterdam Centraal and Leidseplein, with notable stops at Koningsplein, Keizersgracht and Prinsengracht.
* Trams and , both from Amsterdam Centraal, pass through Rembrandtplein.
* Trams and , both from Amsterdam Centraal, head for the western side of the district, with the stop Westerkerk as the most notable one as the Anne Frank House is nearby.
* Tram goes south from Amsterdam Centraal through Muntplein and Vijzelgracht.
* Trams , and go along the southern side of the Canal District between Leidseplein and the Amstel River passing metro station Vijzelgracht. At the stop, these east/west tram lines connect. The district has one metro station on line M51 running south from Amsterdam Centraal. Metro station Vijzelgracht connects with several tram lines at the Vijzelgracht tram stop. As the name implies, the main attractions of the Canal District are the canals and the rich architectural heritage of this area. Built-in the 17th century, the merchant-based oligarchy that ruled the trading city of Amsterdam built canal houses and mansions in the most prestigious locations, especially along the main canals. The city office for Architectural Heritage BMA has a chronological list of the most important ones: * Singel 140-142, De Dolphijn (circa 1600).
* Herengracht 170-172, Bartolotti House (circa 1617).
* Keizersgracht 123, House with the Heads (1622).
* Herengracht 168 (1638).
* Singel 104-106 (1743).
* Singel 36, Zeevrugt (1763).
*  * 
* 
* 
*
* 
* 
*  *  * 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
*Amsterdam Booze Cruise , Herengracht 564. A boat trip through the canals of Amsterdam is always a good idea. Discover Amsterdam from the water while enjoying a drink. * 
* 
*  Most foreigners grab a restaurant in the area around the Leidsestraat. While there are some good restaurants in that area, be wary as there are a lot of overpriced tourist traps as well. * 
*
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
*  Nightclubs in Amsterdam are centered around two squares, Leidseplein and Rembrandtplein. Close to the latter is the Reguliersdwarsstraat, the gay street of Amsterdam. In between these squares are plenty of smaller bars and pubs that are also fun in the daytime. * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
*  * 
*
* 
*  *
* 
*  CoffeeCompany offers free Wi-Fi at Leidsegracht, the walking street from the Binnenstad to Leidseplein.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Oost</name>
      <description>Oost (Dutch for East) is a borough of Amsterdam. It lies between the Amstel River in the west and the IJ in the east. It should not be regarded as a homogeneous area, as there are many different neighbourhoods with their own cultures and identities. The main area is around the Oosterpark. The Eastern Docklands and IJburg are also lively upper middle class areas and their modern architecture shows a completely different side of Amsterdam. Directly south of the Plantage is the Oosterpark, the first large park financed by the municipality of Amsterdam, as it dates from 1891. The Vondelpark is older and larger, but that initially was a private project. Activities can be undertaken in and around the park, and you can visit the nearby Wereldmuseum. South of the Oosterpark are some ethnically mixed working-class neighbourhoods that originate from the late 19th century. The ethnic make-up of the area is best reflected in the local markets. The Dappermarkt, a designated market street since 1910, has products for sale that primarily aim to a Dutch Antillean, Moroccan, Surinamese and Turkish clientele. The Indische Buurt is another working-class neighbourhood with a large immigrant population, as can be seen at the street market along the Javastraat. The Eastern Docklands (Oostelijk Havengebied) date from the nineteenth century, and as the name suggests, used to be a port that served the growing trade with the Dutch East Indies. In the first half of the twentieth century, this area was in full development as warehouses were constructed to facilitate trade with the colonies. After the Great Depression, World War II and the subsequent decolonisation, the area fell into decay. It was only in the 1990s that this area was reconstructed and turned into an upper-class residential area modeled after the Docklands in London. There are some truly stunning examples of modern architecture to be found here. Following this project, IJburg was a new middle-class neighbourhood on artificial islands reclaimed from the IJ in the 2000s. More islands are being reclaimed to build the Amsterdam of the future. Further south is the Amsterdam Amstel railway station, an emerging business district. In 1994 the Rembrandt Tower was completed, 135 metres the tallest skyscraper in Amsterdam and the first in a series of towers named after famous Dutch painters. In 2001, the tower was accompanied by the Breitner Tower and the Mondriaan Tower, both in the same area. East of these lies the Watergraafsmeer, formerly a polder that was incorporated in Amsterdam in 1921. It was home to Stadium De Meer, the home of Ajax football club until its destruction in 1996. It is a green neighbourhood with many trees and sports facilities, as it used to be a popular getaway for affluent citizens of Amsterdam. Now it is becoming Amsterdam's knowledge centre due to the development of the Amsterdam Science Park.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Jordaan</name>
      <description>The Jordaan is a district in the centre of Amsterdam. It used to be a working-class neighbourhood, but has become one of the most upscale areas of the Netherlands, known for its art galleries, speciality shops and boutique restaurants. Among the Dutch, the Jordaan is known for its folk singers; several of its most popular musicians now have a statue in their memory at the corner of Prinsengracht and Elandsgracht. The tram is the easiest way to get around central Amsterdam, and the Jordaan is no exception.  From Amsterdam Centraal, Tram and Tram bring you to the stop Westermarkt at the beginning of the Jordaan-district. Tram continues a few stops further to Elandsgracht at the west side of the district. Tram travels along the west side of the district from Leidseplein to Marnixplein where one can transfer to Tram to continue to Haarlemmerbuurt on the northern side of the district.  Note: No tram service to Haarlemmerbuurt Until November 2022, there is no tram service to Haarlemmerbuurt; however, until then, tram 5 will temporarily provide service within walking distance. Alternatively, Haarlemmerbuurt is only a 5-minute walk from Amsterdam Centraal. * 
* 
*  The Jordaan is a great place to just stroll through taking in the beautiful architecture. The canal houses are always a pleasure, but also don't miss out on the backstreets. * 
* The main three shopping streets in the Jordaan are, from north to south, Westerstraat, Rozengracht and Elandsgracht. These offer a mix of clothing stores, design, art galleries, bars and restaurants. In the side-streets (Tweede Anjeliersdwarsstraat/Tweede Tuindwarsstraat/Tweede Egelantiersdwarsstraat), you'll find more nice restaurants. And in another side-street, Hazenstraat, there's a lot of galleries and quirky stores. On Saturday there is a (pricey) biological market on Noordermarkt and a (cheaper) normal market around the corner on Lindengracht. It's great to stroll around on both these markets. On Monday there is a (second hand) clothing market on Noordermarkt and Westerstraat. * 
* 
*  *
*
*
*
* 
* 
* 
*
*  * 
*  Unlike the mainstream bars and clubs in the Canal District, the Jordaan offers a different atmosphere with obscure rock, metal and alternative music. But there's also plenty of old fashioned neighbourhood bars and 'hip' places. * 
*
*
*
* 
*
*  *  * 
*  *  *
*
*</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Noord</name>
      <description>Noord (Dutch for North) is the borough of Amsterdam north of the IJ. It is a residential district, and with about 86,000 inhabitants, it is a medium-sized city (and it is growing at a rapid pace—three new neighbourhoods are under construction). This district has remained well off the radar among tourists visiting Amsterdam, so amenities are not well-developed. It looks strikingly different from the city centre, so get in with an open mind. Yet, there is more to see than you might think. The ferry to it in itself is a breeze, crossing the river IJ and showing the urban landscape of Noord. Get off at the NDSM shipyard, which functioned as a shipyard until the 1980s, but now boasts a lively art scene. Urban culture comes alive in its large skate park. Then patch up your bicycle, and ride it through the rural farmland in the east. The picturesque villages Ransdorp and Zunderdorp are favourites among the locals for their traditional Dutch farmhouses.  and the Noord]]
The north lies fairly isolated from the rest of Amsterdam, but there is a free GVB ferry from Centraal Station in the Binnenstad. Instead of just being a way to get in, the ferry ride is an attraction in itself. It gives a great view over the urban harbour-front, and shows the diversity of the north's residents. Large signs show when the next boat is departing, and when it does, expect masses of locals to get on with their bicycles. Getting on just before the boat leaves seems to have turned into a sport here. You can take off at different piers, the NDSM shipyard being the most notable. If you want to do some further exploring, be sure to bring a bicycle and a decent map. Noord is also connected to the rest of Amsterdam by the Schellingwouderbrug bridge and the three road tunnels the Coentunnel, IJtunnel, and Zeeburgertunnel. Amsterdam's Centraal Station connects via metro line 52, the North/South-line, which has two stops in Noord: and . Line 52 is served by one train every six minutes, or ten per hour going either direction. Hence, planning your journey isn't a necessity. There's not much to see around here, but you might want to check out the windmill. It's not open to the public. The NDSM-shipyard is also home to the headquarters of Greenpeace. *  *  Take the ferry over the IJ that runs on the north side of Amsterdam Centraal. These are free of charge and provide nice views of the harbor and skyline. Take the ferry to Buiksloterweg and make a short walk to the EYE Film Institute for its architecture and free exhibition in the basement. *  *  * 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
*  * 
*  You can make a full-day cycling tour along the coast, taking in Marken, Monnickendam, Volendam, Edam, Broek in Waterland and other villages of the Waterland region.</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Global hub of sustainable innovation, Amsterdam excels in bicycle mobility and creative water-space management. It combines unique economic dynamism with a top-tier social and urban safety network.</description>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/amsterdam.jpg</landmark_image>
  <nightlife>
    <venue lat="52.3760606" lon="4.9001777">
      <name>'Skek</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="52.3912178" lon="4.9382277">
      <name>'t Sluisje</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="52.3566879" lon="4.8904823">
      <name>Arie Op De Hoek</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="52.3634486" lon="4.9303273">
      <name>Bar Botanique Cafe Tropique</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="52.3656085" lon="4.8679756">
      <name>Bax</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="52.3724859" lon="4.9009348">
      <name>Bern</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="52.3666977" lon="4.9263471">
      <name>Brouwerij 't IJ</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="52.3526052" lon="4.8908646">
      <name>Cafe 't Podium</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
  </nightlife>
</city_report>
