<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="62.3">
  <metadata>
    <title>Berlin</title>
    <name_it>Berlino</name_it>
    <flag>🇩🇪</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>21</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>137.27</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="60.8"/>
    <environment green_score="82"/>
    <cost_index value="74.2"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="25.8"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>The area covered in this guide is expansive, but the most popular attractions are almost all near the Zoologischer Garten train station and the Ku'damm, and thus easily within walking distance. If you want to visit the outlying ones, you may want to use Berlin's excellent public transportation system - the U-Bahn, S-Bahn and the bus networks. West Berlin, unlike East Berlin, had its tram network dismantled and you will find no trams here.</transport>
  <accommodation>
    <hotel>
      <name>Amstel House Berlin</name>
      <price>Four-bedded dorms from €12/person/night. Single and twin rooms en-suite also available</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Gasteiner Hof</name>
      <price>Rooms from €30, breakfast included</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Jet Pak City</name>
      <price>Double rooms start at €30 per person, sleeping hall starts at €18 per person</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Meininger Hotel Berlin Central Station</name>
      <price>Double Rooms start at €39 per person, dormitory starts at €21</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Three Little Pigs Hostel</name>
      <price>€13</price>
    </hotel>
  </accommodation>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="52.5163" lon="13.3777">
      <name>Brandenburg Gate</name>
      <description>Neoclassical monument symbolizing German unity.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5186" lon="13.3761">
      <name>Reichstag</name>
      <description>Historic parliament building with a modern glass dome.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.505" lon="13.4397">
      <name>East Side Gallery</name>
      <description>Longest remaining section of the Berlin Wall with murals.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5169" lon="13.3999">
      <name>Museum Island</name>
      <description>UNESCO site housing five world-renowned museums.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.519" lon="13.4011">
      <name>Berlin Cathedral</name>
      <description>Grand 19th-century cathedral on the Spree river.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5208" lon="13.4094">
      <name>TV Tower</name>
      <description>Iconic landmark offering views from 203 meters up.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5074" lon="13.3904">
      <name>Checkpoint Charlie</name>
      <description>Famous former border crossing between East and West.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5139" lon="13.3786">
      <name>Holocaust Memorial</name>
      <description>Memorial to the murdered Jews of Europe.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5212" lon="13.2958">
      <name>Charlottenburg Palace</name>
      <description>Largest palace in Berlin with beautiful gardens.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="52.5094" lon="13.3767">
      <name>Potsdamer Platz</name>
      <description>Public square and symbol of Berlin's urban renewal.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>City West</name>
      <description>City West is the heart of former West Berlin and even after reunification it represents the main retail centre of Berlin — all the best and most expensive shops are here. The area also includes some landmarks of great historical and cultural interest, as well as a large number of accommodation and entertainment options. After Berlin was split into two by the division of Germany, West Berlin had to develop a city centre of its own, as most of the historic centre (Mitte) remained on the eastern side. Thus came about an unlikely city centre carved out of mostly residential, relaxed districts of Charlottenburg, Wilmersdorf and Schöneberg. The obvious centre became the area close to the Zoologischer Garten train station, which became the main train station for West Berlin, extending southwards towards the Kurfürstendamm (known popularly by the contraction Ku'damm) in southern Charlottenburg. This has always been the traditional retail centre of Berlin, cemented by the construction of the enormous iconic department store KaDeWe at one end, and remained so all through the years of West Berlin, seeing a lot of modern construction filling in the gaps left by World War II and updating the neighbourhoods to ever-changing standards. This remains the area of Charlottenburg you absolutely need to visit for luxury shopping (or window-shopping). Further north from the Ku'damm area is where the Schloss Charlottenburg is located, the beautiful castle and open park from which the district got...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>East</name>
      <description>The East is a district of Berlin. It consists of the boroughs Pankow (except for Prenzlauer Berg), Lichtenberg, Hohenschönhausen, Marzahn and Hellersdorf. The most interesting places for tourists are in Lichtenberg: the Stasi (secret service of the GDR) relics and museums, the Tierpark (zoo) and some remarkable architecture such as the Mies van der Rohe house. Lichtenberg is a district in the east of Berlin. It was merged with Hohenschönhausen in 2001. Lichtenberg is mostly a residential district, but because of its heterogeneity there are all classes of people living there. The centre of Lichtenberg (where there are some buildings left from the 19th century) is home to the working class, as is the centre of Hohenschönhausen (built mainly in the 1970s in rather ugly East German (GDR) socialist building block architecture). The middle class resides in the greener areas like Friedrichsfelde, whereas in Karlshorst you can watch some smaller mansions of the upper class. Marzahn-Hellersdorf is a district in the northeast of Berlin. It is largely a residential district for the underclass and the middle class. It is famous for its GDR socialist building-block architecture, but often ignored are some old, village-like parts. In general it is a very green district. There are only a few interesting sites for visitors. Most interesting are maybe the "Gärten der Welt", the Gründerzeitmuseum and the Schlosspark Biesdorf with its small castle in late classical style. A more thorough...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>East Central</name>
      <description>East Central is a trendy, bohemian, artsy area that consists of Kreuzberg, Friedrichshain, Prenzlauer Berg (sometimes called Prenzlberg), Wedding and Gesundbrunnen. The western district Kreuzberg was merged with the eastern district Friedrichshain in 2001. They skew towards a young and alternative, often politically left-oriented crowd. Both districts feature a very heterogeneous architecture, from whole quarters of 19th century apartment houses to functional and not very pleasant 1960s and 70s residential building blocks. You also notice the differences as the districts were separated by the wall. The remaining part of the wall between Friedrichshain and Kreuzberg is the longest part still existing in Berlin. Prenzlauer Berg is to the northeast of Friedrichshain and has changed considerably since reunification. It has gentrified similarly to Brooklyn/Williamsburg from deserted apartment houses into a lively area for students, artists and young people – if they or their parents can afford it. Rents have risen sharply in the last few years, and many empty apartments in this area are no longer rented out but sold, refurbished into luxurious lofts or hostel rooms. Wedding and Gesundbrunnen formed the Bezirk of Wedding prior to 2001 when the boundaries were redrawn. Wedding has a long tradition of being home to the working class and accordingly voted "red" for most of the Kaiserreich and Weimar era. During partition it lay on the west side of the wall and attracted an above...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Mitte</name>
      <description>Mitte, literally meaning "the middle" and being a contraction of Stadtmitte (city centre), contains the historical heart of Berlin and represents in many ways the real centre of the city. It is here that you will find the vast majority of the most popular sights. "Mitte" can refer both to a larger district (Bezirk) and its smaller borough (Ortsteil), which was a separate district until 2001 when the administrative division of Berlin changed. This guide focuses on the smaller Ortsteil Mitte and the Ortsteil Tiergarten, both of which belong to Bezirk Mitte. Tiergarten is the borough extending northwest from the Zoologischer Garten train station, taking its name from the large park that covers most of its area, which in turn takes its name from the world's oldest zoo in its southern end, close to the train station. On the outskirts of the park there are many little neighbourhoods of varying characters, detached from each other by the park. For other Ortsteile contained within the present-day Bezirk Mitte see Berlin/City West (Moabit and Hansaviertel) and Berlin/East Central (Wedding and Gesundbrunnen). The border between the Ortsteile Mitte and Tiergarten runs right across the Potsdamer Platz, and most of the buildings and institutions described here are actually in Tiergarten, but for the sake of making this guide more useful are described along with the others which fall in Mitte proper. For points of interest lying further West, see Berlin/City West. Before the reunification...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Reinickendorf and Spandau</name>
      <description>The northwest of Berlin consists of the boroughs of Spandau and Reinickendorf was urbanized in the 19th century. Before that, it largely consisted of small towns. In the early 20th century, it was the working-class area with heavy industry where Siemens was founded; indeed, part of Reinickendorf is called Siemensstadt. The area is more residential today, though big industrial complexes remain. Spandau is the westernmost borough (Bezirk) of the German capital city of Berlin. It is a green area near the Spree and Havel rivers. Once a town in its own right, Spandau is one of the oldest areas in the Berlin region and retains much of its unique character, having been spared the worst of the Allied bombing in the Second World War that so devastated the rest of the city. The center of the district is formed by a dense network of medieval streets and a market square, retaining a large number of timber-framed buildings. Spandau was the site of the military prison in which Hitler's deputy Rudolf Hess was imprisoned after the 1946 Nuremberg trials until his death in 1987. The prison was then demolished. Despite being part of Berlin, neither Berliners nor Spandauers usually consider that fact to apply in popular thought. If for example, you ask a taxi driver to take you to the "city center", they will most likely take you to the center of Spandau, not necessarily Mitte or the old heart of West Berlin. It's as much in the boondocks as some Berliners ever venture, and even those who...</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Capitale della resilienza e della cultura underground, Berlino offre una vastità di parchi pubblici senza eguali tra le grandi metropoli europee. Il mercato immobiliare e la sicurezza la rendono un magnete per talenti tecnologici e creativi.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Mitte, literally meaning "the middle" and being a contraction of Stadtmitte (city centre), contains the historical heart of Berlin and represents in many ways the real centre of the city. It is here that you will find the vast majority of the most popular sights. "Mitte" can refer both to a larger district (Bezirk) and its smaller borough (Ortsteil), which was a separate district until 2001 when the administrative division of Berlin changed. This guide focuses on the smaller Ortsteil Mitte and the Ortsteil Tiergarten, both of which belong to Bezirk Mitte. Tiergarten is the borough extending northwest from the Zoologischer Garten train station, taking its name from the large park that covers most of its area, which in turn takes its name from the world's oldest zoo in its southern end, close to the train station. On the outskirts of the park there are many little neighbourhoods of varying characters, detached from each other by the park. For other Ortsteile contained within the present-day Bezirk Mitte see Berlin/City West (Moabit and Hansaviertel) and Berlin/East Central (Wedding and Gesundbrunnen). The border between the Ortsteile Mitte and Tiergarten runs right across the Potsdamer Platz, and most of the buildings and institutions described here are actually in Tiergarten, but for the sake of making this guide more useful are described along with the others which fall in Mitte proper. For points of interest lying further West, see Berlin/City West. Before the reunification...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/berlin.jpg</landmark_image>
</city_report>
