<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "/Users/lauratonsi/ELABORAZIONE/data/city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="63.2">
  <metadata>
    <title>Lisbon</title>
    <name_it>Lisbona</name_it>
    <flag>🇵🇹</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>8</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>111.93</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="70.2"/>
    <environment green_score="68"/>
    <cost_index value="60.5"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="39.5"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>La città vanta un trasporto pubblico efficiente: la metropolitana per le lunghe distanze, e i caratteristici tram, essenziali per muoversi tra i ripidi quartieri storici.</transport>
  <accommodation>
    <hotel>
      <name>Beira Minho</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Bom Conforto Casa de Hospedes</name>
      <price>€20 singles</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Hotel Avenida Palace</name>
      <price>Expensive</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Goodnight Backpackers Hostel</name>
      <price>€18-20</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Pensão Norte</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
  </accommodation>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="38.6916" lon="-9.2159">
      <name>Belem Tower</name>
      <description>Fortified tower symbolizing the Age of Discovery.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.6979" lon="-9.2067">
      <name>Jeronimos Monastery</name>
      <description>Former monastery of the Order of Saint Jerome.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.7121" lon="-9.1303">
      <name>Alfama District</name>
      <description>Oldest district with narrow streets and Fado houses.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.7139" lon="-9.1334">
      <name>Sao Jorge Castle</name>
      <description>Moorish castle overlooking the historic center.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.7075" lon="-9.1364">
      <name>Praca do Comercio</name>
      <description>Large harbor-side square, one of Lisbon's main landmarks.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.7121" lon="-9.1394">
      <name>Santa Justa Lift</name>
      <description>Neo-Gothic vertical elevator connecting city levels.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.7635" lon="-9.0937">
      <name>Oceanarium</name>
      <description>Major aquarium located in the Parque das Nações.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.713" lon="-9.144">
      <name>Bairro Alto</name>
      <description>Central district known for shopping and vibrant nightlife.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.7032" lon="-9.1795">
      <name>LX Factory</name>
      <description>Creative hub in a former industrial complex.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="38.6936" lon="-9.2057">
      <name>Padrão dos Descobrimenti</name>
      <description>Monument celebrating the Portuguese Age of Discovery.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Baixa</name>
      <description>Baixa is a district in Lisbon, Portugal. The Baixa has many squares and monuments, offering numerous photo opportunities. The area suffered devastating destruction in the Great Earthquake on All Saints' Day, 1 November 1755. Lisbon's "downtown" was rebuilt under the guiding hand of the Marquis of Pombal (Marquês de Pombal), who introduced a grid street plan to organize the chaos. The Baixa is served by two Lisbon Metro lines: (Blue) and (Green). The two lines meet at Baixa–Chiado station, the system's deepest, at the junction of the Baixa district with the Chiado portion of the Bairro Alto district. Other Baixa stations are Martim Moniz, Restauradores, Rossio, and Terreiro do Paço. * 
* 
* 
* 
*
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
*  *  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
*  *
*
*
*
*
*
*
*</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Bairro Alto</name>
      <description>Bairro Alto is a district in Lisbon, Portugal. Beyond Bairro Alto itself, the district includes other neighbourhoods, notably Chiado and Príncipe Real. Bairro Alto is recognized for being Lisbon's centre of trendy, youthful dining and nightlife. Many high-end international shops can be found in Chiado and along Avenida da Liberdade, a wide, tree-lined boulevard. Three Lisbon Metro lines serve the district:
* — Marquês de Pombal, Rato
* — Marquês de Pombal, Avenida, Restauradores, Baixa–Chiado
* — Baixa–Chiado, Cais do Sodré Five tram routes pass through the district:  * 
* 
*
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*
*
*
* *  *
* * 
*
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
*  *  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*
*  *
*
*
*
*
*
*
*
*
*
*
* *
*
*  *
*
* 
* 
* 
*</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Alfama</name>
      <description>Alfama is a district in Lisbon, Portugal. The most popular and most fun way to travel into and through Alfama is on the and trams.
* 
*  * 
*
* 
* 
*
*
* 
* 
* *  *  * All these are around the Castelo de S. Jorge: * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
*  *  * 
* 
*  *
*
*
*
* 
* 
*</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Belém</name>
      <description>Belém is a district in Lisbon, Portugal. Take bus 728 to the west (direction Restelo), which follows the coast line and provides an express service with few stops. Or take the Cascais suburban train (line Cascais todos or Oeiras; the express trains don't stop in Belém) to Belém and walk to the attractions. Tram to the west (Algés direction) follows the Junqueira residential line. Check the route map inside the tram: it helps to find the right station for the most famous of Belém attractions. The extensive bus network also serves Belém from various departure points around the city and can be less busy than the tram. To reach the waterfront attractions such as Belem Tower and Padrão dos Descobrimentos from the town centre/tram line, you must cross over the railway line by the footbridges – there is one at the railway station and another near Belem Tower, and a tunnel by the Monument to the Discoverers. This monument-packed area is a must-see place, and it contains Lisbon's two s: the Belém Tower and the Jerónimos Monastery. * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*
* 
* 
* 
*  *  * 
* 
* 
* 
*  *  * 
* 
* 
*
*</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Parque das Nações</name>
      <description>Parque das Nações is a district in Lisbon, Portugal. The "Park of the Nations" was built from scratch for Expo '98 (1998 Lisbon World Exposition) in the northeastern end of Lisbon. After the Expo, many of the impressive constructions and decorations were kept, while new residential, commercial, and office buildings were added to form a thriving, mixed-use district consisting exclusively of modern architecture and making the most of its river-facing location by offering a number of leisure facilities. Metro line ("red", though it's pink on signage) runs cross-town to Parque das Nações, Oriente railway and bus station, and the airport. From the historic centre take the green line north and change at Alameda.   is Lisbon's principal transport hub, designed by Santiago Calatrava for Expo '98. All trains and buses call here, though some trains start downtown at Santa Apolónia. Level 0 is the plaza through the building's main arch. Level 1 has ticket kiosks and machines plus cafes and Level 2 has the platforms. Level -1 is retail, Level -2 is the Metro station with platforms on Level -3.  The taxi rank is west side, then the bus stands are just beyond. Not much here apart from the stands, as you use the facilities in the main building. No timetables, ticketing or departure info, again use the main building.  * 
* 
* 
*
* * 
* 
*  * * 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
*</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Capital of hospitality and light, Lisbon has become a haven for digital nomads thanks to its climate and affordable costs. Its electric mobility plan is transforming the historic hills into a model of sustainable tourism.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Lisbon (Portuguese: Lisboa) is the capital of Portugal situated on seven hills at the wide mouth of the river Tagus (Tejo) where it meets the Atlantic Ocean. With 545,000 residents in the city and 3.0 million in the Lisbon Region (2024) and a thriving mix of Portugal's rich history and vivid contemporary culture, Lisbon enchants travellers with its white bleached limestone buildings, intimate alleyways, and an easy going charm that makes it a popular year round destination. Greater Lisbon comprises many other splendid tourist destinations such as the of Sintra, the seaside resorts of Estoril, Cascais, the world class museums, or Almada famous for its hilltop Cristo Rei statue, all of which are connected with Lisbon by excellent public transportation links. Lisbon is built on seven hills, so getting around Lisbon can be a workout. Many slopes and few really flat areas is one of Lisbon's trademarks. This is also a city of enchanting contrasts: The elegant squares, broad avenues, monumental buildings and rectangular layout of the lower areas quickly gives way to the hilly, narrow, winding, unpredictable and cramped streets of districts such as Alfama and Bairro Alto. The elegant dining rooms and smart rooftop bars of expensive hotels seems like a different world compared to the excellent restaurants disguised behind an inconspicuous façade in a modest Bairro Alto street. Quality patisseries and restaurants thrive side by side with late night bars and noisy discos. The old, tiny squeaky trams (one of the city's trademarks) are no less of a contrast to the efficient metro network. The Portuguese capital is often perceived as less frantic than other million cities, and traffic and barkers are less aggressive than in many other tourist destinations. According to legend, Lisbon was founded by the mythical Greek hero Odysseus, during his travels home from Troy. However, most historians believe that the city was founded around 1200 BC by Phoenician settlers, utilizing the calm and fresh waters of Tagus river and the proximity to the sea. The Phoenician name of the city is Alis-Ubo, meaning "safe harbour". Eventually it became part of the Carthaginian Empire. After the Punic Wars, it became the main trading hub of the Roman province Lusitania, under the name Felicitas Julia Olisipo, later Olisipona. During the decline and fall of the western Roman Empire, the Iberian peninsula was invaded by Vandal and Visigothic tribes. In 711, Lisbon was captured by Muslim forces. During this period, the Castle of São Jorge was expanded. Much of the Moorish heritage is preserved in the nearby Alfama, the oldest standing district of the city. In 1147, a Crusader army en route to the Holy Land helped King Afonso I conquer Lisbon and return it to Christian rule. After the completion of the Portuguese Reconquista some hundred years later, Lisbon was made the capital of Portugal. The Golden Age of Portugal, and consequently Lisbon's history, started in the 15th century.</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/lisbon.jpg</landmark_image>
  <nightlife>
    <venue lat="38.7043089" lon="-9.1749231">
      <name>3D</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="38.7116311" lon="-9.144132">
      <name>A Tasca do Chico</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="38.6809443" lon="-9.1539133">
      <name>A Tentadora</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="38.7105866" lon="-9.1401197">
      <name>Apprazível</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="38.7054835" lon="-9.1473475">
      <name>B'leza</name>
      <category>nightclub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="38.7128224" lon="-9.1437112">
      <name>Bar Arché Cohiba</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="38.7352581" lon="-9.1555128">
      <name>Bar Charh</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="38.7100003" lon="-9.1451806">
      <name>Bicaense</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
  </nightlife>
</city_report>
