<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "/Users/lauratonsi/ELABORAZIONE/data/city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="69.0">
  <metadata>
    <title>Oslo</title>
    <name_it>Oslo</name_it>
    <flag>🇳🇴</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>0</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>165.02</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="75.1"/>
    <environment green_score="92"/>
    <cost_index value="89.2"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="10.8"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>Flytoget (Airport Express Train), operates high speed express trains, generally taking 19-22 minutes to reach Oslo Central Station (Oslo S). Trains to Oslo Central Station depart every 10 minutes on weekdays from 07.00 to 23.10, Sundays from 11.30 to 23.10, and every 20 minutes at other times (04.40-06.50 and 23.10-00.50 everyday, 07.20-11.20 Sundays, and all-day during Saturdays and bank holidays). Every 20 minutes from 05.30 to 00.50, the train also calls at Lillestrøm and continues past Oslo S to Drammen, stopping at Nationaltheatret station, which is more convenient for destinations in the western end of the city .</transport>
  <accommodation/>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="59.9271" lon="10.7008">
      <name>Vigeland Park</name>
      <description>Large park with sculptures by Gustav Vigeland.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9075" lon="10.7533">
      <name>Opera House</name>
      <description>Modern architectural landmark with a walkable roof.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9064" lon="10.7361">
      <name>Akershus Fortress</name>
      <description>Medieval castle built to protect and provide a royal residence.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9036" lon="10.6994">
      <name>Fram Museum</name>
      <description>Museum dedicated to Norwegian polar exploration.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9641" lon="10.6675">
      <name>Holmenkollen</name>
      <description>Ski jumping hill and museum.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9044" lon="10.7553">
      <name>Munch Museum</name>
      <description>Museum dedicated to the life and works of Edvard Munch.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9036" lon="10.6983">
      <name>Kon-Tiki Museum</name>
      <description>Museum housing vessels from Thor Heyerdahl's expeditions.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9161" lon="10.7375">
      <name>National Gallery</name>
      <description>Home to Norway's largest collection of art (The Scream).</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9122" lon="10.7336">
      <name>City Hall</name>
      <description>Iconic building hosting the Nobel Peace Prize ceremony.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.9136" lon="10.7397">
      <name>Karl Johans Gate</name>
      <description>The main street of Oslo connecting the station and palace.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Sentrum</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Oslo.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>West</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Oslo.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Inner North</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Oslo.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Inner East</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Oslo.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>North</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Oslo.</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>World capital of electric mobility, Oslo is surrounded by forests and fjords that extend into the city center. It represents the pinnacle of environmental sustainability combined with rock-solid economic stability.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Oslo is Norway's capital and largest city, with 700,000 citizens in the city proper and about 1.5 million inhabitants in greater Oslo. It is in the East of the country in the Oslofjorden fjord, extending over an inlet of the Skagerrak strait. It is spaciously laid out and surrounded by green hills and mountains and includes 40 islands and 343 lakes. Oslo offers ski slopes for alpine skiing and ski trails for cross-country skiing in the winter. In the summer, the temperature in Oslo may make it comfortable to swim. There are several well-visited beach resorts. Oslo is one of the world's northernmost capitals and so gets only 6 hours of sunlight in the winter. In high summer, sunlight hours soar to 18, making its climate markedly different between seasons, with cold yet relatively dry winters. A relatively compact city squeezed into a thin strip of land along the shoreline, Oslo prides itself as one of the world's most sustainable cities. Central parts of the city are compact, but Oslo as a whole is relatively spacious. While it holds an array of historic monuments, Oslo is perhaps most famous for its modern architecture, including striking and daring projects launched at the turn of the millennium. Oslo's economy is powered by the maritime industry, high-tech and clean energy sectors. In 2010, Oslo was ranked as the world's most expensive city to live in by the Swiss wealth management company UBS AG, but has fallen to 27th place on Mercers ranking in 2022. Oslo is Norway's...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/oslo.jpg</landmark_image>
  <nightlife>
    <venue lat="59.9274649" lon="10.7510975">
      <name>Alf nabolagsbar</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.9236161" lon="10.7573918">
      <name>Bar Bellini</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.9252056" lon="10.7593699">
      <name>Bar Boca</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.9105204" lon="10.7261726">
      <name>Beer Palace</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.9141" lon="10.738227">
      <name>Brødrene Bergh</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.9297631" lon="10.7803576">
      <name>Buen Bar</name>
      <category>bar</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.9127213" lon="10.7734065">
      <name>Bydelskroa</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.9168848" lon="10.7532829">
      <name>Cacadou</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
  </nightlife>
</city_report>
