<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="62.5">
  <metadata>
    <title>Riga</title>
    <name_it>Riga</name_it>
    <flag>🇱🇻</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>0</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>103.23</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="62.1"/>
    <environment green_score="72"/>
    <cost_index value="55.8"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="44.2"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>Bus route 22 runs between the airport and the old town, with a stop near the central bus and railway stations as well as old town. These buses operate as any other public transport in Riga; see Riga#Get_around for more information on riding the buses. The journey to the old town takes 30-40 minutes.</transport>
  <accommodation/>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="56.9491" lon="24.1053">
      <name>Old Town</name>
      <description>Historical heart of Riga with cobblestone streets.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9472" lon="24.1069">
      <name>House of Blackheads</name>
      <description>Historic building reconstructed after WWII.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9514" lon="24.1131">
      <name>Freedom Monument</name>
      <description>Memorial honoring soldiers killed in the War of Independence.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9475" lon="24.1094">
      <name>St. Peter's Church</name>
      <description>Gothic church with an observation tower.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9439" lon="24.1158">
      <name>Central Market</name>
      <description>Large market in former Zeppelin hangars.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9592" lon="24.1089">
      <name>Art Nouveau District</name>
      <description>Area with the highest concentration of Art Nouveau architecture.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9539" lon="24.1158">
      <name>Nativity Cathedral</name>
      <description>The largest Orthodox cathedral in the city.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9556" lon="24.1131">
      <name>Latvian National Museum</name>
      <description>Art museum in a magnificent historicist building.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9511" lon="24.1064">
      <name>Swedish Gate</name>
      <description>The only remaining gate from the old city walls.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="56.9714" lon="24.2272">
      <name>Motor Museum</name>
      <description>Museum with a large collection of antique vehicles.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Vecrīga</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Riga.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Centrs</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Riga.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Outer East Bank</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Riga.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Pārdaugava</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Riga.</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Perla del Baltico famosa per l'Art Nouveau, Riga offre spazi verdi immensi e una crescente scena tecnologica. La sua accessibilità economica la rende una scelta strategica per giovani professionisti e viaggiatori consapevoli.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Riga is the financial, creative, and cultural centre of Latvia. It is the capital and the largest city in Latvia, it is also the second largest city in the Baltic States after the Lithuanian capital Vilnius. The city lies on the Gulf of Riga, at the mouth of Daugava, Riga has a population of approximately 640,000 inhabitants, or 1/3 of the population of Latvia. The city was part of many empires throughout history, each of which has left its mark on the city. It is famous for Art Nouveau and wooden architecture. Riga's historical centre is listed as a UNESCO World Heritage site. There are many administrative districts in Riga. However, almost all tourist attractions, historic buildings and hotels are contained within the borders of the relatively small and walkable Centra rajons district, which is made up of Vecrīga (the old town) and Centrs (the modern-day business district). However if you have already seen the more famous attractions in the city centre, the outer districts do have their own draws too. On both sides of the mouth of Daugava river, the Gulf of Riga offers extensive sandy seaside beaches, which can be reached by city bus or train. A nude beach can be found a 15-minute walk out of Vecāķi. Riga is famous for its world heritage-listed old town (Vecrīga) and city centre (Centrs), in which over 800 buildings — a third of all buildings — are of the Art Nouveau (aka Jugendstil) style of architecture and thus Riga is one of the best destinations to see this...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/riga.jpg</landmark_image>
</city_report>
