<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="48.4">
  <metadata>
    <title>Rome</title>
    <name_it>Roma</name_it>
    <flag>🇮🇹</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>3</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>132.28</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="46.8"/>
    <environment green_score="60"/>
    <cost_index value="71.5"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="28.5"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>Testaccio is a short walk from the metro station and Circus Maximus also has its own metro station on the rome line (Circo Massimo). Near Piramide Metro station is Ostiense railway station, with regular connections to and from Fiumicino Airport. From Piramide you can also get trains to Ostia.</transport>
  <accommodation>
    <hotel>
      <name>Gazometro B&amp;amp;B Rome</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Hotels Aventine, San Anselmo and San Pio</name>
      <price>Prezzo N/D</price>
    </hotel>
    <hotel>
      <name>Testaccio Hotel, Sonder</name>
      <price>Single €99, double €121</price>
    </hotel>
  </accommodation>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="41.8902" lon="12.4922">
      <name>Colosseum</name>
      <description>The largest ancient amphitheatre ever built.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.8986" lon="12.4769">
      <name>Pantheon</name>
      <description>Ancient Roman temple with a massive dome.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9009" lon="12.4833">
      <name>Trevi Fountain</name>
      <description>Iconic Baronque fountain where tourists throw coins.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.8925" lon="12.4853">
      <name>Roman Forum</name>
      <description>Ruins of the heart of ancient Roman public life.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9065" lon="12.4548">
      <name>Vatican Museums</name>
      <description>Art museums including the Sistine Chapel.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9022" lon="12.4539">
      <name>St. Peter's Basilica</name>
      <description>Major Renaissance church in Vatican City.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.8992" lon="12.4731">
      <name>Piazza Navona</name>
      <description>Square built on an ancient stadium with Bernini fountains.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9059" lon="12.4828">
      <name>Spanish Steps</name>
      <description>Famous monumental stairway of 135 steps.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9031" lon="12.4663">
      <name>Castel Sant'Angelo</name>
      <description>Hadrian's mausoleum converted into a papal fortress.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="41.9142" lon="12.4921">
      <name>Borghese Gallery</name>
      <description>Museum in a villa housing Bernini and Caravaggio.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Aventino-Testaccio</name>
      <description>Aventino and Testaccio are neighbourhoods of Rome. Aventino is named for the hill which rises up near the Tiber river and is one of the legendary seven hills of Rome. Diagonally opposite at the end of Circus Maximus is the Celian Hill, another of the seven hills.
Testaccio is an area to the southwest of Aventino along the bank of the Tiber and is named for the eighth hill of Rome, a man made hill that was built from discarded pot amphorae (testae) in Roman times. In Testaccio you can find great traditional Roman restaurants, and at night the zone is filled with discos. Easy access to Aventino from most areas of Rome. From Termini area take a bus to Piazza Venezia and walk from there to reach Piazza Bocca della Verità. Testaccio is a short walk from the metro station and Circus Maximus also has its own metro station on the line (Circo Massimo). Near Piramide Metro station is Ostiense railway station, with regular connections to and from Fiumicino Airport. From Piramide you can also get trains to Ostia. * 
* *
*  *
* 
*
*
*
* 
* 
* 
* 
*  * 
*  * 
*  *
* 
*  * There is usually a temporary food stall near the keyhole (see above) on the Aventino. But the best bet is to buy some food at a shop before you arrive and have a picnic at one of the parks on the Aventino overlooking the Tiber and the city. Volpetti at Via Marmorata 47 has a wide selection of prosciutto, salami, olives and cheeses. Perfect for a picnic. Alternatively, the three bars along the west side of the Viale...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Colosseo</name>
      <description>The Colosseo district is the heart of ancient Rome and the Roman Empire. It has the Colosseum, the Forum, and the Capitoline Museum. Via dei Fori Imperiali cuts through the centre of the Rome/Colosseo district, connecting Piazza Venezia with the Colosseum. It is well served by buses, although if you are into serious sightseeing you are likely to want to walk instead as the Roman Forum is on your right for most of the journey. After the Colosseum, the road becomes Via Labicana and takes you close to San Giovanni. Buses serving Via dei Fori Imperiali include No. 75, which connects Termini Station with Aventino- Testaccio and No. 85, which connects Piazza San Silvestro in the Modern Center (close to the Trevi Fountain) with San Giovanni. The metro station is two stops from Termini station in the direction of EUR. It will also be a stop for the new, and very much delayed, Line , and the Colosseum end of the Via dei Fori Imperiali is made unattractive by the construction site. *  *  *  * 
** 
** 
** 
** 
** 
** 
** 
** 
** 
**  When visiting the Colosseum in late spring, summer, or early fall, it is not unusual to see long lines at the entrance, where the admission fee is €18. The ticket is valid for 24 hours (updated September 2024) and includes admission to the Roman Forum, Palatine Hill, and the Colosseum. It is possible to purchase an admission to the Palatine Hill (or the Roman Forum) for the same sum, which also provides direct access to the Colosseum via an automated...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Esquilino-San Giovanni</name>
      <description>Esquilino and San Giovanni are adjacent neighborhoods in Rome. Esquilino is named for the Esquiline hill on which it stands. It lies south of the Termini station and is centred more or less on the Piazza Vittorio Emmanuele II. It is now partly a Chinese immigrant neighbourhood, and specialty groceries and shoe stores abound. San Giovanni is named after the Basilica, which is the Roman Catholic cathedral of Rome. The area is south-east of the Esquiline. Metro Line A connects station with the basilica of San Giovanni. There are also several buses from the downtown area, best caught at Piazza Venezia or at station by the Colosseum, where you can connect with Metro Line B. Porta Maggiore can be considered the tram hub of Rome, with four of the city's six remaining tram lines passing through. As such, any place in Rome that has a tram stop is connected to Porta Maggiore directly or with just one transfer. * 
* 
*  * 
* 
*  * Movies are shown and some performances are held for free in Piazza Vittorio during the summer. *  There are a lot of Chinese and Indian restaurants, but you will also find many typical trattorie. * 
*
*
*  * 
* 
* 
*  * 
* * Rome/Nomentano &amp;amp;mdash; for the nearby Porta Maggiore</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Modern Centre</name>
      <description>The Modern Centre of Rome, home to the Via Veneto, Quirinale, Castro Pretorio, Repubblica, and Trevi neighbourhoods, is the city's hub of activity, especially shopping and nightlife. It's also home to a huge assortment of hotels, and it's likely that you'll be staying here, despite the fact that most of Rome's historic attractions are elsewhere. The Modern Centre of Rome is not hard to find as the Termini Station brings you into the west edge of it. As you leave the station, the Castro Pretorio neighbourhood is to your right, with many smaller hotels. To the left the main roads of Via Cavour and Via Nazionale lead down the hill. Larger hotels here, catering more for groups than independent travellers. Termini Station is a major bus hub with buses to all parts of town. Beware taxi drivers who operate at the station as it seems to attract the most crooked ones. Get a cab from the rank and ignore the drivers who solicit you outside the station. Always insist that you see the meter is turned on after you get into the cab. No matter what time of day or night the starting price should never be more than €6 (during the day less) and a figure 1 on the meter should indicate that the correct rate is being applied. A legitimate extra fee of €2 is levied for all rides beginning at the station. *
* 
* *
*
* 
*
* 
*  *
* 
* 
*
*
* 
*  *
* For a little bit of shopping, the Via Nazionale is perfect: souvenirs, clothes, Italian shoes, etc. But the main attraction is without a doubt, the Via...</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Nomentano</name>
      <description>Nomentano is a district of Rome. The San Lorenzo neighborhood is a student area south-east of Rome's main train station (Termini). It has a small street market (food, clothing), unpretentious caffès and is a major centre of Rome's night life. The Nomentano area is easily reachable by bus from Termini Station (90) from Piazza Venezia or via Nazionale (60) or by Metro Line (stops: Castro Pretorio, Policlinico, Piazza Bologna, Tiburtina). *  * * Drinking in the open. Do what Romans (students in particular) do: buy a cheap beer in one of the countless bar around and just hang out or stroll, observing people and enjoying the mildness of a Roman evening. *
* * 
*  * 
* 
* 
*  *</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Città eterna dalla bellezza stratificata, Roma sta affrontando la sfida della modernizzazione nel rispetto dei suoi vincoli archeologici. Il suo fascino monumentale resta un asset insostituibile nel panorama mondiale.</description>
  <wiki_intro>North Central Rome is a district that covers the areas around Piazza di Spagna, Piazza del Popolo and Parioli, as well as the magnificent Villa Borghese and its gardens. Further out the area is bordered by Via Nomentana and the River Tiber and includes the area of Salario. Spagna lies in the northern part of the central city, to the west of the park of the Villa Borghese. It includes the Piazza di Spagna and the famous Spanish Steps. It is one of the most fashionable and well-heeled districts of the Italian capital. Parioli is a quiet, affluent and elegant Rome neighborhood close to Villa Borghese. The name originates from a gigantic wall called "parietone". Salario, just to the northwest of the Modern Center and the Villa Borghese, is another elegant, upscale neighborhood, home to a large and beautiful park, Villa Ada. Trieste is also a quiet affluent and elegant neighborhood, close to the Parioli and Villa Ada. It is full of Fascist architecture and early Christian churches such as Sant’Agnese Fuori Le Mura. This is still the centre of Rome. It is served by the metro stations (Piazza di Spagna: Spanish Steps and Borghese Gardens) and . Piazza di San Silvestro, which is a short walk from the Spanish Steps, is a terminal for many bus lines. *
*  * * 
*  * *  * 
*  * 
* 
*  *
* 
*  * 
* 
*  *  * 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* *  * 
* 
* 
*  * Rent a boat and take a row on the lake in the Borghese Gardens.
* The streets to the west of the Spanish Steps, such as Via dei Condotti, house...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/rome.jpg</landmark_image>
</city_report>
