<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "/Users/lauratonsi/ELABORAZIONE/data/city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="60.9">
  <metadata>
    <title>Stockholm</title>
    <name_it>Stoccolma</name_it>
    <flag>🇸🇪</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>0</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>147.63</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="54.2"/>
    <environment green_score="88"/>
    <cost_index value="79.8"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="20.2"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>The most practical option is the airport coaches to the City Terminal in Stockholm (80 min; 199 kr online). A sometimes cheaper option is to take the local bus 515 or 715 to Nyköping's rail station (alight at Nyköping Centralstation), from where SJ regional trains (timetable, direct services run to stations marked in white) on the Norrköping–Nyköping–Stockholm route connect to Stockholm (from 100 kr, cheaper on select days). Tickets can be bought the following two ways: Buy an SL combined ticket from Skavsta to Stockholm, valid on both the local bus and the regional train.</transport>
  <accommodation/>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="59.3281" lon="18.0914">
      <name>Vasa Museum</name>
      <description>Maritime museum with a salvaged 17th-century ship.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3251" lon="18.0708">
      <name>Gamla Stan</name>
      <description>The well-preserved medieval old town.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3275" lon="18.0544">
      <name>City Hall</name>
      <description>Building with a tower hosting the Nobel Banquet.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3253" lon="18.1039">
      <name>Skansen</name>
      <description>The world's oldest open-air museum and zoo.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3249" lon="18.0965">
      <name>ABBA Museum</name>
      <description>Interactive museum dedicated to the pop group.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3268" lon="18.0717">
      <name>Royal Palace</name>
      <description>The official residence of the Swedish monarch.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3261" lon="18.0847">
      <name>Moderna Museet</name>
      <description>State museum for modern and contemporary art.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3217" lon="17.8869">
      <name>Drottningholm</name>
      <description>The private residence of the Swedish royal family.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3178" lon="18.0858">
      <name>Fotografiska</name>
      <description>Major center for contemporary photography.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="59.3233" lon="18.0964">
      <name>Gröna Lund</name>
      <description>Historic amusement park on the island of Djurgården.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Gamla Stan</name>
      <description>The medieval old town on its own island, the historic heart of Stockholm.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Södermalm</name>
      <description>The hip and creative district with cafés, markets and panoramic views.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Östermalm</name>
      <description>The elegant neighbourhood with the Östermalm Market Hall and embassies.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Norrmalm</name>
      <description>The commercial and cultural hub, home to the central railway station.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Kungsholmen</name>
      <description>An island district featuring City Hall (Stadshuset) and quiet residential areas.</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Spread across fourteen islands, Stockholm embodies Scandinavian elegance and functional design. Its dedication to water cleanliness and urban safety makes it a model of social efficiency.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Stockholm is Sweden's capital and largest city, with nearly a million inhabitants in the city, and 2.4 million within Stockholm County (as of 2021). The inner city is made up of 14 islands across Lake Mälaren and three streams into the brackish Baltic Sea, with the Stockholm archipelago with some 24,000 islands, islets and skerries. Over 30% of the city area is made up of waterways, and another 30% is made up of green areas. Air and water are said to be the freshest of any European capital. Stockholm hosts the Nobel Prize ceremony and has around 70 museums. Stockholm is the hub of most Swedish rail and bus traffic and has two of the country's busiest airports nearby, so it is a good starting point for visiting other parts of Sweden. Stockholm's suburbs sprawl out across most of Stockholm County. Stockholm's administrative division may be perplexing - municipal borders might cut right through neighbourhoods. This article describes areas that are geographically close and easy to visit together as districts; the administrative borders of districts and municipalities may differ. The outer parts of the county consist of Norrtälje, Sigtuna, Norrort, Stockholm Archipelago, Södertörn and Södertälje. Due to the post-glacial rebound, Stockholm is slowly rising from the sea. Mälaren was a bay of the Baltic Sea throughout the Viking Age of the 9th and 10th centuries; today's Stockholm was the waterway for the first Swedish cities; Birka, Uppsala, and Sigtuna. As Sigtuna was sacked by pirates in AD&amp;amp;nbsp;1187, the Swedes needed to fortify the strait. As the rising land cut off Mälaren from the sea in the 13th century, Stockholm became an important trading post. The city is said to be founded by Birger jarl (jarl is a title corresponding to British earl), who had a fortress built on an island later known as Gamla Stan. The first known written records that mention Stockholm date from 1252; this is the considered year of foundation. In the 15th century Stockholm replaced Uppsala as the effective capital. Stockholm was an associate of the Hanseatic League, and since its liberation from Denmark by King Gustav Vasa in 1523, Stockholm has remained Sweden's most important center of commerce, although Gothenburg later became the largest international port. During the 17th century, Stockholm was the base of the Swedish Empire, with a land area twice the country's current size, nearly encircling the Baltic Sea. Much of the inner city plan was laid out in the 19th century, and the inner city still contains buildings from all ages since the 15th century. Like the rest of Sweden, Stockholm was largely untouched by the World Wars, but, particularly between 1955 and 1975, hundreds of old buildings in Norrmalm were demolished in a large-scale modernization process, emulating similar projects in other European cities. Since 1901, Stockholm has hosted the annual Nobel Prize ceremony for all categories except the peace prize, which is handed out in Oslo.</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/stockholm.jpg</landmark_image>
  <nightlife>
    <venue lat="59.3198089" lon="18.0688539">
      <name>Akkurat</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.3403556" lon="18.0311352">
      <name>Bagpipers's Inn</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.3340492" lon="18.0565703">
      <name>Bar City Central</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.3327653" lon="18.0581755">
      <name>Belgobaren</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.3321771" lon="18.0738967">
      <name>Berns</name>
      <category>nightclub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.3098213" lon="18.0758442">
      <name>Brother Tuck</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.3333991" lon="18.0557611">
      <name>Fasching</name>
      <category>nightclub</category>
    </venue>
    <venue lat="59.333999" lon="18.037233">
      <name>Flying Scotsman Inn</name>
      <category>pub</category>
    </venue>
  </nightlife>
</city_report>
