<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE city_report SYSTEM "city_report.dtd">
<city_report appeal_score="67.9">
  <metadata>
    <title>Vienna</title>
    <name_it>Vienna</name_it>
    <flag>🇦🇹</flag>
  </metadata>
  <indicators>
    <hotel_count>0</hotel_count>
    <hotel_price>142.27</hotel_price>
    <safety index_score="73.2"/>
    <environment green_score="85"/>
    <cost_index value="76.9"/>
    <economic_accessibility score="23.1"/>
  </indicators>
  <transport>Vienna International Airport Vienna International Airport Vienna International Airport url email address lat48.110278 long16.569722 directionsjust outside the city limits of Vienna on the far side of the City of Schwechat phone tollfree hours price wikipediaVienna International Airport image2011-06-14 10-23-53 Austria Niederösterreich Fischamend Markt.jpg wikidataQ32999 lastedit2025-07-26 contentTo get to Vienna, you have three different railway options. The cheaper but slower S-Bahn line S7 (24 minutes; €4.60) and the more expensive but faster City Airport Train (15 minutes; from €11) both go to Wien-Mitte/Landstraße.</transport>
  <accommodation/>
  <highlights>
    <attraction lat="48.1845" lon="16.3122">
      <name>Schönbrunn Palace</name>
      <description>Grand Baroque palace and former summer residence.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.2084" lon="16.3731">
      <name>St. Stephen's</name>
      <description>Iconic Gothic cathedral in the city center.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.1915" lon="16.3808">
      <name>Belvedere</name>
      <description>Historic complex with two Baroque palaces and art.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.2166" lon="16.3958">
      <name>Prater</name>
      <description>Large public park with a giant Ferris wheel.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.2065" lon="16.3653">
      <name>Hofburg</name>
      <description>Former imperial palace of the Habsburgs.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.203" lon="16.3691">
      <name>State Opera</name>
      <description>One of the leading opera houses in the world.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.1973" lon="16.361">
      <name>Naschmarkt</name>
      <description>Famous open-air market for food and goods.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.2047" lon="16.3681">
      <name>Albertina</name>
      <description>Art museum with one of the world's largest print rooms.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.2037" lon="16.3617">
      <name>Kunsthistorisches</name>
      <description>Imperial museum of art and artifacts.</description>
    </attraction>
    <attraction lat="48.2109" lon="16.3575">
      <name>Rathaus</name>
      <description>Neogothic city hall building and event square.</description>
    </attraction>
  </highlights>
  <districts>
    <district>
      <name>Innere Stadt</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Vienna.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Landstraße</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Vienna.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Wieden</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Vienna.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Margareten</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Vienna.</description>
    </district>
    <district>
      <name>Mariahilf</name>
      <description>Quartiere di Vienna.</description>
    </district>
  </districts>
  <description>Costantemente premiata come città più vivibile al mondo, Vienna eccelle nell'edilizia sociale e nel trasporto pubblico. Il suo equilibrio tra cultura imperiale e modernità sostenibile è la sua firma distintiva.</description>
  <wiki_intro>Vienna (German: Wien; Austro-Bavarian: Wean) is the capital of Austria and by far its most populous city, with an urban population of 2 million and a metropolitan population of 2.9 million (2023). It is the country's artistic, cultural, economic and political centre. It is known for its high living standards, relaxed yet elegant lifestyle and rich musical life. Vienna, renowned as the former seat of the Habsburg court and its diverse empires, stands not only as a grand metropolis but also as a historical center that has perpetually thrived with a substantial population. This city's distinction lies in its privileged stature, fostering an environment that has nurtured numerous eminent artists, notably Beethoven, Haydn, Liszt, Mozart, Schubert, and Johann Strauss II, among others. It was long the largest German-speaking city in the world before being surpassed by Berlin. The large historic city centre of Vienna filled with monuments to its imperial past is inscribed on the UNESCO World Heritage List. Vienna is broadly divided in inner (1–9) and outer districts (10–23). The 23 districts or wards each have a name and a number. They vary immensely in size and each has its own flair. These function subordinately to the city as decentralized administrative branches of the commune, and make local decisions. Wikivoyage has divided the 23 official districts of Vienna into 13 here for travel purposes. The low-lying Danube plain in and around what is now Vienna has had a human...</wiki_intro>
  <landmark_image>assets/images/vienna.jpg</landmark_image>
</city_report>
